Welcome back to grease pencil time
Yeahgrease pencil is so exciting
Grease pencil is amazing re-standing it was something that I had seen people use around
but I was like
ohsounds so difficult
but actually it's not that difficult
Let's kind of I'm going to get rid of the plane of the background for a second and I'm going to get rid of that reference just so we can see what's happening with wrist
So I'm gonna be looking at it from the front
I have my doggie there and I'm gon na add and you see here with grease pencil
Here you are
we have a few different ones
we have blank stroke monkey C
an art collection
and art and object line art
We're going to cover them all at some point or another
but for now
the one we're going use the most is blank
So blank is gonna add a grease pencil object to the scene with nothing applied
So when I added the blank there
my grease pencil is called G pencil
I'm going to have to decide where I'm going to draw
For now
let's imagine that we're going to draw one of our plants
So I'm going to say plant one
So I have my plant one that is going to be my grease pencil
and grease pencil has materials
but they look a bit different
You see
as soon as we generate a grease pencil
it comes with a material called black
So we already know that we're going to be using the color black and it has activated stroke
but not fill
So in order to paint in grease pencil
right now we are not in painting mode
we're gon na have to
we could do it just by going here and selecting drill mode
but there is an especially select a created tab that Blender has done for us for grease pencil
but it's hidden
You need to go here in plus to the animation and add that to the animation tab
And as soon as you do it
you are back in this 2D animation and you see that we are there into the animation and one of the things I don't like is that the 2D animation puts the lighting from the same world
I'm going to deactivate it
I'm going to put the lighting that we had before
I love this warm lighting
I love how it looks when I rotate it
so it looks like it's similar to the other one
and I like it because kind of we're having parallelisms between the two worlds
Now we're going to press the Y because we're looking at the world from the from the front
and you see that I have my deep plant selected
I have a pencil there
suggest I'm painting on that layer
and let's see what things that we have in here
If we click here
we have different types of brushes
we have airbrushed ink pen
different ink pens
We're going to be providing as well different brushes
But this one's I having enough with them
It's amazing how much you can do with them
Let's see what happens if I paint
So I'm gon na
just go around with this one already I have painted something in the air
which is pretty amazing and not only I painted something in the air happens in something in the air that has a bit of a 3D nest to it
Like you see
like when I look at it from the side
it's still having a bit of volume
And what I painted here
the cool thing is that it can be modified
it's a bit confusing because Greece
Spencerpeople think that it's Photoshop
but in reality that it's something a bit more like Illustrator
So we change now front rower mode to
for example
sculpt mode
We have a new different mode in which I'm not assuming that you can see that there is a line that is defined in this entire shape and actually that line is made of little points
We'll see it later
But for example
I have in my sculpt bolt smoothen
and if I smooth
let's see what happens when I smooth it out
my entire shape now gets smoother
you see it's getting smooth
or I can pinch it
I can just select my radius and I can modify and modify my shape
I can make even do it in 3D
so now I'm painting in 3D
this is crazy that you can do this
not only that
you can do it like that
you can do frame by frame animation with a 3D shape
floating in the air
absolutely bonkers when I discovered I was like
ohmy goodness
this is just the best thing ever
and if I go to edit mode
you can see the reality of it all
you can select some of this and you can see that in reality
this shape is made of these little tiny points that are all connected to one another and the fact that these little tiny points are there has many advantages
for example
I can select these points and I can go here to my radius and I can change the radius of my points to make them bigger
and you see that now there's no gradient between them
but today we learned another tool we learned this proportional editing tool
So now if I do that now I can make a change with the shape of my mouse and I can make it to grow in one area
I get thinner or another amazingly cool this as well
so you can really make lines
you were saying
ohthere'll be more brushes
but you can
but this you already got enough
you can do
yeahthere are all the brushes I'm gonna go back to the draw mode
and I'm gonna
for example
use this airbrus I love this one
it's generating this cloud in the air that it kind of works in 3D
you see it is a cloud that is all shaped in 3D
and again
thisthis cloud can be modified
you can smooth it out with my with this shape
I can pinch it
you know
can pinch this cloud in 3D and move it
and it all continues being in 3D with me
so just amazing stuff
we're going to be discovering so many techniques
we were saying as we were saying when we saw spider-man the amount of stuff
they had done with this was amazing
Ohsorry
I deleted everything
I didn't want to
I just want go
I wanted to go to sculp mode and use the eraser
so I'm gonna make it very big and just erase everything I made
Okay
so should we check
how do we do to draw one of the plants
we are going to activate my empty object and now sometimes I don't know why
sometimes I generate
I have some problems with the original materials that come here
sometimes I delete them and I start again when I'm generating my own material
And you need to understand one thing is the material
another thing is the drawing pen you're using
In reality I've been discovering that this pen is defining how those dots are being drawn
so some dots are being bigger and smaller
so in order to generate this irregularity
the program is generating bigger and smaller dots
but the color of those dots is dictated by the material
Right now we don't have any material
so it's completely white
But if I go here and I'm going to try to draw
for example
this plant
so in order to draw this plant I'm going to generate a new material
the first thing I'm going to do I want to make a material that is only stroke
So the two types of materials
filled materials and stroke materials
So the stroke material is the one like we use in Photoshop that generates a stroke
And I'm going to just draw next to it
I'm going to draw it there and I'm gon na have something that looks a bit like that plant is not very good
I'm gon na be trying to be a bit more smooth
Keep in mind I'm using my mouse
we have a tablet
but I want people to know that this can be done with the mouse
By the way
where I'm drawing is dictated here
right now I'm drawing at the stroke origin and I'm looking at it from the front view
And I like that because now drawing this origin
we're going to be looking at more modes
but for now
this is good
So now that we learned that we make that shape
that's good
and now we're going to go into my edit mode and I'm going to select the points at the very top and we have the proportional editing and I'm going to scale them down
And Amm going to make this a bit smaller
and I'm going to scale them down
okaylike that
or maybe a bit bigger
And I'm going to select the points on the bottom
and I'm going to scale them up
It's great as well
if you're using your mouse with the sculpting tool because if you do draw a little bit more jaggedy
you can just smooth it out quite easily
YeahI love this
the sculpting tool like that to use it for that
So now I'm going to make the lines that are coming here for the plants
So I'm going to go back to my draw mode
I'm going to go to my paint and I'm going to make one line there
another line there
and another line there
And if you're finding this confusing
I mean
I have both objects here together
I can move this one a bit to the left
but you can see now that I have my shape that is having dots and it's kind of imitating that we can make our own version
But like for now
this is good
The thing that we are doing now
we're going to make these shapes and these shapes
I'm gon na make them in another layer
So if we go here to see that this looks a bit like a spaghetti
this is the first layer
so I'm going to say that this is my plant
my plant strokes
So my plant strokes are there
I can activate them or deactivate them
And I'm going to make a new layer
And now it's going to be my leaves
So now in my leaves I'm going to use a different material
So instead of using this material for my leaves I'm going to use a new material up
I'm gonna use a new material I'm gonna apply new and instead of a stroke I'm going to use a fill
And my field is going to be this color
Okay
so this now when I go to draw
everything looks the same
I'm using the same ink
then graph
then look at what happens when I draw one of these circles
I can draw like that and now I draw
yeahand it's filling it in itself
Yeahwe can
by the way
activated so it has a stroke and feel at the same time
That's possible as well
So now I'm gon na do something that feels and that's a stroke outside
and that's quite nice because I can draw like that
draw like that and draw like that
and the reason why I'm making two layers
look what's happening now
You see that this is strokes
Here are on front
but here actually these materials in front
So I can go here and I can put my leaves
move them under my stroke
and I have the order I wanted
Perfectas simple as that
Okaynow that we are there
we can just go and generate the rest of the plants
So we make this one on the left
Okay
so for this plant on the left
we're gonna make
rememberwe're working every time with a new grease Sten
new propenal blank gon na
call it G 2
And I feel like now you're kind of really getting what this entire thing is about
you know
like I'm going to deactivate my dog and I
instead of working up
I forgot to put my little cylinder in there instead of working there so far away because my dog is in the middle
I can be working from the origin
So sometimes it's good to work from the origin and I'm gon na deactivate my plant
One plan 2 is here
and I'm going to be even more from the origin
Okay
plan 2
And now I'm going to go to my Chr mode
You can imagine now what's going to be stroke and what's going to be filled when it's there
I got go and just do my
I can do a stroke and feel if we wanted to have this effect
but actually I'm not gonna do that and I'm gonna show people a really cool thing that it's much better for making these weekly edges
So I'm going to only use fill for this material
I'm going to make it
I could call this material if I want some green material makes sense
and also you can name these layers
it just called GP layers can be plant main layer
you know like the more if you're someone that really likes putting names on things
just go for it
Okay
and now I'm gonna draw the shape of these plants are gon na go there
I'm drawing with my mouse
so it is not really easy to draw this
but luckily we have all the sculpting tools that are going to help us later
so I have that there
It wasn't that bad
you know
like for being done without a graphics tablet
that's not that bad
But remember
if we select the plant and we go to sculpt mode
we have the smooth and we can now smooth it all out
smooth and smooth and smooth
and I love this this thing for smoothing it and we can just move it as well if those two are touching Tomas together
Okaythat's looking quite good
And I was saying to people that we don't need to use the stroke with the wiggling because
you know
this can animate and I don't want to be animating the wiggle every single time of having to make a million drawings
And you see here we have a new thing that's called visual effect properties
This only appears on the grease pencil
And also we have the modifiers are modifiers we use all the time
Nowbecause they are dynamic
they are completely different depending on what we are doing
So in order to apply the effects
one of the things we need to make sure is that they only apply on the viewport
Shading is the most advanced of them
And right now we went back to this ugly lighting because the program is using our scene lights and the world
but we don't want that
We just using the HD R S from from the program
And let's for example
add the Pixel 8 effect and now when we add it and we change the size of the pixels
we see that now we made this pixelated effect in our drawing
I don't know in which cases
but it might be that someone wants to use grease pencil to create something that looks like an old video game
And if you​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ deactivate in the end
alyzed suddenly look at that
you are making a 3D kind of shape that is pixelated
It's really cool as you move around
And I guess you can animate with this as well
Yeahyou can completely animate with this
You could have another effect
For example
you could have this wave distortion and this wave distortion
you can change the amplitude
you can change the period to make it longer
you could as well change the face
So you could put some keyframes on this and make it look like a plant under the sea
The one I'm going to use actually is a modifier
so the modifiers are dynamic
so they change depending on the object we have
and here we have the modifiers that can be applied to grease pencil
and I love this one
the noise modifier
If we change the position
we change the amount to that
but then we can change the
I think it's the
let me see with the thickness strength noise scale here we are if we change the noise scale and we make it quite high
and now we make the position a bit smaller
look what we made
we made something that looks like those squiggles
especially when you look at it from from the distance
But now here in randomized
you see there is step 4
so we are making it so it changes every four steps
so we can make a step 1
So now every keyframe we move is changing
but I love that you can make for example
every five frames
So now when I play
is doing that brilliant without you having to do it
You every time It looks as if someone drew many
many times
but I didn't
Okaythat effect looks fantastic
Let's make sure that we are back in the frame 1 because that's gonna be very important when then we start learning of our animation
And now let's go back to my plane
Noto my plane
sorryto my reference
And now we're going to draw these lines there
So super simple to draw those lines
Basically what we did before
we're going to go make a new layer
plant strokes
We know that we want them in at the front of our shape
so they are there
and now we're going to add a new material
And we can just call this
I don't know
dark green
for example
And now this dark green is only going to have a stroke
We're gon na select the color of the dark
Did I select the color
I can zoom in a tiny bit more just to make sure that I selected that one
Perfectand I'm going to go here to the front
I'm just going to go to my draw mode and just draw those lines
So I'm going to draw one there
That might be a bit too thick
so I'm going to change the radius there
perfect
I'm going to do one there
one there
and one there
And you see what's happening
This squiggle
this effector I'm applying is applying as well to these lines
so I can just make them a tiny bit accentuated
But it's really cool because all of these lines inside these are getting that animation effect
Okay
that's looking quite good to me
That's looking fantastic
Obviouslywe now need to do every single of the plant
and I don't want to be boring people with making the plant
so I'm going to draw them all and we're going to meet when all the plants are drawn
And then we're going to be checking how to arrange them
Because remember that these now are 3D objects
We can move them around the scene and situate them so we get the effect that and in the next lesson as well as showing you how to we are arranging everything
we're gon na see how to animate it because animating it is a and animations we're going to use as well for the mouth of our Carter
So there's a lot of stuff coming
so be ready for the next lesson
Okaysee you
see you there