So after the time lapse in which we do all those plants
let's really organiz​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌e them
And this lesson is going to be about how to animate not only those plants
but also the eyes and the mouth of our Carter believe
So I'm gonna select these plants and some of them
the anchor point is gonna be in the correct position
but this one
for example
needs to be a bit more up
Other ones
for example
the anchor point is in the incorrect position
So we just affect only origins and we put this at the very beginning angle
as simple as that
So with the new exclusive of animation
I guess
we are actually not going to animate using that mode
It could
it's possible completely to animate like that
So we could animate a bit of rotation doing this
So we would be moving all the objects at the same time
but we want something a tiny bit more complex
so that's not really giving us what we wanted
Okay
that's good there
and I think this plant
oh no
this one needs to be there
So all the plants now have the anchor points where they should
So now we are going to activate my reference image and let's see where the elements were in the reference image so we can see that this plant was here
we can see that this one
oh I'm going to move it up so it's not intersecting there
This one was a bit behind the Carter
this one was a bit like that
That's looking good there
and now it doesn't need to be exact
but it's good to kind of start putting everything in position
so it looks pretty okay and this one
Ohthis 1 I forgot
I know it's good
this one goes down
okaythat's looking good
that's having enough plants surrounding my car
The only 1 I would put this one a bit on front
I like that it was covering a bit of leg
it's nice to have the surrounding of the character because as well in that if we do that people are really going to see how this all was in 3D
especially when they move
that's going to be very lovely
Okay
so I'm already seeing one little problem is that I have some keyframes that are on the 0．62
that's because I was drawing on the layer 62 and that's very typical
no worries if that happens we're gon na solve that
but it's something that I've done wrong
I think the first plant probably was drawn on the frame one
but these ones were drawn not second
but frame 62 accidentally
so we're gon na solve that in a second
so should we start kind of checking how animation works
Yeah
let's find out
okaywe're gon na go here to 2D animation
that's the way we're going to modify and as I was saying
we don't need 250 frames of animation
Probably something like 100 is going to be enough
And now 100
we can zoom in a tiny bit there
So we go from one to 100 and now I'm gon na
go to frame 1
I'm going to try to move everything I can
I'm gonna select everything in that shape
move it to frame 1
You see that those shapes disappeared because there was nothing on that frame
So that's why it's important to go now to plan for
I'm going to move it to frame 1
Okayso these are all the ones accidentally
okaynice to know you can fix that easily
Yesand it's good
sometimes it can be confusing that
And it's normal because sometimes we are testing the animation and we forget that
So now all my plants are in frame 1
and let's see how we can do animation
So we have a few different ways of animating in grease pencil
One of them is frame by frame animation
so we draw something on the first frame
then we draw on the next one and go frame by frame
So a bit like we would do
for example
in programs like Photoshop or Procreate or Animate
Another way in which we could do it is we could just have two positions and then tell the program to interpolate between them a bit more what we do when we are animating in 3D or for example
how we would do it in After Effects
So we're going to be looking at those both ways of doing it
Now we're going to deactivate
I'm gonna hide everything
I'm gonna go to my frontal view
put a new grease pencil
and I put it here
a blank grease pencil
and let's start understanding how it works
You see here we have the timeline
Make sure you are in this timeline
Exactly this one
That is the one that appears when we have the 2D animation and we have grease pencil selected because it happened to me in the past that I have the normal timeline in layout and that timeline you can not copy and paste grease pencil keyframes
Okay
We want to make sure we're in 2D animation
exactly draw something
I'm going to draw this shape
And if it's not very visible
let's maybe make it so the material of the line of the stroke is white
So I'm going to draw this line
and now I'm going to go to a different frame
And here we have activated
I have activated this because it's convenient to activate my auto key if you don't have it activated
If I draw here now
my drawing got added to the first keyframe
The program is deducing that because I didn't create new keyframes
I just wanted my drawing to be added only to the first one
Actuallythe keyframe get added when I created the grease pencil that twice before I was in frame 60 and it got added to the frame 60
Oh yeah
but now what we're going to do when we have it in this auto key mode
when I go to another frame and I draw the line
for example
I can draw the line here
Now the previous line disappear and there is this connection between the two keyframes
And you see now I go from one to another
So now I could go later and I could make my line to go there
and I could go later and make my line to move there
And now let's see what's happening
Now's starting to generate this animation
Do you see that
Right now I don't have any reference on where my previous line was
If I go
I think another of the modes
if you go here to this viewport shading
you see that we have in green the previous line and in purple
the next line
That is really
really useful because that's going to allow us to know what's happening
And if you want to modify that in audio scaling
here you see that we have the mode keyframes
You can change the opacity of how those lines appears
And you can say how many frames before and after appear
So right now
we only have one frame before and one frame after
but we can do two
So now I actually don't have any more after
I only have one
but now we're getting two levels of green and one of purple
That's great
and anyone who knows about 2D animation will find that super useful
Yeah
we'll be having more courses in 2D animation in the school
but for now
we want you to understand that this is the way in which you would do frame by frame animation inside this program keyframes
by the way
if you don't want them to delay that
you could also copy the keyframe
go here to 26 and paste it
Let me see
copypaste
And now what I did is I went from one keyframe and I copied it in another one
but the keyframe once it's there
we can go to
for example
sculpt mode sculpted
and now what I'm doing is I'm having that keyframe and now it's changing when I have it there
Okayso you can have a very smooth change like that
Yeahand it means that you don't need to draw again
I can just copy this
paste it
copypaste up
copy paste
and now modified
and you can see where the previous one was
and you can animate with the sculpting
You know
it's a way of animating just with the scope
That's a nice way of doing it
Yeah
and this is exactly what we're going to do for the plants
so we're just going to use a scoped mode to generate a bit of a gentle rotation
and then we're going to see how the program can interpolate between these positions
And before we move
let's explain what I mean with interpolate V between these positions
So you see that we have this shape there
and I'm going to copy and paste it because I think people are going to understand it much better like that
and I'm going to put that there
and I'm going to make a new position of this shape I'm gonna put that there
And for interpolation to work well
we need shapes that are similar
So because I'm doing a sculpting
the number of points on the shape are going to be the same
So I have one shape that starts here
another shape that continues there if you want to interpolate between them right now there is none
no interpolation we're going to have to be either
I think it's in way paint mode or in edit mode works as well
But if we not way paint
if I say we paint
I think is in the draw mode
sorryin Dr mode
So in draw mode
when we go here to draw animation
you see that here we have different types of animation
but also we have interpolated sequence
So we need to be in between the two keyframes
It's a bit confusing
You need to be between the two curve frames
We go to draw interpolate sequence
and now we have here a menu
and you see automatically generated all these keyframes
If you move
you're not going to be able to modify
but if you go here
you can say step
So you can say only add keyframes every two or 3 keyframes
And now you can do different modes
So you can have linear
you can have cube
Quantic can take
by the way
if you're finding this confusing
if you just put your mouse and keep it there
it tells you this is weakest transition
almost linear
but with a slight curvature
If you go to quintet
it says quinty kissing
That one is not expressing much
much more
For example
in back
it tells you touby kissing with overshoot and settle bounce is telling you exponentially the came parable bounce
like when objects collide
so it's telling that use this one if you have
for example
a ball bouncing
sure and you can see the little line on the side gives you quite an indication to yes
and when I selected it modifies it there
And now there is a transition between the two lines created by the program
This is not like an after effect
you can modify it live
you know if it's done it done
if you want to do it again
you just delete those keyframes that are blue because those are in between keyframes
And now we do it again
And we do interplay sequence
And we
for example
put more steps
So I can put
ohsorry
less steps
So we put one
and now it's much more smooth because it goes from one shape to a number
Okaythat's really nice
perfect
So with that in mind I'm gonna delete this one and I'm going to go and I'm going to activate the first of my plants
Let's one for example
this one
And what I'm going to do is I'm going to make sure selecting the plant
I have a keyframe there and this animation is going to loop only on is going to reach frame 20 and then in frame 4 is going to go back again
And I know that our entire sequence is 100 frame
So I'm going to show you how to look that forever and ever
So I'm going to go to my frame 1
I'm going to copy Ctrl C and paste in frame 20 my animation
So now that we have there I'm gonna do it again
Ctrl C and in frame 40 is going to be the animation
Right now we have the animation three times the same
but now we're going to go into the one in the middle and we're going to see how we're going to modify
So I'm going to go to my sculpt mode and for doing that gender rotation
you see that we have this twist there
And I'm going to make it a bit big
and I'm going to start doing that
So I'm rotating my shape
and now I'm going to grab it with a big one
I'm going to start grabbing it
so I'm going to rotate it and grab it
okayjust like you were doing
practicing with the line before
but you can do now with your plant
And we have a problem here
It looks like I'm going to now make the act deactivate that
It looks like we have a problem and is that we didn't copy the two layers
we only copied one of them
You see that that is because we have the layer Co one MDP layer
that's my fault for not naming the layers
So I'm going to delete those layers
It's good for people to see the mistakes that come and I need to make sure that I select both layers
both the stroke and the main layer
So I'm going to I'm going to have to go back because I made many mistakes
okay
I'm going to delete all of that
delete the keyframes
We're gon na go to the first layer and copy both of them to frame 20
I think I need to copy them 1 by one
Let me see Ctrl CC plus V
ctrl C
ctrl V
and now I'm gon na
do control B
ctrl C Ctrl and ctrl C Ctrl
and now it's to Na be in the region in the middle
And now
yesI need to make sure that when I do this rotation I'm affecting both layers at the same time
It's looking much better and now I'm going to be pinching them
I'm moving them there
you know
now I'm going quite fast
but when I did it in the original animation
I took my time
taking your time means that you can make it quite gentle and with a lot of love
but I want to go a bit faster there
And now what I'm going to do is here I'm going to be in draw mode and I'm going to go to draw interpolate sequence and I'm gon na do steps of three
so it doesn't go that many
and for now I like the sinusoidal 1
It's just going to go there
and I'm going to do draw interplace sequence and the singles soid all is happening again
The only thing that we need is the other shape
we're going to select layer 1
because it's the stroke draw interplay sequence and draw interpolate sequence
So now both the stroke and the main part are just having that animation
So now someone might be wondering
how do I do this so it repeats again and again forever
So in order to do that
we're going to add a modifier to this plant
And I'm going to go here to the time offset modifier
And the time offset modifier is really simple
The only thing we are doing is telling the program how many frames of set
That means like where do we start the animation with my offset
But here in the custom range
I can say I can
I'm going to repeat my animation from frame 0 to frame 40
So from frame one actually to frame 40
and I want to put it is in the mode it is going to be
has a different ones
I think regular is the one that repeats forever
We could do
for example
ping pong
And what it does is that when it reaches one
it goes the other way or reverse
It kind of applies to in reverse animation direction
but the regular one just repeats our animation forever
So now when I have that there
my plant is just animating all the time
okay
So it doesn't add any new keyframes
it just it just knows and repeats forever
I can make my animation even longer now
800 frames
and it's just continue forever
And you're adding the modifier to the Creese pedestal
I'm adding the modifier to the grease pencil
that means that I can have different loop speeds in different moment
And by the way
if you are finding that this animation
it might be that right-hind is going a bit too fast
Too too fast
Yeahso we could modify the keyframes by selecting them all and just putting them
I think it's possible
by the way
just to get the keyframes and scaling them
you see
So if we start from 0 and now we do scaling
I think it's scale into animation
The only problem we do that now is my animation is 70 frames
So remember to do that on your time of so now we're having a way slow animation that's easier
And how did you do the scaling
Just pressing S as simple as that
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going to go plant by plant
and I'm going to be animating them all
And so I'll see you in a second