Hello Katie
Hello
Welcome to our course 2 D2 3D using grease pencil in blender
And here we have the final result of what we are going to be making today
And not only that looks already quite cool
but also we're gon na see how to animate it
And another cool thing we have here
you can see that Blender is working completely live
We are rendering quite a really nice render using Eev
We can modify the elements completely live without having to wait for render time
And that's something that I find very exciting
somewhat like working on a video game
need to be waiting for the render to happen
We've been really excited about Chris Pencil for a long time now
actually
We've seen a few other artists doing different types of things with it
But this mixing 3D and 2D is something that we've really wanted to get into
Yeahrecently we went to the cinema to see spider-man across the spider-verse and they used themselves Gree Pencil
Many artists work there with Blender and gree pencil
and it's amazing how they were mixing 3D stuff
but then adding little details that were suggesting or making references to the original comic
Yeahactually
whilst we were watching it
I didn't know that they were using Blender and grease pencil
and I was watching it thinking
how are they making this beautiful style
Because yeah
like you're saying
they had the definition of the characters jaw lines or cheekbones
And so you could see really clearly the 2D star
But as they turned
you have the three DS
So that's just one rendering of grease pencil
And this is all part of a wider thing that we are doing right now in Pattaya school
which is exploring how we can get sketches and people's ideas into the 3D world
We want to expand how the 3D world looks
And we think for that
we're going to have to discover new techniques
And Grease pencil is a perfect one for that
So we can see here the original illustration that was drawn for this course and this illustration has a few details
It's very simple
there are not that many colors and the shapes are quite simple
There are things that we wanted to translate into the 3D world
One of them is the brush that was used
This was drawn by k．t
using Procreate
so it was done with an ipad
but it could have been done in Photoshop or whatever other program
but then you have all these kind of nice
how would you say it's kind of a cryon or I don't know
what's the effect
Yeahsort of charcoal is soft edge like that
I mean
in reality
you also could have done it on pencil and paper
Yeahthat's really what this is imitating in the end
but we have all of these brush packs also available in Pattaya school
actually
Yeah
and this entire illustration is inspired by our dog Mickey
We recently acquired a dog variant
and I think that this is another reference or another
the idea for people
just try to look for something in your life that is important to you in the moment and try to illustrate that because we are going to put more love and care
Right now
we're thinking a lot about our dog behind us right now
So we are making drawings about our dog
but just think of what is inspiring you in life and try to go for it in your illustration totally
And the other thing that we had is that we decided that these shapes would be 2D and the dog would be 3D
That's an arbitrary decision
We could have done a different thing
Maybe the dog in 2D and the shapes in 3D
depending on what we do
that's going to be a different translation because the dog
for example
in 3D
we are not going to be able to make this beautiful curved lines that are showing a bit
You know
this is representing hair and are showing a bit of behind the background
So we're have thinking about how those things translate
but the final result that we achieve is going to depend on what you want you can decide you can start with your own illustration and follow it maybe to turn your own dog or if you love cats or whatever pets
make a few plans and then follow the tutorial
We recommend following the tutorial by doing your own thing
I think that especially for people doing this course
we recommend if you've never done a course in Blender before
we have an entire introduction to Blender
so go for that you're gon na deduce the program and when you get to th​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌is
let's work on how to translate 2D to 3D
So let's start modeling in the next lesson
All right
see you there