Hello Katie
hello again
Here we are with all our lovely animated plants
So should we make the eyes and the mouth
Yeahso for the eyes
I could make them and draw them exactly on top of our car
but in reality they can be floating a bit because we are never gon na get it
You know
So lateral that we're gonna say that trick
So I'm gonna go
I'm gonna create again
a eraas pencil
gonna call it blank
and I'm gonna call it eyes
And the techniques we're going to use for this
we actually have been used in them
Everyone's going to feel quite comfortable making this one
if you have been following
welleverything
So I'm going to go to draw mode
There's one thing that we can do in drone mode
I'm going to go to my materials
I'm going to delete this and create a new one because sometimes it generate some problems there
I'm gonna just select the white
I'm gonna make the white part of the eye first
and you have all these shapes so we can make circles
If you are not very good at drawing to just make a circle like that
that you have an eye
NiceI will definitely that easy PC
So now that we have that there
I think I could press
I have to press enter
The material is the white material for the eye and the layer here
very important to draw in layers is the I white
So now that we have that one
we're gon na need another black
And you can see it's quite big because it's kind of going to be cut
So I'm going to make a new layer and then is the pupil the black part
Yeahis pupil
Okaynow that we have that there I'm going to generate a new material and my new material ISS going to be only a field and it's going to be black
I'm going to use the circle again
and what I'm going to do is I'm going to make my material there
I'm going to press enter
So now that we have that drone there
one of the things we can do is masks
So we can use the white of the eye to mask the black part of the eye
You know
we have the pupil in one layer
we have the I white in another
And if you see here
if you select the iwh
you can use that as a mask
So you see that if you select use mask
so we can use a mask
I think we need to use it on the pupil
We select the mask here
we press plus
and we select the I white
So now the pupil is going to only appear where the eye white is
And as soon as I do it I'm cutting one shape to another
okay
And it's amazing because it's not only that I'm cutting one shape to another because we're gonna use this in animation
And again
I started from frame 30 five-eight
so I'm gonna go to frame one
make sure that I move my shapes to frame 1
and I'm gonna gonna see how I do this
So first I'm gonna put it in position
I'm going go to my object mode
my anchor point is in the completely wrong place
so I'm going to make s​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ure that my anchor point is exactly aligned to my eyes
I'm going to deactivate my anchor point
I'm going to put that in front and I'm going to put my eye in a place that I like and you can rotate it in 3D so my eye can be there and I can scale it
And depending on what you're making
you know
you can have your eyes in different ways
That's looking good
Or maybe the eye in the reference was a bit smaller and a bit higher
Soso nice
I always love the way you add eyes to a character so is alive
but now what we can do is we have to have animation
So I know that this white of the eye is not going to be animated
but the black part
the pupil is
So let's see how we can do that
We can go to my pupil here and let's add on frame 10
I'm going to do a copy and paste
so in frame 10 I'm gon na have a different position for the pupil and we can go
for example
to in edit mode if we want
There are many ways of doing it
I can just lock my eye white and in edit mode I press A
so I select everything and now we can move
I can use my normal
the normal of my polygons
I think because I rotate it in that case
it kind of it goes together
it goes in the same direction
And now imagine I change the position of my eye
So I put my eye there
and now I'm going to go on frame 20
I'm going to copy and paste
I don't need to put it in frame 20 to be honest
I can put it a bit later and I can put a frame before frame in frame 26
So I'm going to hold on the same position and then from 26 to 30 I'm going to have a new position that maybe it's going to be looking down there and now I'm going to go and I'm going to go from frame 30 to frame 40
we're going to be in the same position
but from 40 to 47
for example
we're going to go and change that
So right now we still don't have interpolations
we have a little animation
but there is no interpolation happening between it
but if we want it to interpolate
it's really easy
we know that there is a transition between frame 0 and frame 10
so we're going to go here and going to be in drop mode
and we're going to do exactly what we did before interplay sequence
and now I'm getting an animation between one place and another
Now this holds
and now I'm going to have an animation here is going to be a bit longer through interplay sequence
so now I'm going to have a relationship between there and there
and now between there and there
I'm going to make it a bit longer Drew Interpolate sequence and others
There is an animation between there and there
So now my dog
it is looking around and I want to start once I get there
I should now like have an ending to this animation
so you can look forever
So I'm going to do copy and paste from up
Let me see from this position until 63 and 63 to 70
I'm liking this 70 because I go to the original position and I'm gon na double draw interplay sequence
So now I know that I end and frame 70 in exactly the same position where I started
right
And now you can keep going for like we did before
just adding a time offset modifier
I'm in regular mode
custom range 0 to 70
So now I know on frame 70
my animation starts again
So now when I play
my doggie is cooking around
Greatso simple
and you get so much character there
yeah