So should we do the mouth
Yeahlet's see how we're gonna do this
Yeah
so for the mouth
it's gonna be very simple
We are basically doing the same
we are making a blank frame
we are on the black grease pencil frame and we are going to be in frame 1
and I'm gonna call this mouth and let's see how we can make it
We are going go to my front view
so I'm making sure that I'm drawing in the correct place and we can activate where are you reference you are hidden
I think it's because we have all of this movie activated
okayI can see now how my mouth is
so I'm going to be selecting my mouth and I'm going to just try to put it in a similar position
I'm going to select my then
and I'm going to first draw here in the air
and then I'm going to move it in the correct position
I'm going to draw it a few times until I like it
that's good
and now that I have that there I'm going to go to my object mode
change my origins because I want it to be staying there
And for now I'm not gonna rotate it
I can rotate it later
but for my drawing when I'm still drawing for me
I like it just keeping it flat and in reality it works well like that
so I'm going to just keep that there and put my mouth there
and that's looking adorable
My dog is getting a lot of personality
the kid
so let's see how we can just animate this mouth in a simple way
One of the things that we could do is make the mouth appear and disappear
so we can just
let's say we are starting in frame time
we want to have the entire mouth
I'm going to be in drawing mode and I'm maybe on frame 8
I'm going to go in drum mode
I'm going to have my mouth starting to disappear
frame 6
my mouth is there and frame 4
my mouth is a little dot
so I'm having this animation of the mouth and so we kind of hold the mouth until frame 50
I'm copying and pasting this
and now I'm going to make my mouse disappear and my mouse appear left to right
and maybe now it's going to be the opposite ISS going to start disappearing like that
So up here there
now it gets at the beginning
I like it not that much variation
and then I get a lot of speed
That's a way of drawing
which I'm imitating the style of the curve that we would do if we were doing an easy in and out
You know
it gets faster
it's lower
it's a bit more fluid
that's a nice personality there
Okay
so now we are gonna call this layer
we can call it here mouth
if I change the layer here
when we go here to our layers
we are changing it here as it's just a different place to change
it's going to add a new layer and I'm going to call this tongue
And I know that tank was not in the original illustration
but it was in the animation that we made because we thought
ohit would be so pretty to have a tongue kind of moving left to right
So I'm going to deactivate
Oh no
Ithis is the material I'm using for the mouth
I need to make a new material
So I'm going to make this new material and I'm going to make it fill
and I'm going to make this pink material that we can use for my tongue
That's looking good
And now I'm going to just start drawing my tongue
Probably it starts after the entire month appeared
So maybe on frame 15 is the first frame of it
and we are now going to start drawing it
So at the beginning
we only have a tiny bit of time appearing
I can not see it very well
so I'm gon na make this color a bit more saturated
Okaythat's more pretty
And now we
because we have this mode activated
auto kinging is going to be quite easy now to start drawing a bit more
so I'm going to do the second position of my tongue
actually I can make a tiny bit bigger there
so my tongue appear there
and now for my third position
I like the tongue to kind of stay a lot behind
It's just
you know
it's getting bigger
but it's kind of licking the side of the mouth
I think it's so cute
I love these additions that you can make in 3D like you're saying it's not in the 2D
even if you could make a 2D animation
once you've got going with your model
you can have so much extra fun with it
Yeah
and I really would like to see
you know
if people are making their car or their hamster
what are they going to put here
Yeahbecause maybe you can do something that's really specific to you
I think that our dog Mickey glicks his mouth quite a lot actually
Yeahalways hungry
Soso that's good
It goes there
And now when we have that there
probably we're gon na have to be coming in
If I had a graphics tablet
I could be drawing a more detailed one
but I think I like it
and now that goes there and then I'm gon na
just copy that last frame or I can just click of it to create a frame
and then I delete whatever I need
So up
make sure that if I try to delete
we can block the other layer
So we can block the mount layer and when I delete and make sure that I'm only deleting my tongue layer
okayso I think it's that animation is working well there
And I'm gon na go to this mode so I can see what's happening
And now I can see that my animation is there
and then it returns
But I think once it gets smaller
it should start again
So in frame 60
I think we should start again
so we're going to go now to this mode
add modifier time of set custom range 0 to 60
And now my animation plays forever
I have my
and I really like as well
by the way
because my ranges are different
one goes from 0 to 60 and my eyes are from 0 to 70
As we repeat more and more
they are out of sync
so it feels a bit more alive because the mouth
sometimes it's moving when the eyes are looking at one place
and sometimes it's moving when the eyes are looking at another place
We're adding more and more variation with all of these combinations of things
The only thing now before just rendering our entire thing
the only thing I would recommend is that we can simply go and put a bit of the noise that we were using before
And also I can align this mouth
So to align this mouth in object mode
I can just put it there and rotate it
But the only thing I would do now is just add in my modifiers
I would put this noise where you are the noise and do the same we did before
You know
like we can change the noise scale so we can make the noise scale quite high and the position quite soft
So it's just adding a tiny bit of that
Yeaha bit more of the hand drawn feeling
And because the steps are every 4
we are having this kind of thing that is changing all the time and it's adding a really nice effect
If we have an effect that we like and we want to copy to another place
it's really easy
The thing you need to do is select all the objects
So for example
select this plant and this plant and this plant
and maybe the mouth as well
and then
and then select continue doing shift and select the object in which you have the effect that you like
For example
here on the eye
that needs to be the last one
And now we go to noise here and we say copy to select it
I now automatically my program has copied that noise to every single of my layers
so now all my layers are having that noise applied
I need my beta in the mouth
To be honest
I would do the noise a bit softer
so we just can select the mouth and modified
no worries
they are not connected
it simply in position
we're gon na make it a tiny bit smaller because I think it was a bit too much for the mouth
so that's starting to look really good
very lovely by the way
some people are going to think
is there another way of drawing
like can you draw on a surface and it is possible I'm going to show you just as a final extra thing
I'm going to show you that if we add a grease pencil
there is one mode in drawing that instead of drawing on my origin
you can draw on a surface and it's possible to draw
I'm going to just make sure that I am in the correct position
do draw
and I probably was in some random layer 392
My goodness
let's go to frame 1
not to this crazy one
okay
And let's draw in there
So we are now selecting the drone mode and I'm gonna draw in there
And it looks like I'm drawing flat
but because we are drawing in surface
look what happened
I was drawing on top of my object
but it's quite separated and the separation is defined by this
It's defined by this offset
So the offset happens because a lot of times when you're drawing this and by mistake
it intersects the geometry
So usually you want to put something quite small to look as if you are completely drawing on top of the object
And when I do that
now for real I'm drawing on top
And this can be very useful
You know
you could have done the post there using this mode
but it can lead to problems because it's quite difficult to control
You don't really know what you're doing
It's not super intuitive to be drawing so much in 3D
so for now
I only recommend doing it when it's really necessary to do so
And you can see that for this type of 2D animation on top
it's not completely necessary
so we're going to have to be a bit clever about the usage of this mode
But we are then going to be looking
you know
the content on the school
He's expanding more on grease pencil
We are doing all the projects with all the people's illustrations and showing how they can be adapted
and sometimes that mode will be used
So it's not that we are against it
it's only that we are just being a bit careful when to use it
Makes sense
Only use something complicated if it's really necessary
Yes
and oh
a final
final little thing is that when we are rendering
because we are not using any
single light or the world
if you want to render this animation
when you do render animation
So far I haven't found a way in which I can render this animation
And it doesn't go to this ugly mode
You know
I know that I need to position the camera and everything
Let's do that so people understand what I mean
I'm going to go there
And now when I do render animation
you see that it's rendering with the original light from my scene
And it's doing it even if I delete the lights from my scene
I'm going to delete that and you'll to go render render animation and still applying the original light
That's because we deactivated the lights and we wanted to use this kind of Hdri that comes with Blender So far
maybe someone can tell us
So far
we haven't discovered exactly how to do to render with this light
But there's like everything in life
There is a little trick
and it is this trick is quite useful as well if you
for example
want to render this mode
but you want to talk to your friends
all of these kind of lines that are appearing and you want them to see how cool is the look of the program
So if you want to do that
you simply have to go to here to inside
I think it's inside
let me see
Now I started talking and now I'm not going to know where it is so
In view here
in any of the modes
when we go to view
we can go and do viewport render animation
We first need to select where we are rendering our animation like we always do
And now when we do viewport render animation
we render the viewport for the animation range of this scene
So when I click there
it's rendering this mo​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌de
And this is very useful because we love showing like work in progress to our friends
We love showing how it works and it solves the problem here
So we do view render report animation
Now we are rendering that
of course
we need to make sure that we don't have that empty layer there
So and let me make sure that I'm zoom in enough and now I do view is a behavior there view for render animation
And here I am
I'm rendering my animation with the look and the Hdri that comes in Blender lately
I know that's a little extra
but it's good to know because sometimes people say
how do you do to finish the render
And that's how you do it perfect