Hello Katie
Hi and welcome to Noah Sin
I love this one and we are going to be analyzing a bit how it was made
We want people to be able to make their own illustrations
So what we're going to be doing here is we're going to provide everyone this file
This file as well has some animation
So when you play
you can see how we use grease pencil to animate this little
the deer having a bit of a snooze
And also we want to explain how materials will build
Like we know that we are always used grease pencil or grease pencil
It's super versatile and depending on how we use it
we can achieve completely different results
Yeah
and this one's really interesting because when I'm looking at it now
it looks just like
no is a 2D illustration
but you're moving around it in 3D
Not only that
we also
if we go here into post mode
we have created some animation
So the car is rigged
You can see here how I can move the legs
I have the little pole
so I can check where the leg is pointing at
And even the tail animates with the lovely band
We
yesthis illustration is a bit different from what we've done before
We are not going for a different 3D style
Look
What we are trying to achieve is exactly the same look that the original illustration had
I think the original illustration is somewhere around here
Yeahso we are achieving the same look that the original illustration h​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ad
but we are being able now to look at it in 3D and look at it from every angle
So I figure you had to build in 3D
right
Yes
we can look at here at how this was made
This all came from a 3D model
and then we wrecked and then we applied a few things
So you can see here that I have a little bit of a bump
We're going to explain how that was created
and the reason why was that was created
The first thing we're going to show here is I'm going to go file new general
I'm not going to save this
And I want to show how we made the main part of the material on this program
So we have a problem is that when we have 3D
even if we are using Eev
we are getting some type of lighting
You can see here when I rotate it is affecting my
the layers like the different faces of my cube
If I want the cube to have a completely solid color
what we can do is automatically this cube comes with a material called material
So we can go here into my
is this in shading
And we are going to get rid of the principal bsdf This is the one that we usually use has all the specular rough
but we don't really want to do that
We don't want to use any of those properties because the only thing that we're going to need is an emission
So this is an emission color
So animation is a single color
a solid color that the material is going to emanate
but it's not light
it's not an emission in terms of light
we I'm not going to illuminate the scene
The only thing we're going to apply is this color to the
and now when I changed my color
whatever color I use
my material is going to be exactly that color
I can go here to layout
and now we only have one option in my material
which is the color that's it
that's can
So it looks completely flat
but you are still moving around
It still is a 3D cube
exactlywe still have a 3D cube
If we go to the previous setting
we are still there
but now when I look at it from here
it's all the time going to look completely flat
That's what we did with the illustration from No
I can go back here to the illustration from Noah
And you can see here that most of the materials
or actually all the materials I have here
if I go inside my material setting
I have just one material with one emission
Okay
we have another thing that we have in this project that maybe someone might be wondering
why is that
When we go here
we are having all these bumps
Yeahso we wanted to do this thing
We wanted to get a little bit of a wiggly edge around all my 3D objects because that allows us
when we rotate
it looks as if it was like just drawn with with a hand drawn pen
But one of the problems that we had is that there is an option inside this program that kind of was supposed to be used for doing that
So if you select VR
you can go to add grease pencil that you have a collection line art
That means that we are going to apply linear to this entire collection
And the first thing I discovered that you need to do is you need to be looking at the scene through a camera
So I'm going to be looking at it through my camera
I'm going look my camera to the view
So I'm going to be looking at it
So the camera I'm going to be selecting here I'm going to add Kristen
so seeing lineart and as soon as I do it
we are seeing what the program is doing is adding lines on the edge of my entire object
And right now you're getting all of these little dots for one reason
The reason why we're getting is because we are applying another effect
which in this case is this display toate my displays
I'm going to deactivate my displays here and I'm going to deactivate my displays here
Ohmy displays only
I'm going to deactivate displays so you can see what the program can do
It can generate these linear that covers around my object and theres a lovely effect of
of like
you know
like if it was an outline
yeahit looks like a cartoon
doesn't it
And again
you can move around it in 3D
The problem with this effect is first is a bit slow
So you can see that it's slowing down my program quite a lot
And I always wanted to have something that was live that could work live in my stream
But my second problem is that I can change the color
but I would have to generate a single lineart pair material in order to have the color of the edge to be how I wanted it
And then I could go into my line art
You know
when I generated my linear
I could go into
where are you
Is this this line art
YeahI could go into line and apply effects
I could apply
for example
a noise to make it more quickly
to give you that jagged edge
But in reality
Iyou only wanted the jagged edge
I didn't want that outline because this
this illustration
there is an illustration when we show it
I'm going to show it again
didn't have an it
The only thing I have is the squibbing edges
So I decided I was going to do it
applying some noise to the material
And to apply noise to the material
I wanted to apply a displacement noise
So that would allow my geometry to Dis
And to apply a displacement noise
usually you can do it inside your shading panel
Do you remember like you go to shading
there's a displacement map and you add it
The problem is that because we're using evon
not cycles Eev doesn't allow for displacement because it takes quite a lot of time to display some material
So if you're using Eev
instead of applying your displacement as a texture in the material
we can simply go to the object and apply a modifier
And the modifier is called display
So you add a modifier and you need to find it here is here in where are you
Displays
Displayshere it is
You can see that
So after I applied that
the only thing I need to do is load the texture
And in this case
I loaded a noise texture
You can just generate a noise inside the program or you can load a noise texture
you can create a noise texture inside Photoshop it however you want
So once you apply the noise texture
when you activate it
what it's doing is I can see it here
it modifying the entire geometry
putting it up and down in reality is up and down everywhere
not only in the edges
but because my viewing is completely flat for the human eye looks as if it's only in the edges
Yeahand so is that a much lighter way it works
It is a bit heavy
but as you can see
it's moving quite well
And the cool thing about it is that you can change how heavy it is depending on the subdivisions you have in your geometric
because obviously I cannot display something if there is not enough you
So imagine if I have only one subdivision
So you can see that with one subdivision
it's very difficult to see the effect because there is no enough geometry
But I can make
for example
two subdivisions
and I'm starting to see more
and I can make 3
I can make four
and I can make 5
I can make 6
if I make 6
my program might start going a bit slowly
But the cool thing about subdivision is I can put three here
and I can put five in my render time
so I can be working completely fine in my project
and then when I render it in the end
it's going to render well
So this was the most kind of flexible way
I found to do this type of effect
So remember
simply add a displacement texture after a subdivision
put a noise in it
and then you're going to be able to get those quickly edges perfect
The other things I did about this
as well as modeling that
you know
like modeling is basically coming from cube
You can imagine this is a cube with the extrusion from the leg
This head was a separate object
The only other thing was creating all the grease pencil object
So this was an animation that I made and instead of animating it three times
I made only one animation in which I made this set to move around
like from going to one position
you can see I made this position
this position here
and this position here
And then I made transitions between them
But instead of making it three times
what I did is I only made one
and then I copied them a few times
and then I used the time of set that we use in our main course
and then I changed the time of
you know
like it goes from 1 to 71
But now I can change my frame offset
So if you wanted to have a fourth copy
you could do the same
you make another copy
and now when you make the frame of you are simply making them animate at different times
that's very clever as simple as that
and then all the grease pencil I'm using I'm using the noise effect
so they are always changing every
you know
I don't know how many frames
every four frames
Because it creates that effect as if something is hand-drawn
I really like doing that
And in the course
we learn about how you can draw grease pencil onto the surface of an object
It looked like you did that here
Yeahso I only did it actually for this 1
I did it for the nose
I think for the rest I drew in a completely flat way and then I adapted it
But you can do it if you feel like
as I'm saying
sometimes it does work that well
I think I used it
I used it actually as well for this DOC
but you can see here I used quite a lot of distance
you can see the distance between this grease pencil and the DOC
but I can
I recommend only using it if you really need it
If not
rememberyou can always draw in a completely flat way and then you can simply move the object to the position and then you can use the sculpting
you know
always with the sculpt mode
you can modify and move your objects
So you can just adapt them and rotate them and make them to go a bit closer to the geometry
Oh yes
you can kind of get just where you want
And the cool thing as well
you can see here is that grease pencil gets affected by armature
So when I created my armature now when I go into my post mode I'm moving everything and my entire grid pencils is moving with my geometry
So in the next mini
minimini lesson
we're gon na see how it is to rig this character without having to use all the complexity
From Rigby we made a simple rig
I know that there is an entire course about rigging in school
but I know a lot of people is going to Na want to know how do we rig something like this tail and how they will RI these legs without having to go through the entire rectify
So we're going to have this little lesson and we're going to explain it
and then you're gon na be able to make things like this yourself
Perfect to see you in the next lesson
bye