Welcome back
everyone
So this is an E specials sex learning
which we can explain how we can do very simple rigs
We have here the main part of the body with the legs
I'm going to explain how we can build simple rigs with Ik
Ik means that we're going to be able to select the position of the leg
moving it around
and then the entire body is going to follow
And also we're gonna see how to make the tail after that
Ni​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ceokay
Anyone doing this
We recommend first doing an entire course on rigging because I think that that course gives a lot of knowledge about how bones work
But if you want to do a quick break
this might work
So we're going to start by adding an armature is here and a single bone
We only need one bone
I'm going to go to the frontal view
I'm going to go in my transparent mode and the beginning of the bone
it depends on on how you want my chain here is I'm going to start my tail from here
So what I'm going to do is I'm going to rotate my bone there with pressing CT
I do rotations of 5 degrees at a time
And now the cool thing about the bones
if we go into edit mode is that they can be treated a bit like any modeling
So if I press E
I can extrude them and I can extrude towards here
And then I can extrude again where to where my head is
If you send the course of rigging with us
you know that sometimes we don't rig with the head included because usually heads are rigid
And in this case
the head is rigid
So what we do is we model entire head
then we put it all together
we parent it all together
and then we just attach it to this final bone
So we rotate that final bone
the head moves
but it's not getting affected by the weights because I don't like the formations of heads
Yeahunless you are doing the formation of heads
but in most cases we are not
Okay
now we're going to start extruding leg
So I'm going to go one time there
another time there to the middle
another time down
And now I'm going to do it again
one time
one time again there
not the time there
By the way
it's possible if you wanted
it's possible to do this extreme applying with a symmetry
but for this case
because it's so simple
we are not doing it with symmetry
And with this one
how did you
how did you decide exactly
Because obviously this moose coming from the 2D is a completely graphical 2D characters
So how do you choose where you want the bones to go
To be honest
when I model this one
because I love so much how they were not in the same position
the other model is not
is even less symmetric than what we are doing right now
So it was completely me just guessing and doing it
and then checking again
and then check again and check again
There was no science at all to it
It's just a pure game of guessing and taking what it works
But it's a good question because I think a lot of times people think that there is much more planning than there is
But this has been mainly
you know
trying trial and error to know if you make your own character right now with crazy proportions
But the thing is very important now is that the situation of where the bones are is to be in somehow related to where my cuts are in my geometry
And I'm gonna show you because the geometry right now has a subdivision
But in reality
it is a super simple geometry
I'm gonna show you without transparency and I'm gon na go to my edit mode
You see that I made this
it's very simple
but it has some cuts here on the knees and these cuts here on the knees are in these two positions
And if I check my armature and I'm going to try to make it transparent
you see that here
the middle
the circle of my bones needs to be between these lines
These cuts in the middle
the more it is between these lines
the much better it is going to be
because then when it bends
it's going to bend very smoothly while still being a cart that is going to bend animate very well because we don't have that geometry
This is the geometry that the weights are going to be playing with
but then it's going to be softened out with a subdivision after
Okaythat makes sense
but in the body
you're not thinking about that then because that would be a much smoother animation in what do you mean in the body
You're not thinking about where you're positioning the weights depending on the cuts that you have in the geometry
Not really
because in the in the
in the body
the body
the bones are really
really in the middle
So a bone that I bend here is gonna affect almost all the geometry
Ithe thing on the left
the bone is really near the edge
And if I just didn't have
iffor example
I had the bone a bit too high up
when it bends
it's going to kind of make the two points collapse against one another and it's going to look very ugly
I think that it's very important in these cases to just do it simple and practice with a really
reallyreally simple geometry
because you're going to understand much better how it works
Once we have that
the only thing we need to do is just select my geometry
I'm going to call this body
I'm going to select my armature
so with Ctrl click I'm going select the armature and then we do right click parent with automatically weights
That means that the program is going to automatically calculate the weights depending on the distance from the bone to the different phases
the geometry
And as soon as I do it
now if I go
my geometry goes inside my body goes inside my armature
and if I go now into post mode
I can go activate transparency
If I go into post mode
if I rotate any of my bones
you can see that my Carter is basically raked
you know
and it's raking quite well
You know
it's not perfect here
like you correct this bend
but because we're going to be having a flat shading
this is absolutely not relevant
It's going to look good
And if I want as well
I can always go into my body and in object mode
I can select my body and I can add more subdivisions so I can get smoother
But no worries about this not being perfect because then we're gon na
make it all squid with my noise
So I always say this as well to people
you know
only worry I'm gon na do two subdivisions
I only only worry about things and details if they are actually going to be visible
But if they are not
this should be fine
And now people are gonna be wondering how do you do
Because if I try not to move this of the bone
this just rotates And people are going to think
how do you do
So you can just have this Ik system in which you select the location of the feet
and then they follow
So we did an inverse kinematic Ik system for that
And to do the Ik system
the first thing I need to do is I'm you're going to have to do this leg by leg
but I'm only going to do it with this right front leg
And I'm going to generate a couple more bonds
I'm going to go into my edit mode and I'm going to activate transparency
So I know what I'm going to do
And let's make sure that I'm selecting this one in the front and I'm going to do E to generate a new bone
And now I'm going to go to my foot
and I'm going to do it again to generate another new bone
So now this new bones I'm going to separate them
If I press split
if you see
if I try to move this bone
they all follow
But now if I do right click and split
now they are separated from the from the entire chain
And I'm going to do that with both of them
So now I have these two independent bones that are floating there that are going to be used as a reference
This one on the top
we're going to put names to know to get confused and we're going to call it poll and this would be right knee in the front
You can pull whatever names you do
pull R
knee F makes sense
And then this bone is going to be called foot because the foot and this is going to be on the right front
so R and f
right and front
okay
So now what we want is this little bone to control the chain of the leg
And there's a little trick before doing it
I can move this knee a tiny bit to the front and already indicating how my knee is going to bend because if not
it can sometimes make a mistake and bend backwards a bit
If I was how those animals bend backwards
flamingo like a flamingo
yeahor maybe this duck could be bending backwards
that's mistake
Okaythe moves doesn't
So we're going now go into post mode
Somehow this happens post mode and I'm going to select this bone
which is my foot
and I'm going to shift click and I'm going to select this one that is going to be the end of my chain
Whatever you are doing
you always want to do the end of the chain bone
And now I'm going to do right click and I'm going to actually
it's not right click here
I think it's in post
We're going to do inverse kinematics
add Ik to bone
So I'm going to do that
thatand then it's asking me again
act to active bone
So as soon as I do it
let's see what is happening
This bone got turned into yellow
This bone
nothing is showing
And then when I click in this bone
you see that there's t​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌his yellow arrow
This is telling us the beginning of the Ik
so this is telling us there is a chain of things happening
and this is going until the very end of the chain
So when you move that initial foot right back to the tailor is going to move
the entire car is gonna move
and this doesn't make any sense
this is not looking good
So what we want is when I move this tailbone
this bone will move
but that said
how long is this chain
I see one bone and two bones right Now
if I go here and if I go into my options
you can see that the program automatically added an Ik bone constraint and the chain length is 0
Zero for this program means infinite
So we didn't select how long it was
So it was up to the very end of the BU
But now we're going to do a chain of two
So let's see what happens
Actually I'm going to do first chain of three because sometimes people make a mistake and they do a chain of three
So if I do a chain of three
when I now move this bone
things look good
but my chain is a too long
So I'm getting this kind of a strange thing in which my
it's moving like the bone that it should be not moving
Let's make instead of that
a chain of two
And now we're going to see that my entire system up
I need to move this one
My entire system starts making more sense
I'm going to deactivate transparency and going to go to this mode
and I'm going to see that now my me is Ben in a much more natural way
The only problem I have is that I have no ability to say where my knee is pointing
And for that
we usually use poles
And if you remember we had selected
we made one bone that was called pole
our knee
So let's see how we can do to use that as a poll
We can go to my options here
my Ik
and you see here it says pull target
the pole target I can select and I select
And but the first thing I selected is this armature
It is just the armature
but now we need to select within the armature which bone
And if I write here
pole or knee is one that we generated before and we need one extra step
And is that the pole angle is always wrong
but 99% of the time
if we put 90%
it will work
So as soon as I put 90%
now my yellow arrow is pointing at the end of this chain
And now you can see that when I go here
now I can use this pole to select where my knee is pointing at
very nice
So this is basically how I rigged the Carter
I did this for every single of the legs
and then you can say
ohbut it's looking ugly
I don't like that I'm seeing these ugly bones
That'sthat's just visuals
but the visuals that I made in the project that I made to make it more pretty is I did a few things
I went into my object mode and I generated a mesh
You can make whatever mesh you want
In this case
I can make a circle
I can make it a bit smaller
So that's going to be my circle reference
And I can make it disappear because I don't want to see my render
This is going to be simply a geometry I'm going to use because now when I go into my post mode
I can select any of my bones and I go here into my options
and you see a area that it says view for display
I can select that this display as a custom object
and I can select that circle
I can do the same with the bone that is at the end of the chain and I can select that circle my pole is going to be this circle and my pole is going to be and my foot is going to be a circle as well
Sometimes because the pole
you know
for whatever reason
you can make a different type of circle that looks a bit different or you can as well rotate it
translate it
You can do
for example
change the scale and make an elongated like that
and as long as you make all your posts to look the same
people understand what's going on exactly
And the other thing I did is all the bones that were not relevant
and I didn't want the people to be playing with
I just selected height
so I don't show them
So now it's a very magical thing
which I only saw in this circle
and people can change the length of my knee if you are having a bit of a bend
you see that this is not bending very well
this is not perfect
This can be corrected with doing weights
But what I recommend that the problem happened here is that probably the bone was a bit too low
so the bending is not happening in a completely linear way
so I would have put the bone a bit higher
so there's a bit more straight leg
But in reality
because of how this entire thing is made
this is good enough for whatever we are the purpose right now
So you'd recommend rather than using the weight painting
which we learn about in the longer course
you'd recommend more focusing on the preparation 100 preparation is much better than spending a lot of time painting
If you need to paint
you know
we explain in the other course how to do it
But most of the times I forget about painting
I just do it with a bit of preparation
And now that we learned this
want how I'm going to delete this and I'm going to show how I made the tail And the tail is much more simple than people think
If you now understand how this works
I'm going to do it simply with a cylinder and I'm going to make a few
I know actually I can go into my cylinder
I'm going to deactivate this
I'm going to now select my cylinder
I'm going to rotate it 90 degrees and I'm going to scale this
Oh
why is my cylinder rotated like that
Okay I'm going to delete it
and I'm going to start by cylinder again
mes cylinder
and actually I can do it in the options here
so I'm going to do a bit of depth that looks a bit like a tail already
and I'm gon na be a bit thinner
okay
And I can do a vertical because I can explain how it works here
So the way to do my tail is like this
I'm going to go to my edit mode
Of course
in order for my tail to bend I'm gon na need some cuts because even though right now it's not gon na work
it's one of the problems sometimes people have is that they forget that you need cuts for this to work
Click and now I'm going to do number of cuts and I'm going to do a few of them
So this is quite soft
okay
I'm going to do 23
that's going to give me quite a lot of bending
remember that then you can put everything inside the subdivision surface
Okay
so now I'm going to go to my object mode
I'm going to look in front and I'm going to add armature
and I'm going to add a single bone
I need to activate transparency to see that bone and let's put the beginning of my chain
I'm going to go in here and I'm going to start extruding in my edit mode
I'm going to start extruding
What I can do is I can do extrude with E
and I think if you press X
no set
If I press set
I make sure that I'm moving only in the set axis
so I'm gon na do a chain of bones
maybe I don't need the chain to be that long because I'm gon na get bored
So e set and how do you decide how big to make the bones here
I guess you don't want to overlap the geometry
the size of the bones is not relevant
is more of an indication is the way the program is representing them
so it's fine if I made them so big that they overlap the geometry
it's only an indication from the program
So the distance between the volumes
the more volumes we have
the smoother the chain is going to be
but of course our program is going to get a bit slower
But yeah
that's a very good question because at the beginning
I thought that the size of the bone was relevant
but in reality you can go here and change
TheI think
in custom properties is
ohmaybe not in here
but I'm sure if you go into post mode
we can select the bone and I can go and check how it looks
And if I change how it looks and I can make a custom object or chase how it looks and it could be smaller
it's not really relevant to the end of the end
the end result
Okay
now that we have that there
we're going to do exactly what we did before
I'm going to select my cylin cylinder
I'm going to call it tail
and I'm going to select cylinder armature
At this point
probably everyone is an expert on this
you're just going to do right click parent with automatic weights
And now my tail is inside my armature
If I go to post mode
I can just rotate and my tail is rotating
And if it's not smooth enough
it's because remember that we can just go into object mode and add
I can select that and add a modifier and I can add a subdivision surface with a couple of subdivisions and I can shade it all smooth
and I can be this mode
And now you can see that when I go into my post mode
I can select any of my bones and I can start rotating and it's looking nice
and it's smooth for my tail
But the thing that we wanted is to be able to select the last point of the chain of my tail and be able to move the entire tail
And it's exactly the same that we've done before
So oh I'm going to
I don't know why going
but I deleted some of the subdivisions
I'm going to do say the smooth
but I wanted to reset the armature
By the way
if you want to reset the armature
you don't do it like that
I did it wrong
just like all the ones with A
and then you go post transform
Ohno
clear transform all
And now all my transformations get completely cleared
So what I'm going to do now is I'm going to do exactly the same
I'm going to go to edit mode
I'm going to generate a copy of this bone
I'm going to select this
I'm going to split it
So now this is split
and now I'm going to go into my pose mode and select this bone
select this last part of the chat
and we're going to go into pause or pose inverse kinematics
I k to 1
and as soon as I added
we have this that turn yellow and you can not see it
but there is a yellow line that is going all the way to the end of my chain
In this case I'm not even going to have to say in the program how long is my chain because it just went to the very end of my chain and that's what I wanted
So now if I move this in post mode
let's see how this magically my entire tail works
And it looks like a tail
that's great
So does it always
the chain always goes automatically to the final bone
always to the final one
So in this case
because it was good
that's fine
If I wanted the beginning of my tail to be a bit straight and only having in the end bend
I can always select the bone that is telling me the length of the chain
Go here and make my chain length of
for example
you know
You can
I think people now can start understanding what the system is
You know
now if I move it
only the end
if my chain is moving and at the beginning it's completely straight
It's great to see that because I'm kind of imagining what crazy characters people are coming up
Yeah
this looks a bit like you could make one of these things that sometimes they are in America to sell cars and you see them in the UK as well
that they move with the movement of the wind
I love
Yeahand the cool thing about this
of course
you can add a pole to select where this looking at
like we did it before
but I think with this
we have explained enough how to do this rigging on the character
I hope you all enjoyed it
I'm go
go and just show the project one second before
Remember that you are going to be able to access this project the same thing that happened by the way with this
this is just if you go into post mode
these ones that are controlling the head and the body are simply the same Are I selected one of the bones and I made it look a bit like that
so it looked a bit prettier
The same with the head is exactly the same
and by the way
you can see that here
my tail has a bit of grease pencil that is attached to the tail that actually was included when I did pairing with automatic weight and automatically blender applied the weight to the tail and included the grease pencil
which is amazing
A little treat
So I think now at this point
everyone knows how to make every single element on this
I really think that you should instead of trying to copy exactly the illustration from Noah and the version we made in 3D
you should make your own version
Yeahwe'd love to see more people's illustrations appearing here
moving around them in 3D
In the next lesson
we're going to check another illustration
and I think it my favorite
I mean
the three of them are my favorites
but like I really love the translation that happened in the next illustration
Thank you and really well done to know albrech again
thank you very much