So welcome to this illustration from Rose Kaya
And I love this one
I love as well that in this one
as well as having the illustration
we have a beautiful animation
YeahI love seeing the 3D animation mixed with the 2D animation
I think that's something people were really interested in and seeing that frame by frame
puffs of smoke along with this really smooth 3D is really lovely
Yeah
and you know
like when we received this illustration that we have in here
we had to decide what were we going to do
Like we didn't know which parts were going to be 3D
which parts were going to be 2D
and maybe even which parts were not present
I think that I really love how this illustration was very flat
but it had a bit of texture
a bit of gradients made here with this noise
And I thought it was a shame if we were going to lose that in 3D
On the other hand
I thought that many of the shapes
including the wheels and the motorbike and how this felt ter would be a shame not to show that we had made it in 3D
So it was a different approach is very different from Noi
which we made an illustration that looked exactly like the original in this one
We did a reinterpretation
something that I really love about this illustration as well
There's all of the details that are inside of it
seeing how she has on the motorbike
that little flower sticker and the cross there
And I think the colors are really nicely contained
but it's full of detail and I think that's what looks super nice when you get into 3D
Yeah
when we go here
back to the illustration
see that everything got translated
Actuallyevery single element ended up being there
You know
the flowers are there
the bird is there
and even the elements that were in the illustration
like the little details are just appearing on this
And to generate the effect of the speed happening
And those are simply some grease pencil layers that are being multiplied again and again
and we are using the same effect
The time of to change at which time they appear
So we only animated 1
and then we repeat it again and again
And we are generating that speed in the illustration
just like you did with the little Zs
in exactly the same effect
The other thing that we have
ohby the way
I love that you can put in misshaped materials
And if you are using Eev
the only thing you need to go is I actually right now
Now we activate it in cycles up
but like we can use Eev all the time
I did a cycle test
but like when we go in evol see here you have bloom
So when I have bloom
what I can do is if I have an emission material
I can make it to look as if it's just glowing my entire scene
You can only do this in evol
can not do it in cycles
In cycles
you need to do it with post processing
But I love that you can do this effect in evol
and it works so well
and it's generating this super cool look for illustrations
If the lights are just emanating so much
The other details I want to talk about is how the hair was created
The hair was created simply using metal metabolism
if you've never used them before
are super useful
I'm going to just save this illustration
make a new project for a second
and I'm going to delete my cube and my metabolism basically work like this
I'm going to add a metabolite
add a ball
and you can just create copies or either you create a copy Ctrl C
Ctrl V of the metabolism
then you move here
or you can as well if you are in edit mode
if you select the object
you can do Shift D and just start creating copies of it
But you see
as I'm creating copies I'm generating this soft transition between my shapes and then inside the metabolite here
you can change how much the resolution happens on the viewer and on the render
So you could have less resolution on the viewer if your computers have been a slower and have a smaller distance on the render
So it's
I mean
the smoother when you are done with the project
But you can see the shorter I make my resolution
the smoother and smoother the stuff looking
So now that we understand how the hair was created
we're going to be seeing how the hair was animated
not only the hair
but many of the elements you see that we are having here
Even I love the effect that is happening on the little bird
I love looking at it from close up because you can see the movement from the wind
And some people might think that that's very complex to animate
but that's so simple
The only thing we are applying there and I can select my bird
I can have it here
And the only thing I'm doing with my bird is I'm going to add a wave effect
And you can see here exactly the settings I can show them here
I just play it with them
You know
you have a speed
you can make it animate is lower
This effect as well is cycling
that means like cycling or cycling
I don't cycling
so it's repeating all the time and again and again
And we can do different weight
So I could do something very saturated with here
I'm starting to show and break the effect
or I can make it quite soft and you can see that this effect obviously works better when I have more subdivisions
but I was trying to do not that many subdivisions for to be able to play well
But then you can do more subdivisions for the render when we finish the illustration
when we go to render it out
you can have more subdivisions
But in reality at this distance
I thought that there was no need for more
You're getting that wind effect
and then I went through every single element
including these arms
and I just did the same
I applied the wave and it is generating this effect looking like the clothes are flowing with the wind
That's really lovely
How did you know about the wave effect
How did you think to use that one specifically
OhI was just starting playing with them
I was just going around being like
what can I use to not to have to animate frame by frame something and it to look good
And I found that wave effector
like there are so many effectors
and sometimes I Google things when I don't know
like I haven't used some of them
but I think that if they are
there is because at some point they will become useful
So I don't think you should learn them all
I think you can incorporate them as you go
Yeahthat makes sense
It's really lovely as well to see because I feel like it looks exactly like I would imagine the 3D result would look
but so much more seemed to be trial and error
Yeah
and the other thing that we have in here is these papers
And these papers are also using the wave effector
You can see that they are bending in the air
but they have something else as well as the wave effector that you can see that there are all these lines that are following paths
And this follow path is super easy to make and is very useful
For example
we're making a car that is going around the circuit
Or if we are making
in this case
some papers that are flying from the motorbike
So in order to have them
you can see that each of these papers are having in here in the object constraint
I have a follow path
You see that there
and then I have an offset on the follow path
so I'm gon na do it in a new project so people know what I was doing
So I'm going to make I'm going to make
instead of a cube I'm going to make a plan so people can see already how this was made
And I'm going to go to my edit mode and remember the wave effector doesn't work if there are no subdivisions
So you need to do click and do a few subdivisions and then click and do a few subdivisions
If not
is not going to show
Now I'm going to go into my modifiers and I'm going to add a wave modifier
And now hopefully
if everything goes well
when I go to object mode
we already have that effect
you know
And the wave modifier
you can see that now is applying from the middle
You can only do one of the sides
So if now you do
one of the sides is applying like a flat
Okay
so I have my plane flying already
what is the next thing I need to do
The next thing I need to do is my plan to be following some path
So I'm going to add a curve and I'm going to add a the Seer curve
and I'm going to tap
press top and scale it
I'm going to scale it
and maybe I'm going to rotate it because I think it makes more sense to look a bit more
Like with Ctrl
I can do increments of 5 and I'm gon na have
Imagine that this is the beginning of my motorbike tour is going to be there
and then my paper is gonna go and fly up and then go down
I could
you know
change the shape
Just pressing E
I can make more points and I can move them as well in the 3D space so I can make some of the papers to go backwards and some to go front
And now the only thing I need to do is go to my plane
go to my constraints
and then I can do a follow path
Where I do follow path
here you are
and now I need to save the target
The target is of the Sr curve that I have in there
And now I did
I did the follow path on my the year curve
You see the accident I did
you can see that the effect applied in the busier curve
but in reality I should do it in my plane
not in the busier curve because the plane
what is gonna follow the path
So now I'm gonna do the same again
The plane should be the one having this gear
It looks like the gears from a bicycle
And now I'm going to select my VR curve
So now I know that my paper is following my VCR curve
If I do
offset is going to go from one place to another
fantasticand then I have a few different things
you know
I can do follow curve
That means that now the paper is pointing towards the curve
So it curves with the curve
That's looking much better
So if you have it moving a bit up and down like that
your paper is going to do the exactly
So I don't need to be rotating myself
the paper
the paper now is working well
And then the next thing I can do is add a keyframe at the beginning in my offset and a keyframe
I'm only going to do this 20 frames
So I can add another keyframe at the end
There we are
put another keyframe
And now when I play I'm getting it by effect
Fantasticand you just have that several times to have lots of papers from
I have several times what I did
by the way
because I know that at the beginning I wanted them to appeare from the
from the box
from the little folder
and I didn't want to have any problems like
I don't know
having to come out from the folder and it's not visible
So the only thing I do is that they scale them up
You see at the beginning
they are really tiny and then they scale them up very quickly
and then they continue through the scene
Sometimes those simple solutions are enough because your brain covers the rest
you see how you just imagine that probably they are appearing
but in reality
it's just a simple scale
You completely do
And at the end
how is it that they disappeared exactly the same
When they reach the end
You can see here in each of my planes
I get to the end and I scale them down completely
and not only I scale them down
I think actually what I do as well
as well as scaling them down
you can change the disability of the paper
And rig​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌ht now
I don't know exactly what it is
I'm gon na try to show here
You see here I do a scale down
so I have a few keyframes here
97I started scaling them
but the other thing I do
and I don't know why it's disappearing
Ohit disappears because then invisibility
I have a keyframe saying
showing viewport
showing render
and then in 100
I made that only two keyframes that doesn't show in viewport or renders
and there is a bit of a CLT in this program because now when I get here
all the keyframes disappear because the program is like I'm not seeing anything
And that's why it's kind of a bit confusing
And now I need to select it again
but it's simply that I told the program to make the optic disappear
That's a clever trick
okaynow that we have that I can tell you that the rest was done
the arms were made with the same cube technique
starting from spline that we've done in our course on how to brake
how to model in Blender
So if you've done that
you have it and the motorbike started from a cube
Wheels are simple toruses that are in there and the smoke was done with frame by frame animation in a grease pencil layer in which I use a fill in white
Okay
like we've just learned how to do
Yeahand the only little thing that we have that we haven't really covered much in this course
we will have an entire course dedicated at some point on how to do painting
on painting textures is that we paint all these textures in the program
but so far I had to use a little We're going to put the link of the brushes we use
we bought them
it's only 5 dollars
we bought them from someone else that they sell them on
I have don't know if it's gum road or another of this website
but we want to generate at some point a library inside
but at the school
so people don't have to pay those 5 dollars
But so far
the only thing I did is using those brushes to generate these little dots
So I'm going to link
I'm going to put a link to the brush we use from there
but in order to do that
like we've done in other courses
we simply selected the geometry where you be unwrapped like we did in the beginning of this course
And then we painted on top with the texture
So that was basically it
The rest is just spending time and putting some love on it
Yeah
it's really nice to see that all of the same techniques that we've been teaching in every course are applied to this illustration and even if every character looks so different they all come from the same cube
I really hope that people do something that I love doing
This is such a privilege to be able to access this file
So I hope you go through the file and start exploring experimenting
Sometimes even I find that sometimes people ask us questions they like
ohwhy is this thing not being used
And it's because on the way of making it
we ended up just getting rid of something
So I think it's good sometimes to see how the process of the creation of this was made
because not everything is being used
not everything that we tried work
And I think that's the way you should do when you are making your illustrations and turning them into 3D
A lot of experimenting
Try to get all the knowledge you've been getting through all courses and applying it to your straight
I think that's completely true
And if you're trying to make something that looks new and unique
then you probably have to do some experimentation yourself
Yes100 percent
and we can't wait to see all of your results
please share them with us
And big well done again to Rose Kai for her beautiful TD character
And in the next lesson
we're gonna take a completely different style of illustration that was done using Gris pencil
but I think that was very
a good example of how grease pencil is so flexible because the other illustration just doesn't look at all of these ones
We'll see you then
bye