​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌​​​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌​​​‌‌​‌​‌​​‌‌‌‌​‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌​‌‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌‌‌‌‌​​‌‌​‌‌‌​​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​‌‌‌‌​‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​​‌‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌‌​​‌​​‌‌​‌​‌‌‌​‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌‌Hello and welcome to our third illustration here from Natalia Angeli scroa
And he had a very different style
I'm going to show here the style that she had
Her illustration was like this
and I really loved how this illustration had so many little details
like all these dots to generate shadows
I love the colors of the illustration
how graphical the character is
but of course
it was a big challenge
You know
at the beginning we were thinking
are we going to translate like these outlines in the illustration
And we tried
we tried different things and this is the final result
Yeah
I really like the position as well this character is in
It's kind of interesting translating that position into 3D
I think
because the proportions of the face is slightly different from how a realistic face would be
You know
the positioning of the mouth and the one cheek being slightly bigger than another
And I think it's interesting to see that translation so directly
Yeah
to be honest
this illustration works very well if you rotate it even here
But if you start going this way
starts breaking
you see around this area
just like it doesn't look good
Like I think up to from here to here is looking quite good
And I like that
I like that allows for some level of movement around
but in the moment it what it breaks
it just breaks
Okay
let's look at some of the things we did
This animates a bit
We have some animation here for the text that's appearing saying hello
And also we have some animation happening in the cable
And I love that we also have some animation happening
some boiling happening on the on these hat that looks like a
is this an apple
I thought maybe as well could be a Toto
I don't know
it's some fruit
But like we are having this illustration with a lot of boiling effects happening
But the main thing how everything started with with modeling and the way to do it with modeling was just I went into a front view
I started with a cube and I slowly started extruding using the techniques we use
Everything started from my cube
And then in the moment where I was comfortable with how it was looking
but it was not perfect
I just applied all the subdivisions of the cube
and then I went into sculpting
And then when we arrived into sculpting
I started
I only used cree-english bit of this elastic deformation grab
and then I used a lot of inflate
So I started doing for the breast
I started doing a bit of inflation and pinching it to just have all the modifications I wanted
And then for this neck
for example
I just started from a cylinder and I extruded some of the corners of the cylinder to generate this flower effect and the same for the head
You know
you see that this is exactly the same
There's a bit of inflation here
a bit of Cree inflation here
The nose started from a cube
I just want you to know that there were no tricks here
This is only just going bit by bit sculpting all the elements
I was about to say that it sounds not real
it sounds like there must be some kind of hidden trick somewhere
but that's exactly how it was made
And I think that can be quite a nice thing for people to realize as well
The more that you practice and the more that you understand looking at 3D objects in the real world as well
the better you can understand modeling
And you're wondering
how is grease pencil useful in this
Project is useful in many ways
One of them is that
for example
you can have this boiling in this cable
This is was drawn in completely flat way
And then because of how a grosbeak
you can then go into sculpt mode
do your grab mode
and start kind of bending the cable and putting it behind the hand
And I love that
I love that grease pencil allows for these 3D
it's last to the movement of the objects
AlsoI love that you can have these shadows that are just little dots that I have sputter around here and they boil
and that effect
I think is beautiful and a 3D illustration I've never seen before
to be honest
I've never seen something like that
Same here
this you see
you can have all of these effects that are applying
they're just applying a noise
but then I have have all the things if I go to my final render mode
and I have I have it here and that should be look like that I'm gonna deactivate my scene like in a scene world because I just want to use the automatic lighting
I can apply
Do you see that there is this double layer that it looks yellow and it looks red on the front and it goes with the animation
it works completely fine that is coming from this original illustration and it's so easy to do so the only thing you need to do is
and remember that in order to see those effects
you need to be viewport shading mode
But if I select it here
one of the effects that I have is called shadow
but a shadow can be any color
so it's just a creative way of using the shadow you made the black
it's just a shadow that you have for the effect
But if you make your shadow that low color
subtlyyou're having the look that the original illustration had
and I love that type of flexibility
I'm still discovering how to use the kind of mill option that grease stencil has because look at all these effects for sure at some point it's going to be useful to have this pixelate effect that is going to pixelate our entire illustration know like different effects can be used in different situations
And I think that what I like is just looking at them and then discovering slowly when are they useful or when I'm gon Na use them
YeahI think that's really interesting too
and sometimes you might accidentally come across something like that pixelate
and then at some point you'll think
ohyeah
I remember that all exactly
If you're wondering why didn't use this effect like wrist pencil for the eyes is because so far it doesn't work well with transparency
So when I drew it
then I couldn't see a bit of the eyes through the transparency
I wanted to be able to see it there
So I did it with a normal
painting it with a brush
I just UV unwrapped the entire head
and then I painted bit by bit
And the same he things here for the for my banana
I did the same
And then for my hand
I simply made the same effect
I just made some bones and I can just show here with transparency
And I just made some bones
and then I parented them with automatic weights
And then I have suddenly this hand that it's actually raked
which it's not something that we are
you know
like we're showing off much
But in reality
you could just rotate these fingers and they can rotate with the illustration
You know
like we could Riga
make our our animation
a little animation with the character
Maybe it's kind of coming to grab the phone or doing whatever
Besides that
this illustration
I think is quite simple in the way was animated
The only thing that maybe some people are going struggle with is just doing this frame by frame animation in which I transform this speech bubble into a circle
But that's just done in frame by frame
Maybe at some point we're gonna talk a bit more about different effects to animated transitions or fire or effects in frame by frame
But there are so many references on the internet that you can find out your favorite style of animation
I recommend looking at them frame by frame
You can download them and go frame by frame and check how it was made
Great idea
Besides that
do you have any other questions about this one
I was wondering how you chose the level of detail to add on to the 3D character because there are some extra details in the 2D
say on the banana or in the hair there
and how did you choose how much to put in 3D
This is about your personal choice
Would you like
would you think that is gonna work
I don't have an answer for that
but I do agree at some point when we started putting some of those lines in the hair
it started feeling 2 BC 2 crowded
you know
3D and 2D don't work the same way
So it's a personal choice
The same thing with
you know
the shadows here are not painted
are the natural shadows that occur with the ambient occlusion
but the shadows in here are painted and they are boiling and that's just a decision
it's an artistic decision that might be different
You know
if Natalia starts making this illustration in 3D herself
she might have different decisions
YeahI think it's interesting for people to start actually thinking of the 3D illustration
how it translates from the 2D illustration
what the differences and similarities are and how you're keeping the same spirit
that's sort of what we wanted to cover a lot in this course as well
not only the technical aspects of how you model certain things and how you use the grease pencil
but also what you're actually deciding to translate and how you're doing that
YeahI think a lot of people think that the technical bit is the most relevant one or that there is some secret button or something that turns things into 3D that's not the case
You know
we go case by case and that's why the illustrations look unique and special and they end up
you know
if this
even if they started been made by Natalia
it has in the end a bit of a cabeza patata look because we transformed it and I think that that's an important thing
the more you improve as a 3D artist
the more you're going to be able to put your personal touch on everything you make
even if you're translating someone else's illustration
you're going to be able to put to a little detail
probably we went more pastel with this colors than in the original illustration from Natalie because of how we like these pastel colors
the color palette kind of gets slowly shifted and moved towards what you like and I really want people to start exploring 3D in that way
you know
remember 3D is not something that touch from the rest of the art if you like something you can apply it to 3D I completely agree and with that thank you so much for following up here
this was so nice to have this illustration from Natalia
thank you so much for sending it and well done everyone
thank you for following along with the course and please share your results and even share your 2D illustrations
if you have any questions for us or for any of the other students about recommendations for how you might transform it into 3D
just let us know
yeahand please continue sharing your work
It's just how we learn
What people want is how we discover if actually people understood what was happening
And we love seeing translations like this
love to see everyone's do the illustrations
transforming 3D using grease pencil
Thanks everyone
bye