- [Instructor] In this video,
we will have a quick look
at the course content
and how to use it.
At this stage, you should have
downloaded all the content.
You will find a read-me.txt file
that I invite you to read
with some legal informations.
And for each chapter, you
will find a zipped file
or multiple zipped files.
I suggest you unzip those
chapters in a specific folder.
The zipped file will
include all the videos
but also all the English
subtitles of those videos.
One of the zip provided
include all the course files.
You must unzip those file
in the dedicated folder.
Simply right click on the zip file
and choose Extract to
course files folders.
You will find a dedicated folder
for each chapter of the course.
And those dedicated folders
includes all the Blender files,
textures and whatever
resource you will need
during those chapters.
It's important to keep the structure
and hierarchy of those folders
as it is in the zipped file
because of the most files are linked
or are sourcing textures
with a relative path
into those folder.
You will find one Blender file
or multiple Blender file
per lecture or lesson.
This way you can choose whether to start
from the beginning with your own animation
or to use one of the provided file at,
or to use one of the provided file
at a given point in time.
You will also find video reference
for the specific exercises,
and any other resources
used by the Blender file.
Let's have a quick look
through the course contents.
Two is a must-watch
because this is where you will learn
how Blender deals with data.
And since your job will
be to animate those data,
you'd better be aware of how it works.
This is also the chapter
where you will have your first experience
with the animation tool
and how to read and use them.
The graph editor is often confusing
for beginners animator,
so it's very important that
you watch those videos.
This way you'll be prepared
to jump into chapter three.
It's the most extensive
chapter of the course
where you will learn how
to use an armature rig
to perform your first
simple polished animation,
to manipulate your first character,
create a full set of animations,
and then combine them to
reproduce this short animation.
If you're a beginner
or have a bit of experience
animating in Blender,
then I advise you to
follow this whole chapter
and do the exercises multiple time
until you get comfortable.
I will repeat this a lot during the course
but animation is an art form.
Failing is totally normal,
and only practice will make you progress.
In chapter four, we will focus
on learning other animation technique.
We will create a new set of animation
using this robot rig.
And we will see how we can use constraints
and space switching
to generate additional
motion onto our character,
getting convincing result
in a matter of minutes.
We will apply this to a walk cycle,
this artillery shot
and also to shoot rockets
from a moving robot.
This way, you will be able
to reproduce all the
animation in this short movie.
And for those of you eager to learn
how to create the FXs and the environment,
I've already published
and will published
additional tutorials for free
on my YouTube channel regarding
those specific subjects.
In chapter five and six,
you will be introduced
to character locomotion
and body mechanics
through fully detailed lessons
on how to build a run
cycle and a walk cycle.
We will go deeper into reference analysis,
and I will try to teach you
how to correctly study your reference
and get the best from them.
From there, I will guide you
through the whole blocking stage,
'til the final polishing.
In chapter seven, I will
teach you all my techniques
to get great poses
from deep reference analysis
to stylization technique
to push your poses
and the appeal of your
character way further.
Finally, in chapter eight,
the most advanced chapter,
you will apply all what you have learned
during the course to create
this combo animation.
And I'll be there over eight hours
of video to teach you everything
from the base blocking
to creating the breakdowns,
the blocking plus, the
first pass of spline
to the final polishing stage,
and adding some details and FXs
so that you can create a great
and polished animation that you'll be able
to proudly feature in your
demo reel or portfolio.