- [Instructor] Before
we jump into animation,
I'd like to show you my table.
It's made of some exotic wood
and it's very useful too.
Nope, it's not a course about table
but I'd like to show you some resources
that could be useful.
The first one is obviously
"The Animator's Survival Kit"
by Richard Williams.
This is a classic.
I guess all the animators have
this book in their shelves,
and to be perfectly
honest, it doesn't get old.
But you will find in there tons
of lesson about the
principles of animation
and so many drawings that
are still used to this date
to teach animation.
It also comes with a lot of stories
about animation a few decades ago.
But definitely, a must-have.
The next book, which is one
of my favorite is "Drawn to
Life" by Walt Stanchfield.
This is a book that was recommended to me
by my animation mentor, Jeremy Collins,
and while it's mostly focused on drawing,
everything in there is
appliable to animation,
especially when it comes to staging
and creating great poses.
The last book I'd like
to advise is a classic.
It's "The Illusion of Life"
from Frank Thomas and Ollie Johnston.
Beyond the educational content,
it's fascinating to learn stories
about Disney, the studio that
has almost created animation.
While you don't need those book,
I do believe that having them
and reading them will really help you
to dive into the art of animation.
There are tons of quality book
about animation and drawing,
and it's always good to get a step back
from the screen and take
a good book and chill.
I'd like to recommend
you also a YouTube video
by Alan Becker about the
12 principles of animation.
It has more than eight million of views,
and this is definitely because
it's one of the best video
about the 12 principle of animation.
It's short, super well
illustrated and explained.
A must-watch.
And finally, I truly advise
you to use SyncSketch.
SyncSketch is an online media player
that allows you to read
almost every video format,
and allows you to draw on screen,
to leave notes and to create
reviews and share them.
Definitely one of the best
platform to share your reviews
or get feedback from other animators.
This is the tool I use every day
for all my reviews,
and also in this course
whenever I'm analyzing any reference.
If you're looking for an offline solution,
I advise you Keyframe Pro media player.
You can get a free version of it.
There is also a paid version of it
with additional functionalities,
but personally, I prefer
to use SyncSketch.