- Hi everyone, this is
Pierrick from P2 Design.
I'm so happy to welcome you to Alive!,
the animation course in Blender.
In this training course,
we will learn the tools,
the fundamentals, and principle
while manipulating and animating.
As any other art form, you
won't get good at animation
by watching video tutorials.
You do need to practice
as much as possible.
I'm here to teach you my best practices
to help to learning and
improving your animation skills.
Videos are shot to offer the
best learning experience.
I advise you to watch each video once
and then rewatch them and follow along.
Each chapter will focus
on a specific theme,
principle, or level of animation.
Whatever your skill level,
I advise you to take this
course from the beginning,
because they are big chances
you will learn something,
or at least it will
refresh your animator mind.
In the next video,
I will go through the current
content of the course,
but the course will be also updated
and I will add the more
content through free updates.
The course come with a ball rig,
a little police squirrel character rig,
a Battle mech rig,
and the character Trident.
You are free to use those rig
for your non-commercial projects.
You can post any of the
animation you will do
with those characters on your social media
or for your portfolio,
but you can't use these rigs
or any content of the course
for commercial project.
And you must not re-distribute
or share any of the content
of the course, whether it's
Blende file or video files.
The course come with the
documentation where you will find
the list of all the videos included.
The difficulty level of each
chapter will be defined,
my freestyle level.
One star is beginner,
two star intermediate, and
three star is advanced.
You will also find links to the
different external resources
use in this course.
And they will be labeled
in a yellow color.
The video labeled in blue are theoretical
and tools focused video.
So I advise you to watch them
all and come back to them
often so that you don't miss any detail.
Let's jump into the next video
and see what's the content of
the course.