- In blender almost any
input can be animated.
Whether it's an object
position, the armature
or a character, or even
the color of an object.
Let's start simple with
object transformation.
In this chapter,
we will focus on object animation.
An understanding what an
object is, is crucial.
An object in blender is a simple container
and depending on what kind
of object you've added
it contains different objects datas
like mesh datas, camera
datas or empty datas.
These datas can be transferred
from one object to the other.
The important thing
regarding object animation
are not these object on mesh datas,
but the object transform data.
The position of the
object in space reserved
of its location transform.
Its orientation is based
on its rotation values
and size is the result
of its original size
multiplied by its current scale.
For example, acute mesh
that is one meter tall
and has a scale of 1.5
will be 1.5 meter tolls in the viewport.
These coordinates and
transform information
are affecting the origin of the object.
So while the mesh object
might look offset,
its position is not
linked to its geometry,
but only to its origin point.
So basically when transforming an object
you're just transforming its origin point.
We can see that everything rotates
or scale around or
toward the origin point.
We can see this doted line
between my mouse cursor
and the origin point of the object,
showing the pivot to use
for this transformation.
The current location of the object
is based on this origin point.
And it's measured based on the
origin of the blender scene
or the origin of old space.
So by default the origin of an object
is it's transformation pivot
and what we are going to animate.
even if an object seems to be made
of multiple object the
only important thing
for animation is its origin point.
You can use the different gizmos available
in the tool panel to
transform your object.
I generally prefer to use
the shortcuts G to move,
S to scale and R to
rotate combined with XYZ
and shift to constraint
around specific axis.
To summarize, any kind of
object has an origin point.
When animating an object,
we are manipulating its origin coordinate.
So manipulating an object,
is manipulating a single point in space.