- [Pierre] Now that we
have a better understanding
of object transformation,
let's start animating.
We will work on the classic bouncing ball.
Since I'd like to be able to
squash and stretch the ball
during the animation,
using its very center as a
pivot point is not ideal.
What I'd like to do instead
is adding its origin point
on the base of the ball
as this is going to be the
contacting point of the ball
with our imaginary ground.
So I will simply enter edit mode,
select every vertices
and press G, Z, and one
to move everything off
one meter on the Z axis.
When they get back into object mode,
I still have the same sphere,
but its origin is now on its place.
By default, the timeline in Blender
is in the bottom of the screen.
When you press space,
you can see that we are
playing an animation,
meaning that blender is going
through the different frame
of the document.
The play head in the
timeline indicate which frame
you are currently reading.
We can change the length of the animation
by setting the end frame
and the beginning frame.
I will set the beginning frame to zero
and end frame to 24.
When I press play,
we can see the play head
moving till frame 24
and getting back to frame zero.
This value indicates
you in the current frame
that is also alight on
top of the play head.
Animation in Blender
is basically recording
a different transformation
to an object in time,
meaning that we can recall the location,
rotation or scale of an
object on different frames.
To insert a key frame,
we simply need to have our
object selected in space
and press the I key.
A menu will pop up asking you
which kind of key frame you want to write.
Basically, do you want
to recall the location,
the rotation, the scale of the object
or a combination of those?
When I select location,
we can see that in the
transform channel of my object,
the location input turn to yellow.
And on the timeline, I get
a little yellow indicator
that tells me we have
recorded a key frame.
The key frame is a simple
registered value in time.
In our case, we have registered
or recorded the location
of our object on frame zero.
I will place to play head on frame 10
and move my object higher and
insert a location key frame.
Now I can see a new key
frame on my timeline,
and as soon as I move the
play head from left to right,
I can see sphere moving
from its previous position
on frame zero, to the next
position we have key framed
on frame 10.
We have recorded two position
on two different frame
and what we are seeing now
is Blender interpolating
or creating an interpolation
between those two position in space.
key frames can be manipulated
in the timeline as objects,
so you can move them using G,
you can press Shift + D to duplicate them.
You can box select them,
press X to delete them.
You can insert a new key
frame by simply hovering over
a transformed channel and pressing I
or right-clicking and choose
between insert key frame
or insert single key frame
if you just want to add a key frame
on the X location, for example.
Right clicking will also hollow you
to delete all the key frames
from the selected channel
or choose delete only single key frame
to delete a specific X, Y, or Z channel.
So let's start our exercise on frame zero
and insert a key frame.
Let's moved the play head to frame 12
and then move our sphere
or ball on the Z axis
by eight meters.
We can see that our transformed
channels have changed color.
The X and Y are still on green,
meaning that they have
been key framed previously
and their values haven't changed.
And the Z key frame as turned to orange,
meaning that we have
transformed the Z value,
but it's not recorded yet.
And this is a big warning,
because as soon as I
will move the play head,
my ball will return to its
first key frame position,
meaning that I have lost
the Z transformation
I've performed on frame 12
because I haven't recorded it.
So I will jump back to frame 12,
move my sphere of eight meters
and then press I to insert a key frame.
If I now scrub through
frame zero to frame 12,
I can see the ball rising in the air.
So transformed channels
are colored in yellow
whenever I'm hitting a key frame
and they are green whenever I'm in between
or during an interpolation.
I can select the first key frame,
press Shift + D and move
it onto the very last frame
so that I have a looping action.
To create a loop you just
have to make your first
and last frames being the same.
You can move from frame to frame
by pressing the left and right arrow.
Whenever you will press
the up and down arrow,
you will jump from the
previous to the next key frame.
Pressing Shift + right and Shift + left
will bring you to the very last
of the very first key frame.
You can perform all those
play head manipulation
using the UI in the
header of the timeline.
As we have seen before,
anytime while I'm moving
our object somewhere,
we need to insert a key frame
or we will lose the
manipulation we have done.
While it might be okay to press I
each time we perform a manual manipulation
on the single bouncing ball,
when you will start
animating a full character
with thousands of controls,
that's gonna be very tedious.
Fortunately, there is
the record button here
that allow us to auto
key any transformation.
As soon as I move the sphere,
you can see that new
keys are being recorded
for every channel of
this fear automatically.
Not that whenever you
are using this option
and moving your object in space,
you are warned that there
is an auto keying going on
on the top right corner
of your (indistinct)
As explained in the beginning,
we can keep frame mostly every
kind of value in Blender,
and it can be a color.
If I select the material
preview of my sphere
and I click this little rounded icon,
it will add a key frame
on the color value.
And I can find this key
frame on the timeline.
If I go a little further
now and change the color,
since the auto keying is on,
it will insert a new key
frame of this new color.
And whenever I scrub through the timeline,
I can see the color
interpolation of the sphere.
To summarize, we have seen
that we can use the timeline
to navigate through the different frames.
We have seen that we
can create a key frame
by recording any value, whether
it's a transformed channel,
a color or whatever we
want onto a specific frame.
Blender will automatically
create an interpolation
between two key frames.
Key framed values appear in yellow,
animated values appear in green
unrecording value changes
are shown in orange
and gray value are just unanimated values.