- Let's start blocking animation
of the bouncing ball.
Here, I still have my basic interpolation.
So with all the key frames selected,
I will press T and switch
to constant interpolation.
This way our ball will snap
on the different position
we have previously set.
The idea is not to get
disturbed by any interpolation
and focus on the timing and shapes
of our ball.
Since our animation will
be cycling upon 24 frame,
the frames zero and the frame
24 will be exactly the same.
So my timing will be a bit
off if I read both frame zero
and the frame 24.
So I will reduce the
length of my animation
from frame zero to frame 23,
talking about Shape.
We will here now look at
the squash and stretch.
If you're into animation,
I'm sure you already have heard about it.
If you look for squash and
stretch ball on YouTube,
you may find this video.
I put the link in the documentation .
When the ball gets thrown at
high speed on the surface,
and it touches it, it squashes.
With the power of the
impact, the ball get tighter,
but it's volume has to be preserved.
So it also gets larger.
But in this case,
squashing will bring
to us two information.
The power of the impact, and the softness
of the material of the ball.
Regarding our animation,
if we consider our frame
zero to be the frame,
where our object will touch the ground,
we can go like one or two frame forward
and start squashing the ball by scaling it
on the Z axis down,
but also scaling it on the X and Y axis.
This way we will have some
all volume preservation.
You can see here that the key frame,
hasn't been written,
as I need to enable the auto recording.
Since I haven't written any
scaling key frame previously,
you can see that the ball remained flat.
I will just press ALT
+ S to reset the scale
on the first frame and
on all the other frames.
As we have just created
the scaling key frames,
they have just been
added to our animation.
And so by default Lendo will
switch their interpolation
to basic.
So we can see that our location is still
in step mode, but we have
a scaling interpolation.
So I will select all the key frame press T
and set them to constant.
From there, we can work on
the stretching of our ball.
Stretching is physically
less obvious when we
are watching the tennis ball bouncing,
but it's yet still here.
So we can use stretching to
input physical information
to our bouncing ball,
but we can also use it to
input speed information.
If we look at the very beginning
of the video,
we can see that the ball is blurry
and it immediately translate
to us some speed information.
So why the ball
is probably currently perfectly round,
the way the camera is
capturing it forms some kind
of elliptic shapes.
And we have the same feeling
whenever we are watching
something that goes fast.
And if we watched a right hand
of the scientist,
we can see that his
fingers are also blurred
because his hand was moving very fast.
It makes his finger looks a little larger
and longer due to speed.
When an object is falling
and hitting the ground,
it is at its maximum speed
just before it hit the ground.
On the frame zero,
we can input stretching
information by scaling the ball up
and reducing it's scale on X and Y
to preserve its volume.
When the ball will leave the ground,
it will also be it's highest speed.
So I can duplicate frame zero and move it
on frame three or frame four.
The ball stretch, hit the ground, squash,
and stretch again when leaving the ground.
Just by looking those few frames,
we start to have the
feeling of the animation
of the ball.
And this is a very important input
whenever we will be
using the blocking method
is that you have to feel your animation
just through those poses.
As told before,
frame zero and frame 24 are
supposed to be the same.
So I will select frame zero,
press Shift + D to duplicate
it and move it on frame 20.
From frame zero to frame four the ball is
on the ground
and then it's leaving the
ground from frame four
to frame 24.
Timing wise, the ball should travel upward
and downward almost evenly.
So I can offset the
up position to frame 14.
This way, we have 10
frame and moving upward
and 10 frame moving downward.
As a more subtle detailed pass,
what we can do is slightly squash the ball
whenever it reaches its top position.
This slight modification
will translate the inertia
of the ball whenever it's slowing down
to its stop position.
Currently our blocking is bringing
the minimum information we need
to go to the next step.
All the extreme poses
of the ball are keyed
and we have a rough timing.
For this very specific exercise,
it could be enough for
me to go into spline
to go into the next step
of the animation process
but we can also input some more details
into the blocking stage
by inputting some intermediate
poses or in-between.
The in-between will help
us figuring out the spacing
of our ball whenever it's in the air.
Our ball is making a
eight meter high jump,
so I will move it in
between two, four meter
and I will clear the scaling.
Now, depending on where I will move
this key frame,
it will change the
spacing of the animation.
If I move this key frame
closer up to frame four
where it takes off, our
spacing will be larger
in the beginning of the jump than it is
whenever it's reaching the highest point
meaning that on frame seven,
the ball will go faster than on frame 10,
which is what we want because the ball
is leaving the ground at full speed.
So it will reach its mid-air
position before frame nine.
And when falling down it will
be at full speed on frame 24.
So it should be mid-air,
closer to frame 24,
than frame 14.
I know spacing can be a
bit complicated when you
are on the blocking stage
and it will be way more obvious
in the next video.
To summarize, during the blocking stage,
we key frame the extreme poses,
we make a rough timing paths,
we can use breakdowns and
in-between to input more
spacing and timing informations.
We can use squash and
stretch to input speed
and physical information.