- [Pierre] As any Blender editor,
you can navigate in the timeline
using your middle mouse.
You can move selected items by pressing G,
you can scale them using S,
which will push them
further from the play head.
But pressing R won't rotate the key frame.
What it will do instead,
it will all you to change
the key frame type.
Changing the key frame type
won't affect your animation.
It's only a visual
modification of your key frames
that may allow you to better
organize your animation.
I personally never use it
(drowned out by whooshing)
Pressing the zero key on the numpad
will center your timeline
position around the play head.
When you have some key selected,
pressing the dot key on the numpad
will frame or focus the selection.
Pressing the home key will
frame the whole animation
from the very first to
the very last key frame.
You can preview a part of
your animation by pressing P
and dragging and hold on the
section you want to repeat.
Press Alt + P to clear the preview.
You can activate the preview range
by clicking the clock icon
and then setting the
starting and ending frame.
You can set the beginning
of your animation,
pressing Control + Home.
And you can set the end by
When you activate the preview range
with the clock icon is
using Control + Home
and Control + Home, will set
the beginning and the end
of the preview range.
My timeline here is just showing me
the key frame of the selected items.
If I go into view and
uncheck only key frames
from selected object,
every key frame in the
scene will be displayed.
My character currently I've
a subdivision modifier.
If I go to the rendering properties,
I can see that simplify
has been activated.
It allows you to disable
every subdivision modifier
in the scene, increasing
the playback performances.
When deactivated, we can
see that my frame range
in the top left corner turned to red
meaning that Blender is not
able to reach the frame rate
I've set previously.
While this scene is supposed
to run at 30 frames per second,
here I am below 14 frames per second.
While it is not optimal,
Blender allow us to drop frames
so that we have a bit sort
of timing of the animation,
meaning that it will
drop some of the frame
to make sure that the
action run at the same speed
as if we were displaying
the 30 frames per seconds.
To allow this, just go
to the playback option,
to the no sync and choose
whether frame drop or AV sync.
We can see that the
animation timing has changed
and it's trying to catch
up with its regular speed.
Hopefully you won't
need to use this option
as I will try to provide
pretty low poly characters
to be animated, but it's
important to note it.
With Control + Shift, plus left click,
you can select all the keys
after or before the play head.
You can press B click and drag
or just left click and drag
to make a box selection.
The timeline is mainly here
to give you an overview of your animation.
I never use it to work
on my current key frame.
The summary line is
just here to let me know
if there are a key frame
on the current frame.
Here, we can see we have a key
frame on every single frame
from zero to 30.
This key frame belongs
to different controller
of our character and are
stored into an action
that is torn into the armature.
We will discuss about armature later on,
here I just want to show you
the IRO key of the timeline.
If I add a cube to the scene
and add key frames to this cube
you can see that now these
keys are also displayed
in the timeline.
Selecting a key on the summary
will select all the corresponding keys
of the armature and the cube.
This can be great to
offset a whole set of keys.
But if we want, we can
only move, for example,
the X location key of the cube.
Another great feature of the timeline
is that we can add markers.
While you can use them only
for organization's sake,
they can be very useful to switch camera.
When you add two camera
into your Blender scene
and press zero to go into camera view,
you can switch from
one camera to the other
into the scene options.
But if you will, you
can go in the timeline
and add a couple of markers.
You can add them pressing M or
going to Marker, Add Marker.
Now, with one of my camera selected
and one of the marker selected,
I will go to marker and
bind camera to marker.
Now I will select the second marker,
select the second camera
and repeat the process
or press Control + B in the timeline.
In the 3D viewport, pressing zero,
I will jump into camera view.
And when I will play the animation,
each time I will hit those marker,
Blender will automatically
switch to the bound camera.
This is way easier and cleaner
than trying to animate the camera.
To summarize, we have seen
that navigating the timeline
is close to navigating
any Blender editors.
We have seen a bunch
of different shortcuts.
And we have seen that we
can create different markers
in the timeline and bind
the multiple cameras to them
so that we can jump from
one camera to the other
directly through the animation.