- [Man] The previous video,
we have seen that object transform
is based on its pivot point.
Now let's see what we are
currently transforming.
As a Blender user and a 3D artist,
you know that in space we are
using the x-, y-, and z-axis
to move our objects.
We can find the representation
of those axes on the grid
with the x- and y-axes being
those red and green lines.
And also on the view widget
on the top right corner,
that allow us to switch
to the different views.
When an object is not transformed,
its position is aligned
with the world origin.
As soon as we input some
values into its x-coordinate,
for example, it will slide,
moving along the x-ward axis,
and it will behave the same whether
we are playing with the y or z value.
There is no limitation to those value,
they can be positive or negative,
and our object will move
left, right, up, and down,
or front and back, depending on those.
If I enter a value of
one and one on x and z,
we can see our object offset
from the center of our scene.
When it comes to rotation,
we don't rotate along an
axis, but around an axis.
If I rotate around the x-axis,
I can see my x rotation value changing,
and my object is currently
rotating around the red arrow.
And as always, the origin of the object
is used as the origin of the rotation.
If you have difficulties understanding
on which axis you are going to rotate,
you can activate the rotation gizmo
that make it more obvious.
If I now perform a scanning pressing S
and concentrate it on
the x-axis pressing x,
you can see that I'm scaling my object
along the selected axis.
The same on the y-axis
here or on the z-axis.
So, scaling is along the object axis.
One last option that
is available for object
is delta transform.
When I go into the object properties,
I can see this delta transform panel
that looks like the
classic transform panel.
Delta transforms behave
the same way as transform,
but they are added on top
of your transformation.
So you can see here, when
I add the delta transform
of one and one on top of my
one and one classic transform,
my object is offset to the
position two on x and two on z.
To be honest, I almost never
use the delta transform,
and I don't think we will be
using it during this course.
It can be useful whenever
you want to offset
an existing object animation, for example.
Let's say you have animate
an up and down motion
and you want to easily
offset it on the side.
Using the delta transform
will make your life easier.
But there are other way to do it,
and we will see that during the course.
To summarize, we have seen
that location, transformation,
and scaling are done along the axis,
while rotation is done around the axis,
and we can offset an animation
using delta transform.