- The time has come to
give the final touch
to our bouncing ball animation.
To clearly understand
what we need to modify,
I will change the frame
rate of the animation
by going into the document
option frame rate.
Here, we can find a bunch of preset
that will set the pace of our animation.
We are currently using the
classic 24 frames per second,
but they generally use
30 frames per seconds.
Here, I will select a custom frame rate
and I will set it to
five frames per second.
Now, when I play my animation,
it kind of play in slow motion.
It's a good way to identify
the different position
of the bouncing ball,
and it can be a method
to spot spacing troubles.
Switching back to 24 frames per second,
I will select the object
and go into the motion path panel.
I will set the animation range
from zero to 24 frames per second.
And since this is a function I use a lot,
I will right click on the calculate button
and add it to my quick favorite.
This way, when I press the cue key,
I can access the calculate
function anywhere
in the 3D viewport.
You can now see our spacing
and try to see what's
wrong with our animation.
When an object is falling in space,
it's accelerating until
it touches the ground.
The speed of an object might stabilize
due to air friction.
But unless there is a
force pulling our ball up,
it is simple to accelerate
until it touches the ground.
So the spacing should be increasing
from one frame to the
other while it's falling.
And we can see this is what's
happening on those frames.
Each frames forward, the
spacing is getting bigger.
On the last frame, the
spacing is getting smaller.
It means that the ball is slowing down
before hitting the ground
and this is incorrect.
And this is something that
we can read on the curve.
As explained previously,
the curve should get
more and more vertical
as it get closer to the value zero,
which is our ground value.
While here we can see
that it has this S shape
that makes the ball slowing
down before touching the ground.
The curve is easing out toward the ground.
But since we have made a good
blocking of our animation,
it doesn't look that bad.
Those two breakdowns
are currently helping us
getting a better result.
This is why blocking
can be pretty important.
To fix the ground key frames,
we just need to switch the
handle pressing V to vector.
Now I no longer have
this S shape on my curve.
To make things even clearer,
let's get rid of our two
break down key frames
by selecting them and pressing the X key.
I've also switched back
to basic ball handles.
When I play the animation,
you will better feel this
ease in and ease out.
You can see the ball accelerating
when it's leaving the ground
and before it hits the ground.
While if I switch both handles to vector,
now we can feel that the ball is bouncing.
To get even a better feeling,
I will also slightly raise the curve
by moving both vector
handles towards the outside.
And by scaling the upper key,
I will make the ball raising faster
and holding a bit more in the air.
I have bring more
contrast into my animation
by changing the shape of the curve,
and now it's more stylized.
A little touch we can add
to make it even more appealing,
is to slightly offset the
upper key of one frame.
This way we don't have the same timing
when the ball is rising
than when it's falling down.
We can recalculate the
motion path of our animation
by clicking the update path button.
And instead of the in range option,
I've switched to around frame.
From there I can choose how many frame
I want to see on my motion path
before and after the current
position of the ball.
Now, when I look at
the spacing of my ball,
we can see that when
it's leaving the ground,
it has the biggest spacing.
And it's slowing down when
reaching the highest position,
which is correct.
When the ball is falling down,
we also get the proper spacing.
It's getting bigger and bigger
as we approach the contacting key frame.
We now have a pretty cool bouncing rhythm,
so let's work a bit on
the scaling of our ball
or more precisely on it's
squashing and stretching.
Pressing Alt+H in the graph editor
will reveal all the curve.
I can hide the Z location curve,
so that we focus on the scale curve.
Since our balls squashing
is pretty brutal,
we can switch those key frames to vector.
If we have a very slow squashing,
we will have kept them as it is,
as the ball would be
progressively absorbing
the impact for its squash.
Pardon for the animation,
I'm trying to get a feeling
of the motion of the ball.
When the ball squash,
we can imagine it's a
continuity of its fall.
And since we are working
on the cycling animation,
the latest frame is the same as the first.
So if I check the frame before the latest,
I can see that I have a big spacing
between the base of my
ball and the ground.
So it will be better
if I kept this thinner
for the spacing of the squashing.
Meaning that I will offset the squash pose
of frame two on frame one.
And we will have a very
stretched pose on frame zero
and a very squashed one on frame one.
And so it will transition
with the full better.
We are now getting a
more impactful squashing
if we compare with previous version.
But since we have offset
one frame for the squashing,
we should do the same for the stretching.
As you can see my spacing
between frame three
and four is very small.
So I want a faster animation.
I will offset the keys one frame before,
and I will also switch them to vector.
Next is the air squashing.
I offset the key frame
where the ball recover
its round shape and then
it's getting squashed again
with the inner star when it's
reached the highest point.
Since the highest point is on frame 15,
I will make it squash on frame 15.
I'd like to slightly delay the squashing,
so what I will do is that I
will duplicate all the keys
on frame eight and offset
them onto frame 10 or 11.
It makes all the skate
curve becoming flat,
which means that from
frame eight to frame 11,
the ball is perfectly round.
And as the ball will be accelerating
to get back to the ground.
I'd like to slightly offset the time
it's starts to stretch by two frames
because the ball is falling
faster than it is raising.
So making it stretching a
little sooner does make sense.
Animating is not a linear art,
you will need to go back
and forth a lot of time.
And while the animation
gets more appealing,
I feel like there is
something a little off
and since we've been
offsetting a lot of curve,
the ball is starting to relax
while it hasn't left the ground.
Meaning that the ball should
be in air on frame four.
So I just need to re-edit
the curve for the Z location
and offset the stopping
point by one frame.
And now when they play again my animation,
I feel like there is something a bit off
on the air squashing.
The ball slows and then
it starts squashing.
And if we double check the
spacing of the base of the ball,
we can see that as soon
as it starts squashing,
the easing gets stronger
and that's better.
The yellow arrows are getting
smaller progressively,
while there is a big difference
between the two red arrows.
So even if it's very subtle,
it makes the animation a bit weird.
So again I can fix this
by simply offsetting the
squashing key frames,
the plateau we have created
before just by one frame.
Making it happening a little sooner,
so that it will better
blend while it's raising.
I guess you may ask
yourself how do I get rid
of the grid of the motion path,
et cetera my fried issue.
It's by deactivating the overlay here.
And since this is something
I do all the time,
what I did is that I set a
shortcut onto the overlay.
You can assign the shortcut to any tool
or option in blender by simply
right clicking on it and
selecting assign shortcuts.
I've personally used
the shortcut power two
which is just upon the tab
key on my French keyboard.
I'm pretty happy with this
bouncing ball animation.
And in summary we have
seen that curve editing
can dramatically change our animation.
Good blocking makes your
animation a little better
when you switch to spline.
It's important not to be
afraid to break the curve
using vector handles.
Offsetting the key by one frame
can really change your animation
and make it look better
on its troy.
Don't forget that the
devil is in the details.