- Before we start animating
our bouncing ball,
one of the most important
thing you have to understand
is interpolation, timing and spacing.
Timing and spacing are two
of the 12 principles of animation.
Interpolation is quite new
since it's the computer
that is doing the interpolation
between two key frame
while in the past, they
used to animate everything
by and adding drawings and drawings.
Timing is the pace.
It's the moment when the
ball leave the ground,
is up in the sky and
then hit back the ground.
It is defined by the key
moment of the animation
or in the extreme,
the extreme high position
and the extreme low position
in this case.
We have a timing of 12 frame
to get to the highest position
and 12 frame to get back on the ground.
Spacing is the different
of position of our sphere
from one frame to the other.
We can easily display the spacing
by going into the object
option, motion path,
set the frame from zero
to 24 and click calculate.
Then there we create a curve
that go through different point
that mark the position of
the origin of our sphere
on each key frame.
The distance between those
points is our spacing
and this spacing is based on
the timing of our animation
and the interpolation
between two key frames.
By default, blender
interpolation is set to bezier.
What it does is that it
creates an acceleration
when the object is moving from a key frame
and a deceleration when it's
arriving on the next key frame.
These are known as easing out
and easing in meaning that
you are easing out of
the key frame leaving it
for an acceleration
and you are easing into the
next key frame slowing down
before reaching or hitting its position.
So basically with that
we've a very slow motion
and it accelerate along the way.
On frame 12, it will
reach its maximum speed.
So the spacing will be the biggest.
And when it will come close to frame 24,
it will slow down.
This is what the bezier
interpolation does by default.
You can change the interpolation mode
by selecting all the key frame with A
and pressing the T key.
It will open the interpolation panel
where we can choose which
interpolation our key frame
will be using.
There are a lot of different
pre-made interpolation
but we only need to
focus on very first one.
To be perfectly honest,
I never used all the others,
but they can be very useful
if you want to build fast motion
for motion design, for example.
But in our case, we will be mostly working
using those three during the course.
Let's select the linear interpolation.
As soon as I will select it,
the behavior of the ball will change
and we will get a more robotic movement.
In the motion path tab,
I will click the update path
and now we can see that the spacing
between the different
frames is always the same.
The spacing is even.
If we know compare and linear
and bezier interpolation,
we can see that the timing is the same.
They reach the lowest and
highest point at the same time
but on the bezier, we have
a variation of the spacing.
So we have a variation
of the speed of the ball
while in linear it's constant.
The linear interpolation is
very useful for robotic moves
or for wall cycles for example
when the foot is on the ground.
Back to our motion,
I will select all the key,
press the T shortcut
and set it to constant.
I will update the path
and now we can see that
the ball is changing position only
when it reaches the next key frame.
So it's considered a
constant interpolation
or no interpolation
and it's perfect to focus on
the timing of your animation.
This is the kind of interpolation we use
when we are blocking the animation.
In most animation,
blocking is the first stage
and it's very important.
And we will start blocking
our bouncing ball animation
in the next video.
Stepped interpolation
can also be very useful
whenever you want to give
the stop motion style
to your animation like on this example.
To summarize, we have seen
that interpolation occur
between two key frames,
that we can change the interpolation mode
using the T key,
that the bezier interpolation
allow acceleration and deceleration
or easing in an easing out,
that the linear interpolation
has a constant speed
while the constant interpolation
doesn't show any interpolation
and is good to check out your timing.