- [Presenter] Let's have a
deeper look to the graph editor.
In the previous video,
we have seen that those curve
are just a value evolving over time,
and those controller point
are the keyframe values.
Each of those controllers have two handles
that can be used to change the way
the interpolation is set.
And they work exactly as handles
will do whenever you are editing
a 3D curve in the 3D view.
Those vector handles has
different pre-set behavior.
We can access them by pressing the V key
or going into the Key option of the editor
of the graph editor.
By default, all the keys
are set to auto clamp.
You can see the handle type
of the selected keyframe
in the F-curve panel.
When the keyframe is set to auto clamp,
Blender will try to interpolate
from one key to the other
in the smoothest fashion.
But as soon as I try to move
this key beyond the previews
of the next frame, the
handles will become flat.
So, it's clamping the value of the curve
to the current keyframe,
avoiding any overshoot.
If we swtich to automatic,
we will have kind of the same behavior,
Blender will try to keep
as much interpolation
between the previews and next frame,
but in this case, it
won't avoid the overshoot.
Curve wise, an overshoot is a bump
in the shape of the curve,
making the value jumping
up or jumping down.
This is not a handle type I use that much
because sometime I feel like it's behavior
is a bit unexpected.
As explained before,
handle type are set to
auto clamp by default,
but as soon as I try to scale
the handle or rotate them,
you can see that it switched to aligned.
The orientation in scale of the handle
are no longer controlled by
Blender, but by yourself,
but Blender will keep the previews
and next handle aligned
one with the other.
This allows you to keep a
smoothest curve interpolation,
but if I switch the handle type to free,
then each handle can be manipulated freely
without caring about the
previews of next handle,
allowing us to break the curve
which in a lot of case can be very handy.
The final handle type we have to see
is the vector handle type.
As soon as we select it,
the curve will break into a odd angle.
Each angle will point individually
to the previews on next keyframe
and as soon as I try to
manipulate one of the handle,
it will switch to free mode.
It's a very useful type of handle
whenever you want to rapidly
create a linear interpolation.
Setting to consecutive keyframe to vector
will create a linear interpolation
and then, the cool thing
about vector handles
is that whenever we are
moving the keyframe,
they will always be
pointing one at the other.
I use this type of handle
a lot for impact frame.
If we change the interpolation
mode of our curve
to constant or linear,
we won't get any access to the handles,
because the interpolation is pre-made.
It's where there no
interpolation or a linear one.
Adding handles doesn't
make sense in this case.
In the previous video we have seen that
we can double click onto a
channel to select the curve,
we can box select, press A,
press control shift and click
before on after a keyframe
to select all the
previews on next keyframe.
If we click the little checkbox,
it will deactivate the current channel.
Now you can see that the Z
location on the character
is no longer animated and
is not jumping anymore,
which is kind of fun.
The wrench icon allows us to activate
or deactivate curve modifier.
To add the modifier to a curve
you just need to select one
control point of the curve,
then go into the end panel
and switch to modifiers.
There are a lot of different modifier,
let's just add a noise modifier
to understand what they do.
As the modeling modifier,
you can use them to procedurally generate
new behavior for your item.
The noise modifier is super
cool to create camera shake
or to bring texture to your animation.
The lock icon will allow you
to lock the current channel,
making any further modification impossible
until you disable it.
The magnifying glass on the
top left will allow you to
search for specific channels.
It's very handy whenever you
want to isolate a channel
like the location channel
without having to hide
everything else then un-hide everything.
Just type what you want to work on,
then everything else will disappear.
All the previous navigation
showed that we have seen
when we have studied the
timeline of the same,
the home key will frame everything,
the dot key on the notepad
will zoom into the selection
and you can use the P key
to set a temporary preview
range into your animation.
Alt and P will clear.
When working with curve,
we are working with values,
and fortunately those
values can vary a lot.
Some curve will have a
small arrange of value,
while other curve might
have a big range of value.
And in this case, you
can see me struggling,
going back and forth to
select into different values.
The normalize option allow us to convert
to this big range of value
to a range that goes
from minus one to one.
So it doesn't change
the value of the curve,
it changed the way the value is displayed.
It makes it a bit handier to work on
the higher range of values.
If I disable the auto update,
I can move any value beyond the threshold
of minus one and plus one.
Then I will add the vision
of the modified curve,
but if I enable it, as soon
as I move beyond minus one,
the curve is not canceling the move,
but it's re-updating it's position
into a minus one to plus one range.
So as you can see, when I
move the extreme position,
it does quite change the shape
of the curve in the inside.
I don't use it that much,
but it will make more
sense if you manipulate it.
By default you will see the
curve of the transform channel
of the displayed animated object,
in this case, the
controller of my character.
If I hide everything but
those few controllers,
you can see that I only have
those listed in my graph edit.
When activated, the selection filter,
only selected object will
show their animation curve.
When enabling to show hidden,
it will show absolutely every
control channels available,
whether you hide those controller or not,
the curves will still be displayed.
The only show arrows
options will show you curves
or keyframes that are no
longer assigned to anything.
Can happen sometime during
whenever you delete a bone
in edit mode and you didn't
clean the animation later on.
It's very specific and we
don't really need to know
more about this right now.
The ghost curve option will
display you the previous
unedited shape of the curve.
This is something I never
use, to be really honest,
but it can be useful for you
if you find any interest in it.
Click back on the crossed
button to get rid of it.
I won't go through the
whole effect of menus
since there are a lot of options
that are self explanatory.
I believe this is cool if
you are working on multiple
object at once for motion
design, for example,
and you want to clean your selection.
They are different ways you can snap
your different keys on the grid.
By default, it's set to nearest frame,
meaning that whenever you're
moving your key on the X axis,
it will snap right onto a frame.
This is the option I use 99% of the time.
If I use the second step, it
will snap on every second.
So, in our case, every 30 frames.
In the view option in the header,
I can enable show seconds.
Since my document is based
to 30 frame per second,
whenever I try to move the key,
you can see that it's not to frame 30.
You have seen previously that pressing M,
we can add a marker on the timeline.
You can add them also in the graph editor
because the graph editor
is just another version,
in a way, of the timeline.
And if I then switch to
snapped to nearest marker
as soon as I will move my key,
it will snap on the nearest marker.
Finally, you can get rid of the auto snap
switching to no auto snap.
It can be useful in
certain case when you are,
for example, scaling a wall animation
and you don't want every keyframe
to snap to the nearest frame,
but don't forget that
Blender will read the value
on one frame, not reading between.
Be cautious with it because
the value read by Blender
might not be the one on your key,
this can be a bit confusing.
As in the 3D veiwport,
you can use different kind of pivot point
to edit your curve.
The bounding box center
will take the most extreme
keys you have selected
and it will set the pivot
point right in the middle.
As in the 3D view,
you can see this dotted line showing
where is the pivot point
compared to your mouse cursor.
The 2D cursor, as act the 3D cursor,
you can place it by shift
right clicking on the grid
and it's position is defined
by those two blue lines,
the play at and a given value.
With my key selected,
if I press S and Y to scale on the Y axis,
you can see my keys are pointing toward
the horizontal blue line.
This is a good way to set the same value
to several keyframes at once.
The individual origin pivot
point is the one I use the most.
Each keyframe becomes independent
and whenever your scaling or rotating,
it's manipulating each
keyframe handles separately,
allowing you to scale
them and manipulate them
without moving them onto the timeline.
Rotating the keys with
the bonding box option
also move them on the timeline.
As in mesh edit mode,
you can activate a proportional editing.
As soon as I edit one of my keyframe
I can see the aerial
(indistinct) of the falloff
and using the mouse wheel,
I can increase or decrease the size
of the area of the effect.
I don't use it that much,
but it can be very handy
whenever you are dealing with
high density keyframed
curve like baked animation
or motion capture.
As the mesh editing falloff,
it comes with different
curves that will behave
in a different manner whenever
you are moving your point.
You can access new display
option in the view panel.
Whether you want to
show or not the sidebar
you can access it by pressing N.
You can enable the operator
box that is available
in the 3D veiwport too,
but I don't think it's that
useful on the graph edit.
The show cursor option will hide
or unhide the original
line of the 2D cursor.
You can activate the show sliders option
if you want to access
the value of the keyframe
directly in the channels panel.
I never use it, but it definitely is handy
if you want to fine tweak your values.
You will find other option to display
or not the handles of the keyframe,
but I do recommend you
to keep them displayed
and I also advise you to only
display the selected keyframe
in those or your graph editor
will rapidly become a mess.
To summarize, we have
seen that we can change
the handle type of our
curve using the V key.
We can use the normalize
option to display a broad range
of curved values into a minus
one to one range curve value.
We can see that through the
graph editor we can hide
or unhide curve, deactivate them,
lock them or even add the modifiers.
As in the 3D viewport, we
can use different pivot point
and constraint axis.
We can use selection filter
or quick search to make
our selection easier.
We can use proportional editing
to edit multiple keys at once.