- In this video, we will have an overview
of all the curve modified.
In the graph-editor, whenever
I select a curve, I can access
the modifier in the end
panel or properties panel.
Why do we have already
set a cycle modifier
in the preview video?
What you may haven't noticed
is that we already using
modifiers prior to this.
As soon as we have used
the extrapolation mode
whenever we press the shift +
E and make our curve cyclic,
basically, we were
adding a cycle modifier.
Any modifier influence can be activated
or deactivated by clicking the checkbox.
The circle modifier repeat the animation
from the first key to the last key.
We can change the modifier
behavior before the first key
and after the first key, by default
it's repeating the animation as it is.
We can get rid of the cycle
or use the cycle we've offset.
If I use it right now,
nothing will happen because
it uses the position
of the last key frame as
the new starting point.
But since my first
and last key frame are
same, it doesn't change.
But as soon as I offset the
value of the last key frame,
you can see that I get
some kind of ladder motion.
The repeat mirror option
will do what it says.
It will repeat the curve
but each time it will a mirror
it based on the last frame.
Changing the value will
just set the number
of repetition after or before
your current animation.
A value of zero will make
the cycle repeat infinitely.
The restrict frame range
and use-influence properties
are very useful but they
are not the most abuse
on the cycle modifier,
so we will have a look
to it later on.
Let's have a look to the next modifier.
I will get rid of the cycle modifier,
and I add a built-in function.
My animation curve as totally changed.
And we now have a (indistinct) curve
because the default function is seen.
The first multiplayer will allow us
to modify the frequency of the curve.
While the amplitude will
allow us to increase the value
of the curve.
The first offset will offset
the curve on the X axis
while the value offset will
offset the curve on the Y axis.
The restricted frame range option
is a supercool additional
tool as it is named,
it will allow us to limit or restrict
the influence of the
modifier on the frame range.
So we can set this frame range
by tweaking the end value
and the start value.
The in and out value
allow us to input easing,
meaning that we can increase
or decrease the influence
of the modifier at the beginning
and the end of the frame range.
This way we can totally modify
the behavior of the ball
with a non-destructive
workflow because I'm not
currently working on any of the key frame,
but only on the modifiers
of that I can add
or remove. By default The modifier
is replacing our current animation
but enabling the additive option
will add the modifier behavior
on top of our animation.
So setting the amplitude
of the modifier to zero is
like removing it when
it's in additive mode.
And as soon as I increased its amplitude,
you can see Oh, it's affecting the curve.
While it works for the specific case,
this is not the best way to play
with the influence of the modifier.
Fortunately, we have an influence
factor that will increase
or decrease the influence of
the modifier on our curve.
The dropdown menu upon the
additive would enable us
to change the type of functions.
So if you remember your
trigonometry classes
you might recognize
the tangent causing an (indistinct) curve
This square root is a
simple exponential function.
So you can use it to make
your ball rise like a balloon,
with a constant easing,
the natural logarithm does
look like the square root
but it has a slight
offset and it ease more.
Finally, the normalized scene
looks like the scene function
but it does ease very rapidly.
So you can change this
by moving the phase offset
and the phase multiplier.
So it can be hard to find a specific shoes
for those modifiers,
but you have to experiment with it.
And when you do motion design, for example
they are very useful. When
adding the envelope modifier,
We will see a couple of
dotted lines appearing
in our graph-editor lying
with minus one and one value.
These are scaling values or
reference values, if you will.
I will just a couple of
points at the beginning
and the end of my curve. Those
control points will allow me
to change the overall shape of my curve,
also known as envelope.
Those control points are defined
by a minimum and maximum value
that appears as little white
dot on the graph-editor,
they represent the current
scale of the modifier.
So, if I tweak the maximum value,
I will see my curve scaling up and down,
and we can clearly see the max point
of the envelope modifier moving here.
So it might look a bit abstract right now,
so what I will do is that
I will make the bonding box
in a way of my envelop
modifier as big as the curve.
To do so I will set the
minimum value to zero
like the minimum value of my key frame
and the maximum value around
eight, like my key frame.
I will add a couple of control points
and I will give them the
same value, zero and 8.4.
Now you can think of your curve
as being bound by your lattice modifier
or being transformed as in Photoshop,
we've an even transform.
And by moving the value
of the control point,
it's like moving the
corners of the bonding box.
And as into a lattice
we can add more than two control point.
I can add a control point
in the middle set its
default value as the other.
And when I move it,
it will break the curve and
deform it from its position.
Very powerful modifier
to modify the amplitude
of the motion. The noise
modifier is one of my favorite.
And guess what? It noise to your curve.
It's perfect to create camera shake
Or if you are a shaky character
you can use the noise
modifier instead of Nkit.
The scale will change the
frequency of the noise,
the phase we kind of change
its shape or it seeds.
The strength is the
amplitude of the noise,
the depth value is the
smoothness of the noise.
To see it properly, I
will increase the scale
and the strength.
As I reduce the depth value,
you can see the curves smoothing.
The offset, allows you to offset the noise
on the X axis or in time, if you prefer.
So, using the noise modifier
and the restrict frame range,
I can create a slight shaking
of the ball whenever it lands.
The limits modifier works a
bit as a limit constraint.
Setting a minimum Y value
and maximum Y value,
will clump the value of the curve.
Any value beneath the minimum
value will be ignored,
any value upon the maximum
value will be ignored.
It's like creating a roof
and the ground that will bond
your curve while the minimum X
and maximum X value will
currently ignore any values
that is before the set frame
or after the maximum set frame.
So, what if I set the
X maximum value to 10,
any key frame value after
the frame 10 will be ignored.
This can be very useful if, for example,
you don't want the ball
to go under the ground.
The next modifier is the stepped modifier,
it's a very cool and intuitive modifier.
The step size allow you
to change the length
in frame of the step in your animation.
So, basically, this modifier
is converting your curve
as if we were blocking our animation
with constant interpolation
and it gives a fantastic stop motion style
to your animation.
So you can change the step size value,
you can offset it in time.
And this modifier comes
with a built-in starting
frame and ending frame.
It's a bit like the frame restrict range
but you can consider it as an
additional restriction layer.
On the full character,
we will need to add this
modifier on every single curve.
What we can do instead is add
the modifier on the NLA strip.
Don't worry. We'll talk about
the NLA editor later on,
but just consider that
we're applying the modifier
to the wall animation
instead of applying it
to a simple curve.
If we have a loop to this quick animation,
I've made with one
of my students, the
step modify your really
brings the stop motion
feelings to the animation.
As explained before those
modifier act as object modifiers.
It means that they can be layered,
you can add multiple curve modifiers to
get different results and the order
in which you stack those
modifier is important.
If I add the limit modifier
before the noise modifier,
the noise will be applied after the limit
and so I won't see any difference.
I won't see the limits applied.
At the time I'm recording
this video on blender 2.91,
I haven't find any way
to move the position
of those curve modifier.
Hopefully this will be updated whenever
you will be able to watch this video.
We can copy a modifier by clicking
on the little folder icon
with the arrow getting inside.
To paste the modifier on another
curve just select two curve
and click the second icon
with the folder shape and
the arrow, getting out.
If you have multiple modifiers,
they will be all copy and
pasted onto the curve.
To summarize, we have seen
that we can use modifier
to modify our curve
behavior procedurally and
in a non-destructive manner.
Modifier can be stacked one
on each other to get more advanced result.
Modifiers can be copied
and pasted from one curve to the other.
We can add the modifiers
on the whole action for the NLA editor.