- [Instructor] We have left last video
with our happy bouncing
ball, bouncing and bouncing.
But now, I'd like it
to move forward a bit.
So let's do that together.
The first thing I will do is to press
three on my num pad to
switch to side view.
Now, instead of making my
animation loop over 24 frame,
I'd like to make the
animation a little bit longer.
So I will re-open my timeline,
and I'd like to repeat
the animation four time.
So I can tie in all time 24 frames
to get to the right frame number.
But the problem is that
my bouncing ball animation
is not repeating over those 96 frames.
So the more logical
method to make it repeat
will be to select all my keyframe,
duplicate them by pressing Shift + D,
X to move them on the x-axis,
and type in 24 so that they will be moved
by 24 frame on the x-axis.
Then, I can press Shift +
R to repeat the operation.
The problem with this
method is that if we have
any modification to be
added to the animation,
we will have to reduplicate everything
or modify it on each bounce.
While it's not super painful
on such a simple animation
duplicating only four time,
this is not an efficient way to do it.
So I will reset what I've done
and with all my keys and curves selected,
I will press Shift + E to open
the keyframe extrapolation menu.
By default our keyframe
extrapolation is set to constant.
It means that whenever I reach
the very last keyframe in my animation,
the value won't be changing anymore.
That's why we get flat curve.
But judging by this extrapolation menu,
we can see that we can switch it
to linear extrapolation
or even make a cycle.
You can also access the
extrapolation operation
through channel panel in the
header of the graph editor.
With all the curves selected,
let's choose make cyclic.
Boom, our animation is now
cycling infinitely on the timeline.
And the cool thing about
using extrapolation
is that modifying our
animation will be repeating
and updating the along the whole timeline.
(graphic swooshes)
With this problem fixed,
I'd like my ball to move forward in space.
So I'd like to animate
the y-axis of the ball.
So I will insert a single
keyframe on the y-axis,
go to frame 24, move the
ball by about nine meters,
go back onto the transform channel,
right-click and insert a single keyframe.
If I now play the animation,
the ball will move forward
only on the keyframe we have inserted,
and since Blender is creating by default
a new keyframe with the bezier mode,
we have an acceleration and a deceleration
of the ball so it doesn't
look super unnatural.
While this kind of locomotion
could be a little more complex,
we will consider that our ball
is moving at a constant speed.
So I will select both handle,
press the V key and switch them to vector.
You could have chosen to press the T key
and switch to linear interpolation,
but I prefer to use vector interpolation
to keep the handles available.
When I watch this motion,
I feel like the ball should
move a little further.
So I can take my last control point
and move it a bit up more
or insert a new value
in the transform channel
and don't forget to insert the keyframe.
Or we can directly change
the value of the keyframe
by going into the F-Curve properties
and enter 10 meters in
the value of the keyframe.
This is a good method when you want
to enter very precise values.
Now, I'd like my ball to continue
moving on on each bounce.
So I could duplicate the
last keyframe, offset it
or insert a new a keyframe
and set it to 20 meter.
But again, if we want to modify
the timing of our animation
making the jump a bit a longer,
I will have to modify those, too.
And on a more complex animation,
that would be very painful.
So let's get rid of this
and find another solution.
If we go back to the extrapolation menu,
we will find an option that allow us
to create a linear extrapolation.
Blender will take the last
two keyframe of an animation,
and it will do an extrapolation
based on the value
differences between those two.
So that's a great step
forward in our animation,
but there is something that bother me.
When our ball hit the ground,
it stays on the ground for a few frame.
The problem is that
it's sliding currently,
and it doesn't look good.
I'd like the ball to stay
where it is when it's on the ground
and move forward whenever it's airborne.
To fix it, I can simply
duplicate the very first frame
and move it on frame three,
but I need this new motion
to repeat along the full animation.
So I will press Shift + E and
choose constant extrapolation
to get rid of the linear extrapolation.
But now, my animation
is no longer repeating,
and whenever I'm re-adding
a linear extrapolation,
it will just continue on
moving instead of stopping
whenever the ball is
contacting the ground.
So I can try using a cyclic extrapolation,
but the problem is that
the ball will get back
to its original position after each cycle.
So I'd like it to cycle
but with an offset.
And what we can do is
select one of the key
of the curve an go to
the modifier tabs here.
And we can add a cycles modifier.
So it works exactly as if we were
adding the cyclic extrapolation,
but we do now have option
on the cycle behavior.
I can change the way it act
before and after the cycle.
So if I go onto the after,
I can ask Blender to use
the repeat with offset.
And what it does is that it
takes the very last keyframe
and use it as a new starting point.
So offsetting the animation
is currently adding it
on top of the latest keyframe.
(graphic swooshes)
An extra motion
is missing, though.
If we watch this video,
you'll find the link in the resources PDF,
I'd like you to focus on the body shape
and orientation of this lynx.
During this gorgeous motion,
we can see the squashing and stretching,
but we can also see some
rotation of the body.
The body in the beginning is
oriented toward the up point
and then oriented toward
the landing point.
So we do need to input those information
on our bouncing ball.
To get a better preview
of the motion of the ball,
(graphic swooshes)
I will calculate the motion path.
As seen in the previous video,
I will go into the object option,
motion path and click calculate the path.
I will change the path type to in range
and change the end frame to 96.
This will give us the
motion path of our ball,
and it's going to be easier for us
to figure out how much
we have to rotate it.
The idea is to simply rotate the ball
toward its next position
or its next frame position.
And once we have past the highest point,
we will make the ball pointing
toward the previous frame.
Since our first frame is exactly the same
(graphic swooshes)
as the latest frame, or frame 24,
I will jump to frame 24
and give the correct
orientation to the ball.
It seems that 11 degrees looks fine.
Then, I will right-click and
insert a single keyframe.
A new channel has appeared
in the graph editor.
It's our X ruler rotation.
So I will now go back to the frame
where the ball is currently
leaving the ground
and rotate it by minus 12.5
degree toward its next position.
So now as we have did before,
I will duplicate the last frame,
frame 24 of this ruler rotation,
and move it onto frame zero,
pressing Shift + D, X and
moving it with the mouse.
Now that the initial frame zero
and final frame 24 are the same,
I can select my curve
and press Shift + E and make it cyclic,
and it already looks pretty cool.
So while the motion I'm seeing
right now is pretty satisfying,
you know that we need to
check it frame-by-frame.
As any craft, a perfect
animation doesn't exist,
and the level of quality you will reach
depend on the time you can
spend on your animation.
In this case, I'd like to polish
the animation a little more
by making frame number one pretty flat,
because I don't really like the fact
that the ball is slightly leaning backward
when it's getting in
its flattest position.
In the graph editor
with the X ruler rotation curve selected,
I will press I to insert a new keyframe
and choose only selected.
This way, Blender won't add
any additional keyframes
on the other curves
and our graph editor will remain clean.
Then, I can grab this key,
move it on the y-axis,
holding Shift to get a
more precise movement.
And I will call this first
bouncing ball animation done.
The technique we have used in this video,
adding a rotation motion
based on the location motion,
the up and down motion of the ball,
is called the layered approach.
It means that you add layers
and layers of motion
during the polishing stage,
not during the blocking stage.
And we'll study this technique
more in depth later on.
To summarize, we have seen that we
(graphic swooshes)
can create cycles using
the Shift + E shortcut and
choose different extrapolation.
We can access more advanced
cycle option using modifiers.
We can use current motion
of the ball as the guide
to add new motion to it
in a layered approach.