- [Instructor] Before we go further
and talk about the dope sheet,
we need to talk a bit
about Blender's data.
If you're beginning with Blender,
the most common data you are manipulating
is the material of an object.
You may have watched tutorial
where you create a material
and then you share it on multiple object.
For example, we can see
this blue material applied
to the Suzanne head.
If I select the cube,
I can go into the library
and apply to it the blue material too.
Both object are now
sharing the same material
or sharing the same material data.
With my cube selected,
if I apply again the blue material,
I will see the number two appearing next
to the material name.
This number indicate how many object
or users are currently
using this blue material
and it's current two, the monkey head
and the cube.
It means that if I change
the color of this material,
it will be changing on both object
because it's the same data
that they are sharing.
So as explained in the very
first video of this chapter,
objects are just containers
and if I go to the mesh data,
I will also find a data library
that will allow me to
source any other mesh data
from any other object.
With the cube selected,
if I select the sphere mesh data,
my cube will be transformed into a sphere
and Blender indicates us
that there are two objects
using those mesh data.
We have also seen that the object
has changed color because the material
is bound to the vertices.
By loading new mesh data,
we have also sourced the
material data linked to it.
If we now go back to our
bouncing ball animation,
with the graph editor open,
I can see that I'm working on the ball
but just under, we have
the SphereAction.002
that we haven't talked about.
And when we look at at our
graph editor hierarchy,
we can see our mesh object, the ball.
The SphereAction.002 is bound to the ball
and all the transformed channel keyframes
are bound to this SphereAction.
Instead of the graph editor,
let's open the dope sheet.
Let's consider the dope sheet
as being like the timeline.
All the shortcuts and
features we have seen
with the timeline works
within the dope sheet.
We can see our mesh object
and the action in the hierarchy.
If I now enable the collection cone,
and I start animating the location
of the cone by inserting
a couple of keyframe,
a new hierarchy appear in the dope sheet.
We can find our cone object
with a new action called coneAction.
As soon as you insert
a keyframe on an object
that hasn't been animated yet,
it will automatically create a new action.
This action are the name of the container
that contain animation data
and the dope sheet is an overview
of all the animation data
that are being used in our scene.
Here we can see which container
is using the animation data
and what action is being used
but now what if I want to
edit those animation data?
We can access them
through the action editor.
With the action editor,
we will be able to work on
a specific action at a time.
With the cone selected, I can see
that I'm working on the cone action
and as for any other kind of data,
if I click the action icon,
I will access our action library.
So it means that as for material
or any kind of data,
I can share this animation
to any other object.
So I will select my SphereAction.002,
rename it bouncing ball
and when I play the animation,
I can see that now my cone is moving
as our bouncing ball.
And near the action name,
I can see that I have two users
of the bouncing ball animation.
So I can share this animation
on as many object as I want.
I can give it to Suzanne here
and now we can see that
we have three users
and when I play the animation,
our Suzanne monkey head will move
as the bouncing ball too.
Since I've given the
bouncing ball animation
to all my object,
the point action, for example,
has no more users.
And if I brought my action library,
I will see this little zero
in front of the coneAction
and you have to be very careful with that
because whenever you have any kind of data
that has a zero in front of its name,
then they will get rid of this data
as soon as you close the software.
So if I revert my scene,
now reopen it if you will,
the coneAction marked with
a zero has disappeared
and I've lost this animation.
To avoid losing an animation,
you can click the little shield icon
that will create a new fake user.
Whether the data is used or not,
then I won't flush it on restart.
As we have seen before with the materials,
as soon as a data or an action is shared,
editing it on one of the object
will affect any other container
that is using the same action.
If you want to duplicate
the current action,
you can click the number
next to it's name.
This become a new action
or a new data that you can edit freely
and you can see that there
is not more multiple users
on this one.
And this new duplicated action
has been added to the action library.
To definitely get rid of an action,
Shift + click the cross icon.
When reverting the file
or reloading Blender,
the animation data or the
action will be removed.
If you're starting fresh
and your object is not animating,
you can press the New button
to create a new action.
I will insert a couple of keyframe
to illustrate one thing.
When you get this orange continuous line
between two frames,
it means that the value is not changing.
As soon as I enter a value on
one of the transform channel,
we can see that now there
is no more this orange line
on the z location channel.
Switching to constant
or linear interpolation
will create a green line
between the different keyframes.
So it basically tells you
that you are not choosing
Bezier interpolation.
Changing the handle type of your keyframe
will be also displayed
in the action editor.
You will see the shape of
the key currently changing.
The action editor will
become our main editor
when it comes to animation
before we jump into the graph editor.
To summarize, we have see
that the dope sheet shows us
all the current actions
that are being used
in our Blender scene,
while the action editor allow us
to edit one action at a time.
Action is the name of the container
for our motion or animation
data and as any other data,
an action can be shared
by different object.