- [Instructor] This is video
is an exercise video or assignment video.
I invite you to create two new animation
using the bouncing ball
and this parkour object.
The idea is to launch the
bouncing ball onto the surface.
I've made two version of the animation,
one with a very heavy bouncing ball,
like a bowling ball
that will strike the surface
and almost stop and then will be rolling.
And the second animation
with a more squashy
and light bouncing ball
that will just bounce until it stops.
You can find those two animation
in the action library.
I will explain you right
now the key component
of those animation
and the next video will be a time lapse
of me creating those two animations.
It's exactly the same workflow
as on the previous animation.
And I will just double the speed
of the video so that
you can use VLC Player,
for example, to slow down the video
by 50% and get it real time if you need.
On the squashy bouncing ball animation,
instead of moving the screen controller
to give an orientation to the ball,
you can also rotate its root controller
and use the squash and
stretch controller only
to squash and stretch the ball currently.
So only on their z-axis.
The thing you will have to check out
during your polishing is the amplitude
of the squash and stretch curve.
As you go down the parkour,
the ball will lose energy
and so the squash and
stretch will get more subtle
and more subtle as you reach
the end of the animation.
So your curve must lose amplitude.
For the heavy ball animation,
I haven't used squash and stretch at all.
To make the ball feels heavy,
I've used very subtle bouncing
and very short bouncing.
The key point here is to
remove the squash and stretch
or make it very subtle
and make the bounce very small
and you will get this feel
of weight in the ball.
The second very important thing
to watch out on this animation
is the spacing of the ball.
It gets bigger and bigger
as the ball is falling
toward the first surface.
Due to its weight, the ball almost stop
when it hits the surface
as we are close to 90-degree angle
and then the ball is accelerating
until it touch the ground
and then it will slowly lose speed
as soon as the animation
go ahead until it stops.
The longer time it takes to stop,
the heavier it will feel.
You now have all the instruction
to create those animation.
The next video is the time lapse
of me creating those two animations
and then we will start working
on our first character animation.