- [Instructor] Let's
polish our bouncing ball.
The first thing I will do
is select all the key, press T
and switch to Bezier.
Now we have interpolation
between our keyframes
and the first thing we can see
that we get some slowing down
or easing before the
ball touch the ground.
You can switch to the graph editor
through the header or
pressing Control + tab
when you are in the action editor.
I have activated the display selected only
and I will start polishing
the route of my ball.
When looking at the curve,
I can see that only the z and y curves
are currently animated.
All the rotation, scaling and
x location curve are flat.
To make my editing easier,
I will expand the root panel
and I will just hide all the curves
that I'm not using,
only keeping the z and y location curve.
Remember what we have seen
in the previous chapter.
When an object is falling,
it is at its maximum speed
just before hitting the ground,
so I can select my z contacting keyframe,
press V and switch it to three
and then rotate the left handle
to get a proper curve.
It already feels way better.
But I'm a bit disturbed by
the y motion of the ball.
The frame just before
it contact the ground
looks a bit weird.
And this is because we
have easing on our y curve.
The y curve has an S shape
between the IS point
and it's contacting pull.
But as seen in the previous chapter,
when a ball is falling,
it is accelerating until
it touch the ground
but its motion forward is pretty constant
because even if there is air friction
that will slow down the ball,
on such a motion, it's barely noticeable.
So I can switch both
handles to free our vector
and align them to get a
more linear interpolation.
So as a first polishing
path or splining path,
I will simply repeat this
process on each bounce.
To get a clean viewport,
I'm activating and
deactivating the overlay
with a shortcut I've set previously.
So I will break all the z-axis handle
by switching them to vector
on the contacting frame.
I will remove the intermediate
frame on the y-axis
because it's useless
since we will create
a linear interpolation
between the contacting and air pose,
switching our handles to vector.
I will use this method each
time the ball is airborne
but on the final stage of the animation,
I will keep the easing toward
the very last keyframe.
So as you remember in
the previous chapter,
I like to keep the ball a bit
longer in the air generally
just for style sake.
So on the z curve,
I will take each key where
the ball is in the air
and I will slightly scale the handles.
This way, the ball will rise
a little faster in the air
and it will be kind of thwarting a bit.
Please consider that animation
is not a linear workflow.
And I will remove some keyframe,
remove them, retime some
part of the animation
and tweak it a lot.
So it's a lot of back and forth
before you achieve a decent result.
And you can tweak an animation forever
but there is a moment
where you have to stop.
Before the second bounce,
I feel like there is a slight
glitch in the animation
because the ball is staying
too long on the ground.
So I will shorten this hold
on the ground by one key,
offsetting all the keys
after key number 20.
As it does improve the animation,
I will do the same
between frame 25 and 26.
There is a hold on the ground
but I feel it's too much.
So I will get rid of frame 26
by offsetting it onto frame 25
so that on the very last bounce,
the ball is staying on the
ground only for one frame
instead of two.
If we now have a closer
look to our y curve,
we can see that we have
a pretty logical pattern.
Each time the ball touch the ground,
the y curve get flatter and flatter,
meaning that the ball is losing speed
on each impact but when airborne,
it has a linear movement.
And as soon as it stays on the ground,
we will have a slight easing
from frame 29 to frame 43
when the ball is slowing down.
Watching the animation again and again,
I feel like there are still some glitches
and some bugs I have to fix
and when having a closer
look at my z curve,
I can see that I have some easing
after the impact, which is not correct.
So I will fix this.
After those modification,
my animation should look better
but I still have some glitches.
And this is because all the
transformation we have done
with the squash and stretch
haven't been polished
and haven't be retimed.
I've made a few modification
on the timing of the route of my ball,
so now the other animation
that were in sync
during the blocking stage
are no longer in sync.
So I will deactivate all
the other transform channel
just to see my root motion.
And now I can see that
it feels way better.
So there is still this moment
where the ball stops on the ground
but this is because we will have motion
through the squash and stretch.
So without the squash and stretch,
it looks a bit weird
but as I renabled it and
as I will be polishing it,
I will be able to fix the problem here.
If you want your animation
to look a bit more realistic,
just remove those holding frame
and just make the contacting
pose on one frame.
Then reduce a bit the squash and stretch.
This is just a matter
of personal preferences.
I like it a bit stylized,
so I'll keep those holding poses.
I will now work on the upper
squash and stretch controller.
This one is going to be
pretty easy to polish.
I select the first keyframe
and press on the dot key on
the num pad to frame them.
I'm mainly watching the
orientation of the ball created
by the stretching effect.
You can also calculate the
motion path of this ball
if this does help.
Here what I want is to give
back a bit of verticality
to the ball.
So I will slightly offset the beginning
of the stretching on the y-axis.
I will hide the z curve
by clicking the I icon
and then select the first keyframe,
press Shift + D to duplicate it
and move the duplicated
key on frame three.
As it looks a bit too delayed,
I will move back this
key on frame number two
and then I will switch
the handle type to three
so that I can shape a bit the curve.
This way, I have a better feeling
that the ball is currently aiming
or pointing toward its landing spot.
Then I will work on the z curve
that currently squash and
stretch the ball the most.
And I will just switch
the impact point to vector
because this is an impact frame
where the ball switch from
squashing to stretching again.
Then I will go onto the next jump.
I will reselect my root bone
and I will recalculate the motion path
because it does help me figuring
where the ball is supposed to land
and also where the top of the ball
is supposed to be pointing at
and this is why here,
I will slightly push the
top to the ball forward
toward the previous keyframe position
by pushing my z curve a
bit up in the graph editor.
I scrub a bit onto my animation
to see how it does move.
Then I will select the z-axis curve,
switch it to vector on this middle frame
and then move forward
toward the next jump.
First, I feel like it's offset in time.
So I will select all the curves
and move them by one keyframe
prior to the current one.
The ball is currently
leaning too much backward
on on these three
and I can figure this by
watching the F curve value.
When selecting the keyframe,
I can see that its value is set to -65
and if I select the
previous one, it has -56.
It means that this last
keyframe is further away
from its value zero
so it means the controller is offset more
and so it's more deforming the ball
than the previous bounce,
which doesn't make sense since this bounce
is less powerful,
losing energy compared
to the previous bounce.
So I will push this keyframe
towards zero in the graph editor.
For the very last bounce of the ball,
I don't want any deformation.
So I will just get rid
of the next keyframes.
From there, we can watch
our animation several time
and jump into polishing the
next squashing controller.
I will select the lower green controller
and since the curve are pretty small,
I will use the normalize option
to be able to see my green channel.
Since we have used the
upper green controller
to give an orientation to
the bounces of the ball,
I don't need to do the same
with the lower controller.
So I will just make my y curve flat
by removing the keys that are offset
because they won't bring
anything good to our animation
and they are currently almost useless
as their value is very small.
So just get rid of them.
Now regarding the z-axis
that will allow us to
squash the ball in the air
when it's reaching its highest point,
I want it to be very subtle.
So I will offset the
starting and ending keyframe
of those motion by two frames.
And I will repeat this process
along the whole animation.
I will shorten the length of this motion
and as I go forward,
I will reduce the amplitude of the curve
because again, with energy loss,
I will get the less squash
and stretch on this motion.
This controller allow us to
add very subtle deformation
to the ball, so it's interesting
to make it as good as possible.
When I'm done with it,
we can clearly see the energy loss
during the motion of the ball.
I will fix the timing of the last squash
because it doesn't
occur at the right time.
It's supposed to happen
when the ball is at its highest point.
And then again I can watch
my animation several time
to see if it looks okay.
So that's great.
We have a bouncing ball
but it's not rolling.
This is because we haven't
animated the rotation controller
of the ball yet.
In this case, it wouldn't make sense
to block the spinning of the ball.
Since it doesn't change its shape,
we wouldn't be able to see any change
during the blocking stage.
So I will select all the keyframes
but the first one and get rid of them.
Just press X and confirm.
Then select the first keyframe
and move it on frame eight.
This is the frame where the ball
is contacting the ground.
So I get a flat curve
from frame zero to frame eight.
It means that the ball won't be rolling
while it's in the air.
I want it to start spinning
when it will touch the ground
and when part of the energy of the impact
will be transferred to its rotation.
I will duplicate again the keyframe
and move it to move frame 18.
This is where I want the
ball to be spinning already.
Nothing happens because I have disabled
the transform channel.
I need to reenable it.
Now when I move the curve,
the ball should be rotating
but it's barely noticeable
and this is because I need
to unzoom in my graph editor.
Since the value of the
rotation is in degree,
I need to drastically modify the curve
and move it onto way
higher or lower values
in this case.
Pushing the value down to -360 degree
will make the roll spin forward.
So that's fine.
On the impact, the ball will
get full rotation speed,
so I will switch this to vector.
Due to the frequency of the rotation
and the animation, I have
a hard time figuring out
if the ball is currently rotating or not
because the ball pattern
seems to get aligned
on each frame so it's a bit weird.
So I will get rid of the overlay
to have a better vision of it.
I will also switch the second handle
to vector two because
the rotation of the ball
is not supposed to slow in the air
and since I still have some difficulties
to read the rotation,
I will enable all the
other controller keyframe
and disable their
influence on the animation
so that I can clearly see
if my ball is rotating or not.
The initial air rotation speed
of our bouncing ball
is not that important.
What will be important
is the final rotation speed
because it will have to match the speed
of the ball traveling on the ground.
So what we need to do is to
duplicate the current keyframe
and move it on the next contact post.
And we need to make the ball
spinning a little less faster
than the previous pose
because it's losing energy on each bounce,
so it's also losing rotation speed.
Then we will create a
last keyframe on frame 43.
It's the frame where the bouncing ball
is currently stopping in space.
And this time we will
switch it's handle type
to Bezier because we need
some easing in the end.
We don't need a linear interpolation.
The ball is slowing down
so its rotation is also slowing down.
To make this stage
readable, I need the grid
because I will need a
point of reference in space
to see if the pattern of the ball
is still aligned with
it whenever it's rolling
on the ground.
So I will re-enable the overlay
and I will zoom a lot onto my animation.
Now I will try to find the point
of reference using the pattern of the ball
and the grid.
When I find it, I will
Shift and right click on it
to place the 3D cursor.
Now what I want is to make sure
that the pattern of the ball
is pointing toward the 3D
cursor as the ball stop.
To do so, just zoom a lot
and then fine tweak the
position of your last keyframe.
You will also need to
slightly tweak the rotation
or orientation and
scale of the last handle
to make sure that we don't
have this sliding effect
on the ground.
Just do it by little touch.
If you see that your
animation is completely off,
it means that your whole
curve is completely off
and the difference between your final key
and the previous key,
the key from frame 30
is way too big.
Rotation easing when
you have a contact pose
is pretty hard to get
right on the first shot,
so be patient, tweak your curve
until you get this nice
rotation on the ground
and the feeling that the ball
is really rolling onto it.
And if you can't achieve
this, don't panic.
Open a new Blender file
and just make the ball
rolling and stopping.
Work on the curve until you
get this animation right
and you will understand the relationship
between your rotation curve
and your translation curve.
It's not a question of math
or geometry or whatever.
It's just a question of practice.
It might be a bit complicated at first
but with a bit of training,
you will get comfortable
with this kind of motion pretty soon.
And if you really want
to get good at animation,
it's very important
because you will use
animation curves every day.
So from there, I can
call this animation done
but there were a few glitches
that I wanted to fix.
Those are little things,
so I won't be going in details into it.
I've just added a very small
additional bounce at the end
and I've a bit revised the
z amplitude of my route
so that the ball get a more even bouncing.
So there is not much you will learn
from the next step.
I'm just refining some of the poses.
I'm doing what we've
been doing just before,
slightly revising the timing,
the amplitude of the curve, et cetera.
What you need to understand
is that again, an animation
is never finished until you say stop.
And just work your animation
until you get to a point of satisfaction.
If you're struggling with the animation,
start a new one.
And this is the only
way you will progress.
I've said this before
and I will say it a lot of
time during this course,
you need to animate to
become a good animator.
You need to make this bouncing
ball exercise multiple time
until you will get a good result.
This is how it works.
I am still struggling
to get a good bouncing ball result
after several years of animation.
And to bring a character to life,
to animate a character,
you need to first be able
to give it motion and then
you will input personality,
input emotion but before
you input emotion,
even into a bouncing ball,
you need to learn motion.
All right, enough of
philosophical discussion.
Let's go ahead with the next video.