- [Instructor] Before we
start animating the squirrel,
we need to talk about overlapping,
follow through and overshoot.
We talk about overlapping motion
when a part of a moving object
is delayed compared to
the rest of the object.
So when we have a look
at the current animation,
we can see that the ball
is leading the motion
while the tail is trained to follow.
If we track the tip of the tail,
we can see that its position is offset
compared to the position of the ball.
This is something we will
use a lot for tails, clothes,
whatever is hanging on our character,
but it can be used on
any part of the body,
a relaxed arm on a walk cycle
or even on this crab character,
the eyes and the crab claws
are currently following
the body motion with a slight delay
so it's also an overlapping motion.
We can also say that
those parts are dragging
behind the body motion.
A very important thing is
those overlapping motion
will communicate weight and
stiffness of the material
or the character you are animating.
The more overlapping motion you will have,
the heavier it will feel.
The more overlapping motion you have,
the smoother it will feel also.
So it can also communicate
if your character is relaxed or stressed.
Follow through is a bit
like overlapping motion.
It defines the fact that
some parts of our character
are still moving after
the character stops,
so their motion is offset
compared to the character.
So basically an overlapping motion
generates a follow through.
And as explained before,
it will communicate
the weight and stiffness
of your character.
We generally use overshoot when a motion
has a dramatical change in its orientation
or when it's stopping.
It's accelerating until
it reaches its destination
and we can see that it's
going a little beyond
its final position and get back.
And this is what we call an overshoot.
Curve wise, it's pretty easy to identify
in the graph editor.
We have those two key frames
that have the same value
so they are aligned on the y-axis
and we have an additional key frame
that goes a little beyond this threshold
and create the overshoot motion.
This is something we
are going to use a lot
because it convey weight, but
also speed, impact, balance,
a lot of things.
It can be very interesting
for a punch, for example,
or to give extra appeal to a fast motion.
And when you combine overshoot
with overlapping motion
or follow through, you can get
very interesting animations.
In this case, there is an
overshoot on the first punch
and some overlapping
motion as the claws jiggle.
Here, I just want to
show you a quick example
on how you can build
convincing overlapping motion very fast.
When opening the blender file,
you will be directly on the
action to do this exercise.
With the first bone of the tail selected,
I will try to spot the frame
where the ball is currently
moving the fastest
and it's frame 10.
I will select the x
rotation curve of the tail,
duplicate the frame and
switch them to auto cleanse
so that it's clean,
and move the key value up
so that the tail is dragging back.
Since the animation is
looping on 40 frame,
there are great chance that on frame 30
I get the fastest motion
of the ball the other way.
So I will duplicate my current frame
and move it on the negative side
so that the tail is
dragging the other way.
Then as we are walking on a cycle,
the first and the last key
frame must be the same,
so I would press shift D it to duplicate
and to make a proper blending,
I need to rotate to those two key frame
using individual origin
to align the starting and ending point
with the current shape of the curve.
Now to make it a little more
stylish and interesting,
I will select those two extreme
and scale them up a bit.
Since the overlapping motion is an offset
of the current motion,
I can select all the point of the curve
and press control C to copy them.
Then I will select the next
tailbone in the hierarchy,
make sure I only have the
x rotation curve selected
and I will press control
V to paste the curve.
Then to slightly offset the motion,
I will press shift D to
duplicate the whole curve
and move it before the frame zero.
This way I have twice
exactly the same motion.
And if I now move the whole curve
by one or two frames to the
right so I'm delaying it,
I will get a dragging motion for free.
From there, I can copy this curve,
select the next joint or the
next bone in the tail hierarchy
and repeat the process.
Select the X curve, press
control V to paste the curve,
I will align it with its original shape
and then offset it a bit by three frames.
So the idea is to use the
same curve for each joint
but offset it in time by one
or two additional frames.
Then you can play with
the shape of the tail
by changing the shape of the curve.
Since I have a symmetrical motion
I can use the 2d cursor as a pivot point.
Its position is represented
by the crossing blue lines
and as seen in the previous chapter,
you can place it wherever you
want by shift right clicking,
or going into the view option
and set its value, here zero.
Now I can press S and Y with
all my key frames selected
to increase the amplitude of the curve
because I'm scaling the
curve only on the Y axis
so we will have a broader
motion of the tail
making it look more relaxed or heavier.
This is a fast, easy and cheap way
to get this kind of
overlapping motion done.
It will sure be a little more
complex on full characters
but that's a good tip.