- [Instructor] Now that we
understand the very basic
of using an armature,
let's do a new bouncing ball animation
but with some more advanced mechanic.
For this animation,
we will be exclusively
working from a side view.
It's like working on a
2D animation in a way.
So I will create a new action
by duplicating our keying set
and I need bouncing ball.
It means that this action
will keep the keying set
we have created before
or the keyframe we have inserted before.
And I've enabled the only
active keying set option
in the auto keying
and enabled the filter available.
On frame zero, I will
position my bouncing ball
at about nine meters on the z-axis,
using the root controller.
This controller will allow us
to move the ball in space,
while the other will be used
for secondary motion
like squash and stretch
and rotation or revolution of the ball.
We can plan our animation
by directly drawing on the screen.
I'm holding the D key
while left clicking and
dragging on my screen
to use the grease pencil notes.
Here I've made a beautiful drawing
of the path of the ball
that we are going to animate.
The idea is to bring a
bit of physics into it
so that it looks more believable
and input a bit of damping
until the ball stop.
You can access your
annotation in the view panel
under Annotation and
click the minus button
if you want to remove it.
As soon as you make a new drawing,
a new annotation will appear.
You can change the color
by clicking the little
vignette next to its name.
These annotation are in 3D,
so you can rotate around them
and you can create new annotation layers
or new annotation slot by
clicking the plus button.
If you make multiple drawing
on multiple keyframe,
a new drawing will be
created on each frame,
allowing you to do awesome animation
with the annotation
or a crappy drawing like this one.
All joke apart,
it's very handy whenever you want
to review your animation
or plan the next move.
Let's start animating our bouncing ball.
I will select all the existing key,
press T and set them to constant
so that we can start our new animation
as we did before by the blocking stage.
We will be animating in pose to pose
by first setting our main
keyframe on golden keys.
Then create some in between
and then start polishing.
So I'm currently trying to match
the different extreme poses
of the ball.
The different poses when it hit the ground
and the different poses when
it is at its highest point
in the air.
Seeing that I don't have a
green line between the keys
on my action editor,
I figured there was
still busy interpolation.
So I've pressed T
and reset to constant all the keyframe.
As I've erased my annotation,
I have a hard time figuring
out the position of my ball.
But there is tools that could help me
and that we have already used.
It's the motion path.
So while I'm trying to
figure out the spacing
of the ball from one frame to the other,
it would be easier if I add an ID
of the previous position of the ball.
So instead of fighting
with my animation and my brain,
trying to figure out or remember
where the ball was in the previous frame,
I will simply add up to
the armature properties,
not the object properties.
And here I will find exactly
the same motion path menu
that we have seen previously
but this time, we are using
it at the armature level,
meaning that I'm currently
tracking my root ball.
And I can track any of
the bounce of the ball
or even multiple bounce at once.
I've previously set a couple
of quick favorite I can
access pressing the Q key.
You can create your quick favorite
or assign your own shortcut
to any tool in the window
by right clicking on it.
From there, it's way
easier to position the ball
from one key to the other.
I'm creating a new
keyframe every five frame.
This is pretty arbitrary.
You could use every 10 frame or whatever.
I'm used to use every five frame.
And when all my golden keys will be done,
I will then go into a slight timing path
where I will move all those
keyframe left to right
to revise the timing of the animation.
Here I'm writing the ultimate pose
and then I will play my animation
or scrub through the timeline
to fill the motion.
See if the up and down
and forward motion feels natural.
And this is something
you have to train about.
You have to train your eye about this.
And this require experience.
And you will get experience only
by animating, not watching videos.
So even if you are a
more advanced animator,
I advise you to do this exercise.
And if you are a
beginner, embrace failure.
Failing is an important step
in the learning path.
The sooner you accept failure,
the faster you will learn.
And being a good artist
is not really about your success
but the way you bounce
back after a failure
and the way you learn from it.
All right, let's stop our
philosophical discussion here
and let's go with animation.
In my action editor,
I'm moving all the keyframe of the ball
on the timeline.
The smaller the bounce,
the fewer the frame I will
have between two keyframes.
And then I'm moving the latest
pose pretty further away
because the ball will be
slowing down before it stops.
So it will take some time to get there.
To quickly manipulate the key,
you can box select them
as we have seen before
or click the summary
so that you will get all
the keyframe underneath.
You can watch my timing on the timeline
but don't feel wrong
if your timing is not the same as mine
because it depend on the
height of your bounce.
And we will certainly revise the timing
during the animation.
But try to make it feel
as natural as possible
as soon as possible.
We will now start detailing
this blocking path,
meaning that we will
add a few more keyframe
and input a bit of squash and stretch,
using the upper and
lower green controllers.
I will start by adding those stretching
and squashing information
on top of the existing keyframes.
As explained in the previous chapter,
when the ball is contacting the ground,
it reaches it at full speed.
So it is full stretched.
And since the first pose is the one
where our ball has the maximum speed,
it is the pose where it
will be the most stretched.
You can use the stretching controller
to orient the ball toward
its previous frame.
Just translate it a little backward.
This controller only allow you
to move it using its
location, not its rotation.
The ball will automatically stretch
toward the green controllers.
I will then scrub through the next frame
and with my green
controller still selected,
I will press Alt + G
to cancel any location transformed on it.
I will take the lower squash controller
and I will push it up just a little touch
to make the ball squash
when it slow down in the air.
I can see that I have
a little interpolation
between my keyframe,
so I will select them all, press T
and reset them to constant.
This happen sometime when you try
to add the constant interpolation
on a single keyframe.
So I will go ahead
and input a bit of stretching
and orientation to the ball on each frame
and as I go along,
I will reduce the stretching strength
on each consecutive bounce
because the ball is losing energy.
Each time, I slightly translate
the upper green controller
toward the previous frame
and when it's up in the air,
I'm slightly moving the
lower controller up.
I have forgotten to insert a keyframe
on each channels.
So in the action editor,
I will go on each keyframe,
press I and choose all channels.
I can now add some breakdowns
or in between to my animation.
This will really help
me reading the animation
in the blocking stage.
So what we are going to do now
is add the squash just
after landing of the ball.
Be very cautious with
the squash and stretch
because it translate the
softness of the ball.
If you're going to extreme,
your ball will look like a water balloon.
As impact occur on frame eight,
on frame nine, I will
slightly squash the ball.
Then on frame 10, before the
ball is leaving the ground,
I will stretch it a bit
toward the next position.
To do so, again select
the upper controller
and press G to move it
towards the frame 13.
See how after the bounce I'm stretching
the ball less than before?
Because as it touch the ground,
it's losing energy,
so I can't make it stretch
as much as when it was
going to touch the ground.
Again, I did a little
mistake along the way.
If you check frame 18,
we can see that our bouncing ball
is not touching the ground
and I'm offsetting its root controller
to fix the problem
but the issue doesn't come from
the root controller position
but from the second squash
and stretch controller.
The lower one.
When I inserted the keyframe
on all the controller previously,
I've forgotten to reset its position
when the ball was touching the ground.
So currently, this controller
is still in its squash position
as when the ball is in the air
position on frame 22 and 13.
And this is why the blocking
stage is so important
because if I was already
splining my animation,
I would have a hard time to stop this
and I will be fighting this
deformation with my curves.
So with the lower green
controller selected,
I will go over all the keyframe
and press Alt + G
and you can see the ball getting back
into its original shape.
And now I can fix the root position
on each of those frames.
Now, to make my action
editor a bit cleaner
and more readable, I will
collapse all the panel
because I don't need
to see all the channels
and starting with the
root bounce controller,
I will duplicate the frame 18
and move it on frame 20
and get rid of frame 19.
Since the ball position doesn't change
between those two frames,
I don't need to have
a keyframe in between.
And duplicating frame 18 on frame 20
will ensure I have consistency
into my animation or at
least onto the position
of my ball when it's on the ground.
I will also duplicate frame 26 on frame 27
because the ball is still on the ground
on this frame.
Then I'm checking each frame
and I see that I need to
revise a bit the squashing
with the lower controller
because it's still very
strong on frame 29.
So I press Alt + G to cancel it
and then press G and Alt + Shift
to move it on the z-axis very subtly.
From there, I will play
my animation several time
to fill the timing.
So I can see that on the first bounce,
there is something a bit off.
Having the first upper
position on frame 13
is a bit too soon
and we configure this in the timeline,
the upper pose is on frame 13
and the contact pose on frame 18.
So I only have three
frame to get up in the air
and five to fall down.
So I will offset all the
keyframe from frame 13
by one frame
and then I will move all the
keyframe from frame 18 or 19
by one frame back
so that I get an even spacing
between the upper pose and the lower pose.
The first bounce uses
eight frame to complete.
So I guess we can use six frame
to complete the second bounce.
So frame 20 will be the contact post.
23, the upper pose,
26, the next contact.
And the final bounce
could use one frame less.
So our bouncing ball
timing is quite logical.
I start with an eight-frame bounce,
then a six-frame bounce
and finally, a four-frame bounce.
It's totally fine if
your timing is different.
The important thing is to
get this logical pattern
between the first bounce
and the last bounce
with a decreasing number of frame
between each bounce.
This logical approach of motion
will help us solve some
animation problem later on.
It's not a rule of thumb though
because animation is also
a matter of randomness.
Our ball could be bouncing on
an uneven ground, for example,
so it will make the timing
a bit off at some point.
But in your learning path,
it's important to understand
the logic of motion.
In this specific case,
the fact that the ball is losing energy
on each bounce so the timing
between each contact pose will be shorter,
in the next video, we
will polish the animation
using the graph editor.
To summarize, we have seen
that we can use the
grease pencil annotation
to plan our animation.
Using the motion path display is important
even at the blocking stage
as it really help us figuring
out the motion of the ball.
We have to be careful when
using squash and stretch
because it does communicate the softness
or the material of our ball.
So ask yourself what kind
of ball am I animating?
We can tackle our animation timing
with a logical approach.
Our bouncing ball will lose energy
on each bounce so there will
be smaller and smaller until.