- [Instructor] Let's have a quick overview
of the squirrel rig.
When opening the Blender file,
you will find two object,
our squirrel Armature
and the squirrel object
that is using an Armature modifier.
The object is called a squirrel.
And it has as all material.
By default, you should
have the Text Editor opened
with this squirrel rig
UI text file opened.
When my rig is selected and in pause mode
if I press the play button,
it will execute the script
and generate a little
UI that will allow us
to hide or display the
bones of our character.
The script doesn't run automatically,
you will have to run it
each time you will open your blender file.
What if your script is not open
because you don't have
the Text Editor opened?
you just go to the editors panels,
select the Text Editor and in the Library
you will select the squirrel rig UI
and then just press the Play button.
You can then close this editor area.
The rig is pretty straightforward.
The root bone allow us to
move the entire character,
the dorsal roots allow
us to move the whole body
and give it its orientation.
But the legs won't follow.
You will find a chest and a hip controller
that can be moved, rotated and scape.
The neck and head can also be controlled
by one single bone that
will behave the same
as the chest and hips bone.
You can then find some tweaker
bone that will allow us
to only rotate the neck
or only rotate the head.
Smaller controller
bones are also available
to be able to squash and stretch the head.
Move the ears at will,
close the eyes or move
the tip of the nose.
All the bone transform
channels are already locked
when they are not to be used
making our keying set
step a little faster.
(whoosh)
The legs are using inverse
kinematic controllers,
meaning that we are controlling
the whole arm or leg
by simply moving the end of
the foot of our character.
While the motion should
come from the shoulder,
then the arm, then the forearm to the end
it's inversed.
The arm controller is just here to be able
to give an orientation to the elbow.
On the back leg,
we will also find an inverse kinematic
from the foot controller,
but the heel and knee orientation
will be using a pole target.
It's a bone that can move freely in space
and the knee or heel of our character
will be pointing at it.
The tail use a simple
forward kinematic bone chain.
So it basically rotates
or is being controlled
from its root to its tip.
We will then find a lot
of secondary controllers
that will allow us to move
each joint of the character.
They will mainly be used
to fix some deformation
or to add subtle motion to the character.
The rig also comes with
some custom property
that we can access by using these bones.
When the bone is selected
we can find those custom
properties in the item panel.
Those properties will allow us
to hide the legs of the character
or the tail of the character.
This will be really
useful to isolate the body
and clearly read it's motion.
The tail follow option allow us
to whether isolate on not
the rotation of the tail.
By default, the tail of our character
is following the rotation of the hips
and is aligned with it.
But if we select the property boon
and set this tail follow to zero,
the tail is not rotating
with the hips anymore.
This will make our life way easier
when it comes to animating the tail.
So before we jump into animation,
I will just create the
keying set for our character
by inserting a key frame on the channels
that are going to be used
and remove those that are locked.
Nothing really interesting here.
So I will switch to a time-lapse
till the end of this video.
(whoosh)
(slow piano music)