- [Instructor] The time has finally come
to animate our squirrel character.
The first thing to do
is to play the Squirrel_Rig_UI.pi script.
It will enable our rig layer
and we will be able to
hide bone groups easily.
You can duplicate our keying set action
and create a new action
that we call 01 Run cycle.
And then double check our preferences
by going into the Edit
menu in the top bar,
Preferences, Animation
and check that the Only
Insert Available is on.
It will override our usual
automatic keying set,
making sure that we don't have any key
that will be written
if there is not an existing keyframe.
If I move this knee
joint tweaker controller,
you can see that the auto keying is on
but Blender is only recording
and writing location keyframe
for this controller.
This way, our action editor
is clean in the keying
but on top of this,
we can still use a specific keying set.
And I will enable the
whole character keying set.
This way, when I press the I key
to insert a keyframe,
Blender will key all the controllers
of my character and this is done
on top of the only
available option we have set
in the preferences.
When we were blocking the
bouncing ball animation,
I advised you to key all the controllers.
And here is the reason why.
I will rapidly block out a turn
with a change of foot position.
Our little friend is rotating his body
to look to the right
and he's also moving his feet accordingly.
During most of the animation,
his right front foot stays on the ground
and it switches position
only on the very last frame.
Here I've done the blocking
of those three poses,
only keying the controller I'm using.
It looks great in step mode
but as soon as I will switch to spline,
the right front foot
will be interpolating
from the very first frame
to the last.
And it doesn't look good at all.
And I will have to move the keyframe,
insert new keyframe, et cetera.
While if I insert a keyframe
on the whole character
on each main poses,
I will get a better behavior
and the right front foot will only move
from frame 20 to frame 30.
So you may think this is not a big deal
but believe me, if you
have this kind of problem
on the whole character on every leg,
this is going to be a pain.
And if you have the same issue
with all the controller,
the head, the hips,
that's gonna be a nightmare.
So key all your controllers
during the blocking stage.
The second step is to study references.
You will find a link to this one
in the documentation.
It's very important to watch
as much reference as possible
and honestly, nowadays,
it's not that complicated
with YouTube to find good
references of animals.
I guess you already know
what I'm going to show here
is that the body of the squirrel
is like the bouncing ball.
Squashed when it's on the ground
and as soon as it's going in the air,
it is stretching.
Basically, the chest of the creature
is arriving first
and then the hips are catching up.
So when preparing an animation,
you have to make this work
of seeing the character
as a whole piece.
Look at the curve
that make the body, for example.
Once you have the broad detail,
you have to go for the smaller detail.
Look how the front feet
arrive at the separated time.
It's just one or two frame of difference
but it will make your animation way better
than if both end arrive at the same time.
In animation, when we
get something symmetrical
or something occurring at the same time,
we call this twinning.
And this is something
you should always avoid
unless it is done on purpose.
If you do the Hulk smashing the ground
with both his hands,
you want both to hit the
ground at the same time.
It will communicate impact and strength.
But in the case of our squirrel,
look at how breaking the
symmetry looks way more natural.
On the left, the character looks stiff,
on the right, it looks way better.
So don't forget to avoid twinning
both in timing and in shape
and let's get started.
I don't know how many
frame I will need to block
or how long will be the jump
but I will start by aligning the feet
with the ground.
One cool feature
is that once I've positioned one
of the foot, I can select it
and press Control + C
to copy its pose and you
will get a copied pose
to buffer message in
the footer of Blender.
If I now press Control + Shift + V,
I will paste the mirrored
pose automatically
on the other foot.
This is a shortcut I'm going to use a lot.
From there, I will start
posing the pushing pose
when our character is preparing to jump.
So I have my reference
image on a second screen.
So I invite you to have it always open
and try to find the frame
where the squirrel is preparing to jump.
His body should be very squashed
and the root of the
torso almost horizontal
with the ground.
Starting with the back legs,
I'm slightly rotating the foot
toward the outside of the body.
This way, I'm breaking the symmetry both
from the side view and the front view.
Then I will move its front feet right
in between the back feet.
I'm also breaking the symmetry,
having one of the front
leg slightly more forward
than the other, one slightly
more raised than the other.
Then we need to squash the whole body
by rotating the chest controller
and the hips controller.
You can also slightly move them
toward the center of gravity
of the character.
Just think of your character as a box
and this box has to
contain the heaviest part
of the character, the chest and the hips.
The head and the tail
counterbalance each other
and if we draw a straight
line in the middle
of this pose, we can see
that our feet are more or less
framing this contact point
between the vertical line and the ground,
offering a balanced pose to our character.
When blocking a character,
you should always start
with the most extreme position.
So I will now block the airborne position.
I start by moving the root controller
by half of the length of the jump.
In this case, I move it
by 30 centimeter forward
and then I will use the torso controller
to raise the character.
In most cases, you will use
the root controller only
to move your character
on the y and x-axis.
When I do a run or walk cycle,
I generally deal with it
without moving the root bone
as if the character was on a treadmill.
But it's a bit harder to
read the shape of the jump.
So during the blocking stage,
we will use what we call a root motion.
And when the animation will be finished,
we will get rid of this root motion
so that our character
will be jumping without moving forward.
This way it's gonna be
way easier to use it
as a run cycle
and we will just have
to move the root bone
wherever we want in our scene.
Don't worry if you don't get it right now,
we will do it together later on.
Back to our air pose.
You can see that I've
slightly stretched the body.
So I've canceled the rotation on the hips
and the chest and then I'm
resetting them by hand.
So this is something I advise you to do
when you don't have a
major change in the pose.
You select the hips and
the chest controller
and press Alt + R and Alt + G
to get rid of any rotation
that was recorded on the previous pose.
And then you create the new pose yourself.
Blocking a new pose from a neutral one
will push you to correctly
look at your reference
and force you to work on
the shape of the new one.
The back legs are pointing
toward their starting point
while the front leg are pushing forward
to pull the whole body in the air.
Both the front and back feet
are currently pointing inward.
It preserve balance
and aerodynamism to the character.
You can use the pull target
and the rotation controller
to fix the elbow and the
knees of your character.
Don't forget to scrub between your first
and second pose
to kind of feel the motion, the movement.
Then to improve the pose,
I will stretch my character even more
and realign a bit the hips and the tail.
During the blocking stage,
figuring the overlapping
motion of the tail
is pretty hard.
That's why I'm just working
with the very first controller
of the tail.
We can work on the
follow-through of the tail
while detailing the blocking
or even during the
polishing of the animation.
To finish the blocking
of those extreme pose,
I will have to guess the landing position.
On the air extreme pose,
I will set the root bone position to -0.3
and I will duplicate all the keys
on frame zero and move them on frame 10.
Since the airborne root
position on the y-axis
was -0.3, I will set the landing at -0.6,
two time further.
Now I scrub through the keyframe
to feel the motion
and I feel should be a little further.
So I just need to select the root bone
and on frame five,
I will try a -0.4
and now I feel like I need
to tweak a bit this pose
to make the character a
little more horizontal.
So this is something important.
Don't hesitate to revise your blocking.
The blocking stage is
the most important stage.
And if you don't do it properly,
if you don't spend the time now,
you will suffer even more
during the polishing stage.
I can now push my root bone
to the position -0.8 on the landing frame
and now it feels like the squirrel
is jumping too far away for me.
So I will try to find an in
between with -0.35 and -0.7.
Compared to the reference,
our squirrel is making pretty
large jump to move forward
but animation is not necessarily
about copying the reality.
It's exaggeration.
And this will lead us to a peel.
It's a but like making
a caricature of motion.
When you do a caricature,
you try to find the cool feature
of the face and exaggerate them.
We are doing the same here with motion.
In the next video,
we will start adding breakdowns
to detail the blocking
animation of our character.