- [Instructor] Before we start
animating our query character
we need to understand the difference
between world space and local space.
If we have a look at this world object,
as soon as I will change
its value on the x-axis,
it will move on the x-axis.
If I change the Y the Z,
it will follow the global
axis, also known as world axis.
So our sphere is currently
moving following world space.
If I now rotate my planet on the X axis,
we can see that it's Y
axis is no longer aligned
with our seen axis also
known as world axis.
But if I change it's Y value,
it will still slide along the
Y axis of our world space.
And this is because on any object,
transform channel are read in hierarchy.
The first transformed
channel read are location,
then rotation, and finally scale.
That's why the rotation doesn't affect
the location transform of the planet.
It will be such a pain to
animate or to read curve.
But since scaling is read or
is performed after rotation,
we can see that when I
scale on the Y, X or Z,
it does follow the local
space of the planet.
To better illustrate what is local space
let's display the Bob collection.
This is Bob, and as you can see,
he's aligned with world space.
His head is pointing
upward along the Z axis.
His origin point is slightly offset
from the center of our scene.
And we can see this in
its location coordinates.
So what I will do now is to
place Bob on our planet earth.
So we can see that Bob has no rotation
and is slightly offset from the Z axis.
I will now parent Bob to the planet.
So I will first select Bob,
then the planet and
press control P objects.
Now, Bob is a parent of our planet object.
And as soon as our planet
object move or rotate,
Bob will follow.
When rotating the planet on the Y axis,
we can see the coordinates
in the rotation channel.
And if I display my planet axis,
we can see that they're
aligned with Bob axis.
So Bob has been rotated
in world space his Z axis
is no longer pointing up.
But if we have a look at
his rotation coordinate,
we can see that they are still to zero.
Because while the word has been rotated,
Bob, hasn't rotated, he
hasn't moved off an inch.
He has visually rotated in world space
but in its local space, he hasn't rotated.
It's like when you are driving a car,
you are moving in world space
because the car is moving,
but you you're not moving,
you're still sit in the car.
You are a child of the car.
So if I now edit the z location of Bob,
we can see that he's moving
along its own Z axis,
also known as local space.
So world space correspond
to the axis in our scene
while Bob local space
correspond to the axis
that are displayed on top of his head.
So if we now have look
to the graph editor,
whenever I will move the X
curve of my planet, it will
follow the world space as
our bouncing ball previously.
But if I now do the same with Bob,
I will see that will be
offset on its own X location,
on its local space.
And this is a very important concept
when we will start animating characters.
Think of the hand parented to the arm,
we will need to animate
it in its local space.
As the hand will be the child of the arm.
On top of this, we still
have our channel sequence,
meaning that the rotation
occur before the scale
and after the location.
So I can still rotate the
character in its local space
and then scale it afterward.
And both rotation and scaling
will follow its local axis.
So, basically you are always animating
in the local space of your
character, object, whatever.
But by default it's local axes
are aligned with world space.
But as soon as you have a
parent and child relationship,
there are great changes that they're
no longer aligned with space.
If you are using the gizmo
from your transformation,
you can switch it to local space.
And a lot of animators
uses the gizmo to animate
and uses them with a local space.
As I've rotated the planet
and Bob is still a child of the planet,
it's local space has been rotated,
and we can see that the
axis of the manipulator
or gizmo are aligned.
So when I use the manipulator
to move Bob on its Z axis,
I can see his Z coordinate changing.
So the gizmo give us
a great representation
of the local space of our character.
And it does also work well
whenever I'm performing
a rotation around the nexus.
And we also have a
rotation and scaling gizmo
at our disposal.
But you have to be cautious
with those manipulator
because they can be misleading.
It's totally fine to use them
to manipulate your character,
but don't rely on them too much
when it comes to figure out
what is the local space of your character.
Because if I do rotate my character
and then try to perform a translation,
the manipulator will be visually aligned
with the local space of my character.
But the location
coordinates of my character
wont be aligned anymore.
Because the rotation is
performed after the translation.
So when I will be editing
my curve, I will be editing
the current Y movement I
see on the screen right now.
Because the curve's output
has the value of the location,
rotation and scale that we can
see in the transform channel.
And it's not the case of the manipulator.
So if I really want to
align the manipulator
with the local space of my character,
I need to reset any
rotation on my character.
And now they are aligned.
If my character is rotating,
moving it using the
manipulator in local space,
will currently edit
different location values.
I know it can be a bit
confusing, but don't worry.
It will make sense
whenever we are animating.
And you won't have to
take all those things
in consideration, but it's
important for you to learn them
to better understand
animation in 3D space.
When editing your curve with
a bit of trial and error,
their behavior will make sense,
even in local space, don't worry.
To summarize, we have seen
that by default an object space
is world space.
In a parent to child relationship,
the child will follow any
transformation of his parent,
but it's transform
channel won't be modified.
And this is because transform channels
output the local space
coordinate of an object.
Transform channel are read in sequence
with location first, then
rotation, and finally scale.
You can use the gizmo in local space
to make your manipulation easier,
but don't rely on them to
figure out the orientation
of your object.