- [Instructor] From the time being,
we've been animating only object.
And we have seen that each
time we try to animate
a new object, the new animation
or a new action data is created.
And when it comes to animating an object,
we are currently only animating
at point, its origin point.
But what if we want to animate
a more complex object or a character,
will we have to create an
action for each finger,
or do you bend an armor if
it's not a separated object?
There is one tool that
allow us to do this,
and you've probably
already heard about it.
It's a rig or an armature.
So if you think of a
human with character rig,
it's generally a skeleton
with a bunch of constraints and mechanism
that allow the animator to
manipulate the character
in an intuitive fashion.
And you can rig absolutely anything.
Here is a new version
of our bouncing ball.
So there is a new object in my scene,
I can find my ball object,
but I also can find this
ball armature object,
and as an object, it has
transformed channels.
And as any other object,
it's a container with specific data,
we can't find armature data and bone data.
Also as a specific object,
it has a specific mode,
an edition mode, that
allow to bird the armature,
and that is used by a riggers,
so you won't need to enter
edit mode at any time
and a pose mode, that is
the mode that will allow us
to manipulate the armature
and animate whatever character
or object that is bound to this armature.
We can change mode from object to pose
by pressing Control + Tab.
So let's have a closer look
to this rig or armature.
When in pose mode, you can
select whatever controller
you want, those are called
bones, and you can consider them
as being sub object of the armature.
It means that each bone
will have its own transformed channels
and each bone have a specific
behavior or a specific task
such as being created by the rigor.
On our bone domain
controller is called the root
and allow us to move the entire ball.
Moving the green controllers allow us
to use squash and stretch,
the yellow controller allow
us to rotate the ball.
So instead of transforming
the ball directly,
here we are using those controllers
to create those transformation.
And it will allow us to
create way more complex
transformation on to a character
than animating simple objects,
because the armature can deform the object
that is bound to it.
The armature is actually a simple modifier
that deform our object.
So a versatile armature
or rig will allow you
to give the pose you
want for your character
and the good rig will give you the maximum
of posing possibilities
with intuitive fashion.
So before we start animating
this query character,
I will give you some good practice
when it comes to animating
using an armature.
(swooshing slide)
With my ball rig file open,
I will enable the Auto King
and I will switch to pose mode
by pressing Control + Tab.
As soon as I transform
one of the controller
by selecting it pressing G, S or R
as I will do for any object,
I can see that my Auto King
is recording what I'm doing
and Blender is creating a keyframe
for the transform channels
of the controllers.
The first awesome thing is that
if I switch to the doc sheet
in the action editor and switch to see
all the keyed channel, I can see that
all the different manipulator animation
are stored into a single action
because the action is associated
to the armature object
and we can consider each manipulator
as being a sub object
that can be animated.
And as for any object,
I can see that each of the
manipulator has their location,
rotation and scale key, but
each of those controller
has a specific desk, for example,
this rotation controller,
if I try to move it or scale it, I can't.
And when I try to rotate it,
it only rotates around its x-axis.
So instead of having a keyframe
for every transform channel,
that couldn't be better
if I add only a keyframe
on its x rotation, since I won't be using
any other of its transform channel.
So I've selected all the
transform channel I don't want,
And I will simply press
X to get rid of them.
Now, I will go a little further in time
and I will try to rotate the ball.
As soon as I rotate to
rotation controller,
I can see Auto King is on and
the x value being arranged,
meaning that it's being
transformed but not recorded.
But as soon as I release the
transform Blender, right again,
a keyframe on all the transform channels,
and I can go ahead for
a long time like that,
removing the keyframe I don't want
and whenever I try to
transform this manipulator,
Blender writes a keyframe on everything.
So to get rid of this issue,
we need to create what we call a king set.
To access the king option, we
need to go into the timeline.
So the first thing I do
is renaming the action
and call it zero zero
so that it will be first
in the alphabetic order, king set ball.
Now I will check each controller
and for each transform
channel that is locked,
I will get rid of the
corresponding keyframe
because these are the only keys
that will really serve
the animation of the ball.
In the end I only have
14 keyframes remaining
instead of the 36 initial I had.
So my action editor and my graph editor
will sure be way cleaner, I
now need to open the timeline.
So I will drag a new editor
and switch to the timeline.
In the timeline header I
will go to the king set
and in the active king,
I can see that I have a
lot of different options.
So I will choose rotation
and I will try rotating
my manipulator then
Blender is still recording
all the keyframe, and this is because
we need to tell Blender
to use this king set
by clicking the arrow near
the auto recording button
and choose only active king set.
Now when I try transforming
my manipulator,
all the rotation channel will be keyframe.
So we are getting close,
I will get rid of the unwanted keyframe
and if we go back into the king set,
we can see that there is a lot of option
and the one that is interesting
for us is available.
From there Blender will only
auto record the keyframe
that has already been written,
meaning that to channel
where we have inserted a keyframe
file to use this king set.
If you haven't set the first keyframe
before applying the king set,
then the Auto King
won't write any keyframe
and if I try inserting a
new keyframe pressing I,
I will get this error message.
Basically, I can't write a
keyframe with the actual setup.
To fix that, we only need to
insert a keyframe directly
into the transform channel panel,
then I can get rid of the
two channels I don't want,
the Y and Z channel.
There is another way to set the Auto King
on available by default, it's
by going into the preferences,
animation, only insert available.
It's really a matter of
personal preferences.
I personally use the king filter,
please note that I'm
using Blender 2.92 Alpha,
so the position of the
different option might change.
All right, now you are ready
to animate using an armature.
We have seen that we can use an armature
to perform more complex transformation,
that an armature can deform
the object that is bound to it.
So the armature object
is made of super object
and called bone, each of those
controller bone can be king,
but Blender will create a single action
that will hold the different key
of all the controller
of a single armature.
It is highly recommended to
create a king set to keep
your dopesheet and graph
editor as clean as possible.