- [Narrator] Welcome to chapter three.
You are beginning in
animation and this chapter
is one of the most important chapter.
You will learn everything you need to know
to create all the squirrel animation
used in the first course teaser.
We will warm up through
some bouncing ball exercises
where you will be able to
sharpen your motion technique
and get familiar with
the use of an armature
or a rig to animate.
I will mix those exercise video
with some theoretical videos
where we will explain the core concept
between world space and local space,
overlapping, follow through
and overshoot in an animation.
The different steps of animation creation,
blocking, breakdowns, in
between going to spline
and polishing the
animation, understanding ox,
timing, and spacing.
We will also have an in-depth
look to the NLA editor.
This is a very important chapter
as you will learn all the fundamentals
and as I would repeat it along the way
it's very important that
you make every exercises.
If you want to get good at animation
and be able to create all those animation
you have to animate.
Watching those video won't be enough.
Make those animation,
don't be afraid to fail.
It's a part of the learning process
but if you carefully
follow the different steps
and understand the core
principle, you will rapidly get
to a satisfying result, let's get started.