- Finally, the polishing
stage of our run cycle
or gem cycle animation, as you wish.
With all of our keys
selected, I will press T
and switch to Bézier interpolation.
This is what we call
splining the animation,
because we are just changing the curve
from constant to spline.
And I must say that from our blocking
it already looks pretty cool.
I will quickly clean up the ROOT bone.
So I will select it
and use the only selected
option in the action editor.
When doing a locomotion cycle
it's better to have a constant speed.
So I just need to keep the first
and last key frame and switch
them to linear interpolation.
Linear interpolation means constant speed.
And while we are polishing the animation
we can enable or disable the ROOT motion
to check the motion path of our character,
while moving forward or in place.
For the polishing stage,
it can be interesting
to use the properties I
have created on the streak.
You can access them
selecting the property bone
on top of the character.
The hide properties are
not supposed to be keyed.
That's a mistake I have made.
So I will just try click on it
and choose to clear key frames.
Hiding the legs and hiding the tail
while we are polishing the torso,
for example, will help a lot,
because we won't be distracted
by the legs motion nor the tail motion.
And so we can approach the animation
of the torso of our
character as a bouncing ball.
A very common rule in animation
is that everything is a bouncing ball.
That's why the bone simple
exercise is so important.
Whenever you are learning animation.
Finally, as always
it's very important to use the motion path
as explained before I've
added to my quick favorite
so I can rapidly access
them, pressing the Q key
but you can also find it
under the armature properties.
Let's starts by polishing
the torso controller
or the root of the torso, if you will.
I've hidden the tail
but I advise you to also hide the legs
because they are a bit
distracting in the end.
I've hidden them a little later on
but it's better to hide
them right at the beginning.
I will first work on the Z location curve
since it's the most
influential curve in the motion
of this controller, it's
pretty straightforward
because it does really looks
like our bouncing ball curve.
There are two main differences.
I've slightly scaled the upper vector.
So that my character is kind of
floating when it's
reached its highest point.
So it brings a bit of
style into my animation.
And the second thing is
that we have a slight
easing on the contact frame
because the legs of our character
are absorbing the shock.
So we don't have a broken vector
on frame zero and frame 12.
Remember that frame zero and
frame 12 must be the same.
So I will basically revise a bit
the position of frame one and
11, and then they I will scale
my key frame on frame six,
when I'm editing the curve,
especially this kind of broad curve.
I often only press the cue key
in the 3D view port to
access my quick favorite.
And I update the motion path.
Don't forget to check the animation
both with the ROOT enabled and disabled.
Here the video is sped up twice
but you have the curve in
reference on the top right corner.
And at this stage
you should be able to polish the curve.
Again as an art form,
I can't teach you
everything about animation
because a lot of it is
about feeling the motion.
So you have to feel if you
want to hold your character
a little more in the air or
make him jump a little higher,
a little lower, that's about you.
The thing I'm pretty convinced here
is that the leg are really distracting.
So don't forget to hide them right now.
I'm now switching to the X rotation curve
and the weird thing here is
that we have our XYZ rotation
but also W your rotation.
And there is also this
strange quaternion name.
Don't worry about that for the time being
we will be focusing on the
X, Y, and Z rotation curve.
We can kind of ignore the
W quaternion rotation curve
for the time being.
And I will explain you Euler
and quaternion rotation later
in this course,
the X rotation curve allows us to
lean our character forward and backwards.
We can see, we have an
important change on the rotation
or orientation of the
torso of our character
when it's contacting
and leaving the ground.
I've created a little
plateau in the middle when
our character is floating in the air
the key on zero and 12 are identical
and I've rotated the angles
so that we have a continuous
flow of the curve.
When I'm editing this rotation curve,
I'm thinking of how I want
my character to behave.
It's a very light animal
with a lot of agility.
So I want a very smooth motion.
So I want to shape the body
of my character so that it
follows the flow of the jump.
And I curve the body even more
when the character is landing
and pushing to jump again.
When I got this feeling
I fixed the first and last key frame
aligning them using the individual origin.
It allows you to rotate both
key frame independently,
and then I've created this little plateau.
To have my character slightly flatter
or horizontal while in the air.
It will make it float a bit more.
And here is the result after
polishing the X rotation.
The Y Location, motion of our
character is barely noticeable
because most of the forward
and backward motion is
generated by the ROOT bone.
And I've used the Y location
of the body control during the bulking
only for very subtle
adjustment of the pose.
So I've zoomed on the curve
because the value are very subtle.
And what I will do is
just to align the curve
on frame zero and frame 12.
This will remove any
jitter during the cycle.
We can enable later on the cycle modifier
so that you will see the
continuity of your curve,
and it might be a little
more intuitive to edit them
to align them.
I will apply the same process
to the Y and Z rotation curve.
They are here to slightly twist the torso
of our character and slightly
rotate it side to side.
So they just communicate
a bit, the fact that we
haven't been using tweening
when our character is landing
meaning that his front legs
don't land at the same time.
So there will be a bit
of twisting in the
shoulders and in the torso
because everything is
connected on our character.
And this is something super important
when you are animating a character,
remember that everything is connected.
So if you move your hand,
it will, at some point
make your legs move.
I know it's a bit extreme,
but just keep this in mind
so that you won't forget to
kind of polish a bit everything
or think about it whenever you are working
on the extremity of your contractor.
So what I will do for the Y
and Z quaternion rotation,
since those are very subtle motion,
I will just create a
subtle flow in the curve,
making sure that when the curve is going
from one extreme frame 12 to the other
frame zero, it does flow properly.
So I create a slight overshoot
by pushing the key number two, a bit down.
The idea's to get smoother
changes in the curve
instead of adding very
brutal changes in the curve.
So it's a bit the same with the Z curve.
When I zoom on it,
we can see that we have a peak at the end.
I will smooth the curve down,
rotate the very last key frame,
duplicated it on frame one.
Now my curve is diving
between frame zero and one.
So I will just push down a
bit the key frame number one
onto the front two
to get a smoother curve
on its whole shape.
We haven't used scaling so
those curves are perfectly flat.
So the first pass of polishing is done
for the body controller.
Those curves will probably be adjusted
when we have polished the chest,
hips and head of our character.