- [Instructor] In this video,
we are going to polish
the legs of the character.
It's pretty important
because it will help
defining the silhouette
of our character.
It will also communicate
its weight and agility.
Here you can see the final result
of the whole character polished.
Try to use the file
provided as a reference.
Since they are the biggest,
I will start with the back
legs of the character.
Since we are using inverse
kinematic mechanism
for those leg, the location
are the most influential transform channel
for the animation of the legs.
This is the first channel
we are going to edit.
Now the legs of our character
are dragging a lot toward the ground,
making them looks very heavy,
and like our character has
a hard time raising them.
So we will need to rework the leg position
while in the air.
But we do need to keep a bit of delay
on the leg motion
since they are dragged by the body.
And the first thing I will do
is to offset by one frame
all the keys on frame six,
putting a bit of delay
on the air extreme pose
of the leg.
From the side view, I will
be working on the z location
and y location curve of the leg.
So I will hide all the other channel
and focus on those curves.
And while I'm polishing
the motion of the foot,
I'm watching every single frame.
The further you get
from the center of mass
of your character, the
biggest will be the arcs.
So when you are animating legs or hands
on a character,
it's very important to
track what you are doing
and to polish it as much as possible
'cause a sudden gap in your curve
will make the motion of
those parts very broad
or very large.
You will get a big glitch into the arc.
Another thing to remember
is that a falling object
will accelerate before it hits the ground.
So make sure that your spacing
is the biggest before hitting the ground
and when leaving the ground.
And you can convert the contacting frame
with the ground to vector.
It's the best way to avoid
easing in the first step.
Finally, to have a better readability
of the first leg,
what I will do is go in front view
and press Alt + B
and frame off of the character.
It will enable the view clipping mode.
It's like creating a tunnel
and whatever is outside of this tunnel
won't be shown in the 3D viewport.
It's support handy to cut the visibility
of your character in half.
While it's very useful
in modeling for sure,
that's also very useful in animation.
Just press Alt + B again
to clear the clipping view.
I'll advise you to
calculate the motion path
of the foot as soon as possible.
You can see that I have a
very decent arc right away
but I will polish it
using the motion path.
The main thing I will focus on here
is to make sure that the
character is pulling his leg
as high as possible when jumping.
So it will drag in the beginning
and then it will catch up
and even get very close
to its belly.
So as my arcs looks very smooth
and as I'm pretty satisfied
with the motion of the leg,
I will switch to the front view
to work on the x location
curve of the leg.
Here the method is pretty simple.
You want to avoid zigzagging motion.
And when the foot is stuck on the ground,
you may not have any
left and right motion.
So polishing the x curve
is pretty straightforward.
We apply the same rule
as when we are working
on the under curve.
Whenever the leg is contacting the ground,
I will switch the handle type to vector.
The next channel that
inputs the most motion
into the foot then will be the x rotation.
So this is the next curve
I will be working on.
While I was pretty satisfied on the arc
of the leg here,
I've made quite a big mistake.
I've worked the foot animation only
without root motion and that's a mistake.
I advise you to check your animation with
and without root motion
as often as possible
because in the end, what
you will be animating
or seeing into your animation
will be your character
moving with the root motion.
It will be moving forward,
not moving on place like that.
And while the arc of the leg looks cool
without root motion,
when I've enabled the root motion,
it didn't look that great.
It's not going to be a major
issue on the animation here
but I will have to fix it later on.
So that's an issue.
And you will save time if
you switch to root motion
as soon as possible.
Back to our foot x rotation.
The main focus is to
get a smooth transition
while in the air
and to get a pretty fast flopping motion
when leaving the ground.
The foot is pushing the body forward.
This is why we have a pretty big change
between frame two and frame four
and I'm polishing the
curve between frame one
and frame two so that
the foot doesn't clip
with the ground,
which is represented by the y-axis here.
One of my main concern
was to choose whether I
would input foot roll or not.
And I've decided to go ahead with it.
That's why our character is
landing on the ball of the foot
and then it switches to
a flat foot position.
You can think of it as a foot roll
from the heel to the toes
but on digit grad, like
cat, dogs or squirrel,
the heel is currently
not touching the ground.
So I'm not here to give
you an anatomic course
but it's important to take
this into consideration
because you will intuitively
translate human motion
onto animal motion.
While it can work or be a stylized choice,
it's important again to watch reference
of animal and understand the behavior
of the different part of their body,
depending on their function or purpose.
Here I'm polishing the x
and y rotation of the foot.
The idea is to make the
foot point a little inward
when it's leaving the ground
and point a little outward
when it's going to contact the ground.
One last thing, on the contact frame,
I want the foot to contact
with the ground slightly
with its outer edge.
This is a very subtle motion you will find
in the foot motion of a human being
during a walk cycle.
The foot has a slight
tilt from left to right,
while pushing on the ground.
So even if it's very subtle,
it's better to input this information
in the foot motion of
our squirrel character.
When I got onto polishing
the other back leg,
finally made the clearer move
to check my animation
with the root motion on
as I told you in the
beginning of this video.
And this is where I
spotted the weird curvature
of my arc for the left leg.
You can see some kind of vertical easing
on the motion path.
We had to get back onto the
polishing of the left leg.
Fix this issue.
And that's perfectly normal
that you have to refine
every single controller
each time you are polishing one of them.
As I told before, since
everything is connected,
fixing a bug somewhere
or a bad motion somewhere
may modify the perception
you have of the other part
and you will have to polish it again.
As every art form, an
animation is never finished.
It's up to you and your schedule
to call it done.
The second important point
is to watch the silhouette
of your character.
I don't think there is a
shortcut in Blender to do so
but you can go to the shading option,
switch to flat and then object.
This way, your character will
turn into a single solid color
that will help reading its silhouette.
The idea is to avoid some part of the body
to overlap and make the
silhouette harder to understand.
For example, here if I overlay both feet,
one one top of each other,
the silhouette is harder to understand.
While if I separate them,
I can see there are two feet.
So this is not something you will be able
to manage all the time
because sometimes, the point of view
makes your body part overlapping
but just keep it in mind.
That's also why the position of the heel
is slightly offset so that
we can see both heels tip.
On the final polishing stage,
I have tweaked the
position of the pull target
to make sure that the legs
were not pointing outward too much.
This is not really about
polishing any motion here.
It's mostly about fixing bugs
from the inverse kinematic.
But I'm moving the controller in space
whenever I feel the need,
then playing with its curve.
So I will lead you there
with a little time lapse
where I will be polishing both back legs
and I'll see you a little
later in this video
to polish the front legs.
(tranquil music)
For the front leg, I didn't
make the same mistake
as for the back leg
and mainly worked with root motion.
The process is basically the
same as for the back leg,
so I will just give you the two key points
that you have to figure
out for this motion.
The front legs are the
first to get in contact
with the ground when your
character is landing.
While it's important to make them drag
in the beginning of the jump,
when the character is
then losing altitude,
it's important to show that
the squirrel is in control.
So you may not swing the
arms all the way around.
Since we want to show that our character
is in control of its run cycle,
then he will aim at the
target point he will land on
with his arms.
If we look at this reference
where the character is shaking his arms
and legs all the way around,
we clearly understand
that he's not in control
of the situation.
Again, you have ask yourself
how to move the legs
but also why you will move
them in a certain way.
Again, animation is
like any other art form.
If you want to make it believable,
it has to make sense.
From the timing, the
behavior of our character
is mainly based on its weight,
its agility, et cetera
but as we go along in this course,
we will try to ask also ourself
how does my character feel?
And how can we translate those emotion
through motion, through animation?
So keep this in mind whenever
you are animating something.
The other thing here I want to avoid
is to have the legs or
front arm over extending.
This current rig is stretchable
but it doesn't look that
good on this character.
And also, even if the
animation is a bit stylized,
I'd like to keep it on the
realistic side of things.
I advise you to try to keep
this animation grounded,
at least for this chapter
because later on,
when we will be working
on humanoid character,
we will push the style a little further.
Realistic animation is
a very hard exercise
because it's about very subtle motion.
Here I have a couple of frame
where the character has
his front foot contacting
with the ground.
I've placed the 3D cursor as a guide
by Shift + right clicking
and tweaking the y location curve,
I will make sure that the
foot is on the same position
on both contacting frame.
Then I will duplicate the
last frame on the first one
so that both the first and
last frame of the cycle
are the same as usual.
So here you have the key component
to polish the front legs.
Avoid overextending limb,
avoid unnecessary and
goofy motion of the limbs,
aim at the landing point.
Make sure that the feet stays in place
whenever there are
contacting with the ground
and don't forget to check the silhouette
whenever you are working
on both front legs.
I will leave you there
with a little time lapse
of me finishing this polish
and I'll see you in the next video
where we are going to polish
the tail of our character.
(tranquil music)