- [Instructor] In this video,
we will polish the moment our character
is making his head turn and smell the air.
He's sniffing the air.
For this one, the body controller
motion is quite subtle,
because in the end our character
is not really changing stance.
He's rotating a bit and raising a bit.
So as usual, I'm trying to make a nice arc
when I'm doing this kind of motion.
This time, the arc is
more subtle than usual
because the motion is subtle.
As the character is shifting to its left
and rotating to its left,
I'm first slightly lowering the whole body
and then raising it.
It will create this arc.
This lower stance can be used
as some kind of anticipation.
One thing I should have
done and you should do
is that just before the
character smells the air
as he push his body a little upper
you could add a micro anticipation
on frame 60 for example,
just lowering the body attached
before raising it even more.
This is something I've explained before
when we have done the walk cycle
something I like to update
early on or polish early on
are the contacting controllers.
So as our character's shifting
his weight onto his left
I want to move his foot controller too.
As the body was polished,
I have reworked the
spacing of the footstep
making it a little faster
and then I've changed it's timing
so that it starts just after
the body start rotating
but it lands before the
body hit it's extreme pose.
Motion-wise it's pretty
simple for the location.
The X and Y axis are using vector handles
so is that I have a linear interpolation.
As for the other foot contact
animation we have done before
for the Z location,
the contacting frame 49 and 53
are using vector handles
and on frame 51 I've created
a slight bump on the curve.
Keep it subtle, don't
forget that we are lazy
and we won't be raising
the foot that much.
What will really improve this footstep
is the rotation in the foot,
this is very important.
It's a very subtle motion
I don't say that I'm doing it perfectly
but what I'm sure is
that animators will look
at these kind of details.
When the foot raise it's dragging
so the outer part of the
foot is pointing down.
Then it's raising so
that the ball of the foot
is facing the ground.
On the contact frame the
foot is still rotated
and on the next frame,
I will make the foot flat
so that I have this slap
motion on the ground.
From the side view,
it's even more obvious the foot's raised,
the tip of the foot is dragging.
Then just before the contact frame
the tip of the foot is raising
on the contact post the tip
of the foot is still raised
and on the next post it's flattened
to get the snap effect on the ground.
The chest motion is here to
support the head rotation.
The head is leading the animation
meaning that the chest
will be slightly delayed
compared to the head.
In the end they arrived
almost at the same time
on their extreme pose.
The little extra information
regarding the chest controller
is that I've been using the location
to emphasize the smelling motion.
I've used it to pull the character up
and then I've added a
slight bump on the curve
to create the smelling motion.
It adds an extra up and
down motion to the chest
which is connected to the head
and the head will be rotating
or moving this up-and-down motion
that translate our
character smelling the air.
As usual, when I'm
polishing the head rotation
I'm tracking the motion path of the nose.
To create the smelling motion
I've just added a couple of
bump on the X rotation curve
of the head controller.
Keep it subtle, you don't
need the head to nod that much
and test different spacing.
In my case, having the
first bump on frame 66
and the second on frame
73 was the good call.
After I finished polishing
the head rotation,
I've added a bit of
extra motion on the nose
playing with its Y curve.
The idea wasn't to make the nose dragging
but instead moving forward and inward
so that we can feel the
breathing of our character
while he's smelling the air.
This is why the Y curve was
working great for this one.
You can pause the nose by hand
if you're not comfortable with the curve
and try different timing.
Another detail I wanted
to add on top of this
are the eyes slightly closing
while our character is smelling the air.
That's a pretty common
thing when you are focusing
on when you are smelling something good,
you tend to close your eyes
to focus on the sense that is
used to focus on your smell.
There's only the Z curve that
controlled the eyeopening
so editing this curve is very simple.
The ears are also pretty important
to support this specific animation.
If you watch the spacing
between the head rotation
tracking the eyes and the ear rotation,
we can see that the
spacing is more important
on the left ear
and this is because I wanted
the ear to lead the animation.
The character rotate the
ears towards his next move
because the ears communicate
his center of attention
and as he's going to smell the air,
the ears, the eyes, everything is pointing
in the same direction
because he's focusing on smelling the air
in this very direction.
For this part of the animation
I've also softened the hips rotation.
So they are still there.
There is still a little twisting
as the character is pulling his left leg
toward the contact point.
This is why I spent a lot of time
on the Z quaternions rotation curve.
Between frame 52 and 56
the leg is getting pulled and on frame 58,
the pose settle.
So we can see the curve
changing direction.
It's getting down between frame 52 and 55,
and after that it's getting
up ever so slightly.
The next thing I have polished
on this segment of the
animation were the arms.
Since they are not
contacting with anything
try to draw nice arcs
with your arm motion.
The second thing we have pointed out
during the blocking
stage was using the arm
as a counterweight to keep
our character balanced.
So as the body is raising
for the smelling segment of the animation,
the right arm is dropping.
It lowers the center of
gravity of our character
and it's also a nice contrast
with the left arm that is raised.
In the time-lapse you will
also see me a bit fighting
with the right tail board character
because there was a bit of intersection
and wobbling in the right arm.
This is the kind of problem and limitation
you can get when using inverse kinematic
without a pole target
as we are for the legs.
There is a little technique
to fix it using constraint
but this is something that we
will see in the next chapter
where I will introduce
you to space switching.
On the time being I'm a bit
fighting with the curve,
that's not a big deal, honestly.
And if you have the same kind of problem
just try to fix it but don't
waste too much time on to it.
Regarding the time motion, there
are two things to consider.
The little wiping animation a bit nervous,
again, to translate the
character of the squirrel,
the root of the tail
doesn't move that much,
there is just the middle and
mostly the tip of the tail
that are moving.
Again, this is not a big motion
as during the run cycle or
to recover from the jump.
It's just a little something
to give personality to our character
and to transition into the next pose,
which is very important.
If we watch the silhouette
of our character
we can clearly see
that he seems to be slightly
bending or leaning forward.
This is the pose where
he's smelling the air
surrounding him.
So he's trying to reach as
high and as far as possible.
And it seems that he's
going to fall forward.
So in this case,
the final pose of the
time is very important
because it serves as a counterweight.
So those are all the
details you need to look for
when you are going to polish
the segment of the animation.