- [Instructor] Since it's
a pretty complex animation,
we do need more poses
in the blocking stage
so let's add some in-betweens.
The first pose I've been
working on was the pushing pose,
the character is getting
almost fully extended
the front legs or hands are
just about to leave the trunk,
the back legs are not extended yet,
pressing Shift S I've snapped the cursor
to the leg of my character,
now I can push the foot backward
and then move to root bone forward
or upward since our
character is rotated to match
the previous position of the foot
so that we don't have this
sliding contact effect.
The trick here is that I input the value
of the movement with the keyboard
pressing G then Z to move
along the global Z axis
and press 0.08 to move
by eight centimeters,
this way, I do know how
much I have moved the foot
and I will offset the root bone,
but also the hands of the
character by the same value
this way I'm sure that I will
have corresponding motion
for all the parts of the characters.
It's a good way to do this
because it's very accurate
but it's also a bad way
because it's a very constraint
way to do this thing,
this is why I advised you
not to use any root motion
for the blocking of this
animation in the previous video
but to show doing so that's not bad
because this is something
we will have to do later on,
so it gives us a base to work on,
doing it the hard way
here might not be the most
intuitive way to do it
that's what I'm meaning
but I will have a solid base
to go into polishing them.
Dispose is the one where the head
has the biggest spacing compared
to the previous pose,
it's one of the first pose
where the character is pushing forward,
so I will extend the neck of
the character quite a bit,
it feels like the front
legs are a bit too extended
and on the reference we can see
that the front legs are not
touching the trunk anymore
so I will put them into a pose
where they just took off the tree trunk.
Since this in-between
is starting to define
the emotion of the character
because we have the extreme
poses and this is an in-between
so it makes the transition
between those two poses,
this is why I'm playing the animation
of curbing through the frames a lot
beyond matching the reference pose
I'm trying to feel the
emotion of the character.
Try to fix the orientation of the arms
I'm facing some kind of
issues with the rings,
some limitations, this is pretty usual
with this kind of inverse
kinematic controllers
so I reset the rotation
and instead I'm using
those tweaker controllers
to give a better shape to the arms,
so I advise you to deal
with the shape of the arms
using those controller
for this specific animation.
The next critical pose for me is the one
whenever the character is contacting
with the surface of the tree trunk,
this contact frame is occurring
between frame 15 and 20
so I will set it up from 18
for example, it really doesn't
matter from the time being
we are just breeding the different poses
and then at the end of the video
we will do a rapid timing paths.
The first thing I do to switch
to this new pose is to move the root bone
so I've been trying to move
it using the same technique
as for the previous pose
meaning that I'm moving the root bone
entering a proper value with the keyboard,
but since my character has no
contact with the tree trunk
it doesn't really matter if
shall not really accurate
with the position of the root bone
right now, there won't be
that much of the problem
we will be able to
offset a bit the position
of the root bone during
the polishing stage.
What's important here is that
since there is no contacting frame,
no part of the character contacting
with the tree trunk or with the ground
for example, the fact
that the root bone motion
is not perfect, doesn't matter,
we won't have any sliding foot effect here
because there is no
contact with the ground.
So in the end, because of this foot motion
and the squeal to have
everything perfectly aligned
and to try, I spent
most of the time trying
to figure out a way to
position the hands properly
while it wasn't important,
the only thing important is
to make sure that the position
of the hands are correct
compared to frame 20
and even if there is a bit of a challenge
a bit of a difference this is something
we'll be able to fix when we are polishing
by moving the curve or
duplicating the curves,
what's matter here is really
the pose of the character,
so the front legs are
almost fully extended,
the back legs are catching up pointing
toward their landing pose.
And finally, we have
still the hip sat down
dragging a bit, but they
are slowly catching up,
while the chest and head
are getting very close
to their final pose or to
the pose we have on frame 20,
so you can see on the reference
that the curvature of the body
of our character is slowly
getting back into it's S shape.
The next pose is more of a breakdown
that in in-between onto this breakdown
between frame zero and
five, because on frame five
our character ends a normal
angle contacting the tree trunk
with all my read controller selected,
I'm pressing a Shift E,
then when I moved the mouse left to right
I changed the value of the breakdown,
I will set it to 50%,
then they will left click to confirm
this way blender has
automatically interpolated
all the controller of my character by 50%
between frame zero and frame five,
now I don't want to move
the hand controllers,
so I go back on frame zero
select one of the hand controller
press Shift S snap the cursor to it,
then I go back onto frame
two my break down pose
and press Shift S selection to cursor
the hand will be snapped
on to the same position
as on frame zero,
I will repeat the process for
the other hand and this way
my whole character body
and root has moved by 50%,
and I can work on this pose
and the feet position is fixed,
thanks to this little manipulation.
So now I can work on the torso
controller to refine the pose
and offset the different element
because if everything
is interpolated by 50%
I will have a very robotic
motion of my character.
So here, as we have explained before
during the reference analysis
I'm pushing a lot the neck
and chest of my character
while the hips are dragging a bit back,
from there what I did is that I have taken
all the key frame of each pose
and I have set them every two frames,
so one on frame zero one on frame two,
four, six, eight, 10, and 12.
I feel like this cycle
should be 12 frame long
so I'm just kind of distributing
the different posts evenly
for the time being because I'm not working
on the timing of the animation right now
but it does help reading the animation.
The last pose I wanted
to create is the one
where the back legs are
contacting with the tree trunk
as explained why we were
locking the idle animation
you should create a
bring down pose each time
there is a drastic change in
the pose of your character
meaning that here the back feet are abohm
and then they are
contacting with the surface
in this regard, their mechanical function
and the way they move is changing a lot
because when they are floating in the air
you should be looking for arcs
while when they are impacting
with the tree trunk,
you're not looking anymore for arcs
but mostly for a linear interpolation
as the foot is sliding along the surface.
So it's better to add a breakdown
to this pose than trying
to figure this out
during the polishing stage,
this pose was pretty quick to achieve
because we have already depends
on the front legs already
contacting the tree trunks
and the only thing we
had to do is to make sure
that the back legs are
contacting and the hips catch,
I've made a quick timing paths
here, but I will show you
how to get a better timing
paths in the next video.
Lastly, I couldn't help
polishing a bit to tail motion
but honestly, at this stage
it's mostly a waste of time,
don't work the tail for the
time being since it's ending
and following the body, we will work on it
during the polishing stage
once we have finished
the whole motion of the body.
What was a little more
important here is to rotate
around your character,
check out all the poses
and then fix a bit the pole
target to give a better
orientation to the knees and also check
out the elbow tweaker bones,
you can see that my elbows
are pointing in word
and it doesn't look super natural,
so double check each poses
and check that the silhouette
show character, the shape
of the arms of the legs
et cetera, looks good
from every point of view.
In the next video, we will revise
the timing of this animation is still
in step mode before jumping into spline.