This is the final part of the
polishing stage of the idle.
It's gonna be a quick one
because there is not
that much of an action.
In the end, our character is
getting into its anticipation
before jumping into the run
cycle to flee the danger.
You now should know that we
are going to track all the arts
especially the head motion.
For this segment of the animation,
the body controller
will lead the animation.
Then the chest is dragging,
then the head is dragging.
We can really feel that
the head is getting
(indistinct) by the hips
motion of the character.
And since after the idle,
we have a pretty extreme
motion with our run cycle.
The idea was to eat the
extreme pose on frame 104.
And on the next pose, we will push
that extreme compressing our character
to a maximum before it goes
into the jumping action.
Since most of the last
pose were duplicated
from the run cycle,
the handle of the curve might be rotated.
So, I will select them, press
V and switch to auto clump.
Then polishing the body
controller was pretty fast.
I, (indistinct) a bit on
to the rotation curves
so that I get a bit of easing
before reaching the frame 104
which is our extreme pose
that we are going to push on frame 105.
Then I've worked on the chest rotation,
the idea was to make the chest dragging.
So, I've slightly delayed the rotation
by pulling a bit the curves down
toward their previous value.
And as I reach frame 103,
I slightly rotate the curve
so that I get a natural overshoot.
'Cause I'm getting a nice
arc with a nice spacing,
you will see me pushing
the X rotation curve
down on frame 105.
This is where I'm really pushing the pose
to have a very strong anticipation
before the jump forward.
Polishing the head
rotation was pretty simple.
I've made the head dragging
and I got rid of any twisting
or unwanted rotation.
The idea is to get a very clean rotation
toward the extreme pose as our
character is going to flee.
There is no secondary motion in the head
because it's a very fast transition
to the anticipation before the run.
Then I've quickly reworked
the heels animation
to make sure that their timing
was a bit offset compared
to the head timing and
the whole body timing.
The idea is to change the pose of the head
within one or two frames to
get to very snappy rotation,
very snappy motion of the heels.
Then I spent some time
trying to create an eye blink
as the character while
he's rotating his head
but I didn't kept this additional motion.
Because as the eyes are blinking
it creates a slight
glitch into the animation.
And we already have a very fast
motion of the head rotating
but the silhouette of our
character get a drastic change
and it creates a lot
of visual information.
Adding the eye blink on top of this,
make this portion of the
animation very noisy in the end.
The other thing is that, this
black dot that is the eye
of our character, really help
tracking the head motion.
So, it really helps the audience following
the head rotation in this particular case.
So, if you make the eye disappear
while the character is rotating very fast,
it's like, he blinks and
then he's in another pose.
That really doesn't read well.
So in end, I've just slightly squashed
the eyes so that we get
a different head shape
but I've kept the eyes opened.
So, adding secondary motion
will sure bring more
appeal to your animation,
but sometime it will
make sure animation worst
by destroying its readability.
So, be careful with this and if adding
this kind of secondary
motion then looks weird
and you can't identify the
problem on your animation
just get rid of it.
Secondary motion like an eye blink
is here to support the animation.
To make it more readable
or more interesting.
When polishing the hips,
I've just make it drag a bit compared
to the main body controller,
and I've made sure that I
add some kind of big drop
between frame 104 and 105
to again push the pause on frame 105.
This is going to be our micro
anticipation before the jump
so every controller that defines
the silhouette of our character
should be pushed a bit.
The feet steps were very fast.
There is nothing new compared
to the previous polishing stage.
Just make sure that you
have different timing
for the different feet.
And make sure that your
spacing is correct,
avoiding easing whenever the foot is going
to contact with the ground.
This is why I almost
always switch my contacting
location channels to vector.
And then as usual, I
will polish a bit more
the foot motion by
inputting a bit of rotation
to make the tip of the feet
drag compared to their location.
One super important
secondary motion I wanted
to add was the breathing motion.
To create it, you have to
use the chest controller,
and use the X and Z scale channels.
Because the Y scale channel will push
in a way the head forward
while the X and Z scale will
make the chest slightly bigger.
To figure this out, I've
just been moving the curve
up and down and see how
my character behaves.
And once I was happy with it,
I've tried to find the right
spacing for this animation.
After a couple of tests,
I found that using six frame
to make a full breathing cycle,
kind of marched what I wanted
to have for this character.
When you watch the reference, you can see
that the belly of the
character is moving very fast.
And this is very common,
the smaller an animal
the faster we'll be it's breathing.
I haven't created any breathing variation
on this animation because again,
that will take time and
the benefit was pretty low,
but adding the secondary motion
of the breathing was very important
and it really brings
something new to the table.
So, in the end on frame 20
and 26, I've slightly scaled
down the X and Z and on frame
23, I've slightly scaled up.
Then I will get rid of
all the next key frame,
select those three key frame press Shift
to duplicate X constraint on the X axis
and move by six frame on the right.
And then, I've pressed
a Shift+R several time
to repeat the operation.
Just press Shift+R until you have filled
your timeline until a frame 105.
These little secondary action,
the breathing motion really
adds to the animation
and I feel like it
betterly define the kind
of character we are currently animating.
Adding these fast paced
secondary action really
makes our character feeling more alive.
As I finished polishing
this idle animation,
I want to isolate it from the run cycle.
So I will insert a keyframe
on all the channels on
the last frame, 105,
and on the first frame of
this idle, the frame 12.
Then I will select all
the keys on the frame 105,
press the V key and switch
the handle type to free.
I will do the same on frame 20.
This way we can remove the
previous frame and the last frame
without any influence on
frame 12 and frame 105.
From there, we can duplicate our action,
make sure it does a fake user
by clicking the shield icon.
And then we can remove frame 0 to frame 11
and all the key frame after frame 105.
Then select all the keys and offset them
so that the first key
frame starts on frame zero.
And now we have our
cleaned up idle animation
ready to be used later on.