- Let's gets starting with the blocking
of the climbing cycle of
our squirrel character.
For the previous animation,
we will start fresh.
I will duplicate the keying action
rename it off free climbing blocking
and make sure that it does affect chooser
by clicking the little shield icon.
I will select the rig
and instead of protecting
the character vertically in pose mode,
I will rotate it in object mode
so that we can have a
vertical representation
of the character but it
will still be moving forward
whenever we are animating it.
It's also better to
create a tree trunk dummy.
So in object mode, I will press Shift + A
and add a cylinder and I will scale it
in edit mode vertically.
I will make sure that
its silhouette is aligned
with the z-axis so that it's aligned
with the origin of the document.
The initial pose I will
use the squashed pose
of the character in the video reference.
Can use the corresponding then
their file as a reference,
all the picture in this video.
First in object mode, I'm
make sure that my character
is properly aligned with the tree trunk.
I always start the blocking off of pose
by moving the main controller of the body
and trying to find the
contact pose for the feet.
One important thing when
you watch a reference
is to see the position of
the different body feature
compared one to the other.
If we have a look to the back feet,
they're more forward than the hips.
The hips are currently hanging in the void
and the back legs are pulling the body up.
The tail motion on this
animation will be pretty subtle.
So I just place it so
that it's smoothly hanging
and not clipping with the tree truck.
Then I'm working on the
feet and hand position
so that they are contacting
with the tree trunk, why?
You generally aligned the feet
with the running direction.
In the case of this animation,
I've opened the feet and
the hands in a V-shape.
This way, our character
will have a better grab
on the tree trunk.
When they look at my reference,
I would slightly push the hands up.
Imagine you are hanging
on to a wall or a tree,
your arm will mainly be stretched.
The main difference here is
that the character is very light
so he won't be stretching his arm
or his arm won't be as extended
as if he was very heavy.
But this is something
I will have to consider
whenever I'm starting to
polish my character animation
is make sure that we have the feeling,
he's pulling himself up.
Finally as I felt that the
character was a bit too squashed,
I've just pulled a bit the
hips and the chest controller.
And we are done with this first pose.
When it comes to block the second pose,
I advise you to go for one
of the most extreme pose.
Don't try to block the next pose
in the emotion of the character.
The second advice is that you can choose
whether you move the root bone or not.
I've decided to move the root bone
and try to compensate
the position of the feet,
and it was some kind of extra work.
You can animate your character on place
and then during the polishing stage
or during the splaining stage,
we will input some linear motion
of the root bone to fix that.
Important thing here is not
to answer any technical issue,
but really to match the references.
As the second extreme
pose, I've selected the one
where our character is
about to lose contact
with the tree trunk.
The front legs are already not contacting
the tree trunk anymore,
but the front leg are
still in contact with it.
The key feature we have seen that
during the reference analysis,
is that the body is getting
closer to the tree trunk
as the character is pushing the hips,
chest and head get really extended,
the head and chest extend first
and those three body features gets more
or less aligned into a straight pose.
So one important thing too is
that we have to push the pose.
So here I feel like the pose is okay
but not pushed as much as I liked it to.
It's better to push it a little too much
as it's going to be a
very fast-paced animation.
So we need quite of a
striking silhouette change
of our character so that the
animation will read well.
Only to the mistake I've made
and I will need to fix later on,
is that I've used the main body controller
and pushed the character up a lot.
So you can use the body controller
for the left to right up and down motion,
but avoid moving it too
much forward and back
because this is a motion
that will be mostly generated
by the root motion and the
locomotion of the character.
Slightly adjust the hands of my character
and I think we are good
to go for the next pose.
As explained before, I
haven't made my life easier
by choosing to move the root bone.
So what I'm doing here is
that I'm trying to figure out
how much of a distance
the character is moving
during one jump.
So I'm trying to figure out
a point on the tree trunk
or the back of the tree and the head
and hips position of the character.
In the end, I figured that the character
was moving his whole body
and the hips were getting
further away by one head.
So the character is jumping
off it's full body length
plus one head.
Since we are building a cycle,
the first and last pose
should be the same.
So I will duplicate the first
pose and move it on frame 20.
And holding the D key and left clicking,
I will draw some reference point
to measure the position of the head
and then the position of
the hips of the character.
So I move the base of the hips,
one head further than
the position of the head
on the previous pose.
This is not rocket science,
you can push it a little
further if you want
it will make your jumping
motion a little more dynamic.
The next pose I want to work on
is when our character is airborne.
So I just push a bit the root bone up
because our character is
traveling through space.
And then we can start
reworking the silhouette
of our character.
This is the point where the front legs
are fully extended forward,
the body shape of the character
is pretty straightened
but the head and the chest
are slowly catching up
meaning that the distance
between those two
is getting a little smaller
while the hips are really dragging.
When you are posing the legs,
make sure that you look
at it from every angles
and realign the knees with the body.
I also make sure that both the feet
and the ends of the character
are not symmetrical,
It will look a bit boring.
For this motion, I haven't
set any left to right motion
into the spine nor any twisting.
I guess there should be some
but it's pretty hard to
figure out right now,
while in the polishing,
based on the contacting pose
we might be able to input a bit of it.
As our main key poses or
golden poses are now down,
we can go ahead and add some
in-betweens or breakdowns.