- [Instructor] Let's continue
polishing the idle animation
of our character.
We will be focusing on the next portion
of this animation
where our character is
switching to a sitting pose.
Let's have a quick look
to the body motion first.
I will make a little draw-over
using SyncSketch here.
When transitioning on frame 28.
We can see that the body of our character
is moving a little up
in micro-anticipation.
This is an anticipation, very subtle,
that occur on only one frame.
The idea here is not to
input that much of energy
into the movement
but to give a little
contrast to the next move,
and let the audience know
that our character will be sitting.
Thanks to the locally
style of our character,
it's pretty easy to track its motion.
I just want to show you
the design of the arc
when our character is sitting.
But also the spacing.
Our character is
contacting with the ground
but he will slow down.
There will be an ease
into the sitting pose
so that he doesn't hurt his butt.
This arc and spacing
does read on the curve.
On frame 28, I'm creating
the little micro-anticipation
by just pushing the curve a little up.
Then I've created the arc motion,
using the motion path as usual.
And I'm creating the easing out
with our curve flattening in the end
of the motion on frame 36 here.
Once I'm happy with the
main body controller,
I always work on the chest.
So if we track the shoulder
that is directly influenced
by the chest motion,
I've created a dragging motion,
mainly working on the
rotation curve of the chest.
If you compare the
tracking of the blue line
with the red line,
we can see that we get a nice
C shape with the blue line,
and a nice S shape with
the dragging chest.
As we use the tip of the nose
to track the head motion,
you can use the neck controller
to track the chest motion.
Note that I've hidden the limbs.
It makes the readability
of the torso way better.
(screen whooshing)
When working on the head
before I track my arc,
the first thing I've done
was to remove this bump on the z rotation.
It didn't fit the current
motion of the head,
just adding extra noise to the movement.
And it doesn't make sense
that our character shake
his head left to right
when switching to the sitting pose.
Motion wise, the head is
slightly dragging compared
to the torso,
but I haven't input that much rotation
because I want my
character to be in control.
If you input too much up and
down rotation to the head,
it will feel a bit weird
as if the head was very heavy.
So we can see that the arc of the head
is very close to the arc
made by the torso controller.
Here we can see the result
with the body controller,
chest and head polished.
I did work on the ears and the nose
as in the previous video,
working with the straighter head method,
meaning that I'm
animating quite on the fly
as the animation goes,
inputting a very, very subtle
follow-through animation
to the ears.
And then I did the same
with the tip of the nose.
Since the sitting motion is pretty slow,
pretty subtle, pretty light, whatever,
your follow-through animation
should be very subtle too.
So it's just an extra motion
that will give a bit more
life to your character.
If you're not comfortable with this,
it's better not to do
it than overdoing it.
Before the head turn,
I like to add an eye blink.
I oftenly use eye blink
whenever the character is
changing his head stance,
like a big head turn in our case,
but also if our character is surprised
and push his head up very quickly,
I like to use the eyes to
support this animation.
I'm doing the same eye
motion on both eyes,
and the idea is to have a slight ease in
and a slight ease out.
Shape wise, the eye is fully open.
Then it's closing a bit on the next frame.
On the third frame, it's totally closed.
And then when reopening,
it will open just a bit
and then on the next
frame, it's fully opened.
(screen whooshing)
Next step was to animate the tail.
In this case, the tail is not used
to balance or in reaction to the motion
of the character's body.
The idea was to create a wiping motion
before our character sit.
As if he was relaxing
his tail before sitting.
Think a bit as if you
were going on the beach,
on the sand, and you were
just wiping your towel
before laying onto it.
That's exactly what I
wanted to communicate here.
The final stage was to
polish the hands animation
or front legs animation.
As always, the arcs are
the most important thing
you have to watch for,
so make sure that you draw
nice arcs with the motion path.
And using the rotation,
make the tip of the fingers
or the tip of the foot slightly
dragging in the motion.
You can add a slight overshoot
when you reach the top position.
Beyond those classics,
there are two things
you have to watch for.
First, avoid the twinning.
So we have broken the twinning in the pose
during the blocking,
making the left hand going
higher than the right hand,
but it's better also to break the twinning
in the timing,
meaning that here my right
hand hit its highest point one
or two frame prior than the left hand.
Also, the right hand is
moving slightly faster
than the left hand
because the character is pushing with it.
So there is an impulsion
on the right hand,
while the left hand that
doesn't contact the ground.
It's just continuing the previous motion.
So beware of the spacing
between the right hand
and the left hand.
The next video will be a time lapse
of me polishing this whole
section of the animation.
Just double check the notes
that I have highlighted in this video
into the next one, and I'll
see you in the video after.