- [Instructor] This is the last video
of the run cycle for
our squirrel character,
and it's currently the shortest.
I will just be slightly
reworking the heels
because we need to animate them.
They are important
even if they won't show
that much they appear
so so we need to give them some love.
I'm doing it in two step.
I'm mostly posing the heels
directly in the 3D view port.
I'm not really considering the curves,
I just want a very
slight shaking or wabble
just after the impact frame.
This is why I have a big change
between frame zero and frame two.
And then I'm just dragging them a bit
while our character is moving forward.
I will just have a quick
cleanup on the curve
to make sure that I don't
get any jittering motion,
just something smooth
But with pretty critical
change in the beginning.
The second thing to
consider is the silhouette
of our character.
As we did for the legs
I will try it from a side
view as much as possible
to separate the heels.
This way I'm breaking the tangent
in the shape of their heels.
And we can clearly see
that there are two peaks
on the head of our character.
So that they will make sure that frame 12
and frame one are the same
and then I will have
a quick polishing pass
onto those curves.
I'm just revising a bit
the flow of the curve,
I'm not even really
focusing on what's happening
in the freely huge.
Is just to add the smooth motion
avoid any jitter or stuff like that.
This is not a critical step
and I could have left
the curve as they were.
As usual it's a matter of time and energy
you want to spend onto an animation.
The last thing I will do
is to animate the eyes.
So I won't make the eyes blinking
and you should avoid that on the cycle
because since the cycle is very shot
your character eyes will blinking a lot
and it will really looks weird than CG.
What I've done here is
just to slightly lower
the eye controller on impact.
It's super subtle,
but it's just about having
the whole body connected.
So when the body is impacting the ground
even the eyes or the eyebrow are reacting.
It might not show that much in the end
but you can definitely tell yourself
now that you've been working
this animation from a to Z.
Though you are happy
with the result or not,
proud of it and do another animation
and this is all you will get,
good finish animation
and start another one.