- [Instructor] The last animation we need
to complete our squirrel sequence
is the climbing animation.
I've already explain you
that studying reference was very important
and I found two nice references
for this animation.
And to be honest while studying them,
I was really surprised
on how the squirrel
move while its climbing.
If I was to do it without reference
I would have not done it right for sure.
When studying reference,
it's better to study each part separately.
I will start with the
silhouette of our character.
And I will try to draw
the hips, chest and head.
Whether it's the squirrel character
or a human character.
It's very important
to check out the position
between the hips and chest
and chest and head.
Look at how during the motion,
the hips, chest and head gets aligned
and how the space or the distance
between each features is growing.
The whole body of the character
is stretching toward the next part.
(wind howling)
The next thing you can do
to help you read the
shape of the character,
is draw what we call the line of action.
We will have a deeper look
to what line of action is
in the mastering pose chapter,
but for the time being,
just think of a curve
that connects the head,
the chest and the hips
and that define simplified
version of the curvature
of the body of your character.
This is the most simplified version
of the shape of the body.
That we're going to create.
It's really fascinating
to see how we start with an s-shape
and how it gets stretched
and get back to this s-shape.
(wind howling)
The next step is to track the hands
and the feet of the character.
While the shape is not that surprising,
the thing is that I don't know when
the feet are contacting,
compared to the hands,
and this is why I'm
tracking those elements.
I'm trying to figure when
they take off the trunk
and when they contact again with it.
And we can see that the ends
of the character take off very early on,
while the feet stays in contact.
There is a moment where our character
is totally our bones.
So it means that he's jumping
and then the hand and the feet
have like one frame offset or the contact.
If I quickly do the same
with the second reference
you will find a link to the YouTube video
in the documentation.
The behavior of the character
is pretty close to what we
had on the first reference,
the front legs or hands,
are taking off very early on
while the feet are still
in contact with the trunk.
The main difference
compared to the previous reference
is the timing of the contact pose.
On this reference,
both the ends and the feet
seems to contact at the same time.
(wind howling)
The next thing I wanted to check
was the spacing of the hips
and the spacing of the head.
So I've tried to pound a point on the hips
that allow me to track them.
There was a different of color
in the fur of the character
and to track the head,
I've simply tracked the
eyes of the character
and we can really see
that the head is going very fast
in the beginning and stops,
and then the hips catch up.
So there will be quite of a difference
between the hazing of the hips
and the hazing of the head position.
(wind howling)
The last thing I've
checked was the distance
between the chest of the character
and the tree trunk.
And it's pretty surprising,
as the character is pushing forward,
his chest is getting
closer to the tree trunk.
This isn't something I would have guessed
because when you are
used to make run cycle,
you tend to push your character
away from the ground,
while he's pushing on his leg
to move forward.
While here as the character is pushing on
his legs is getting closer and closer
to the tree trunk.
And as you get in contact
with the tree trunk
is slightly get away from it.
And that's a major difference
compared to a run cycle.
Let's block this animation.