- [Narrator] Anticipation
is a very common rule
or principle of animation.
If we have a look to the throw animation,
the current pose will be the key pose.
A moment where the character
is releasing whatever he is throwing.
In the previous video,
we've seen that anticipation
was a motion built
to gather energy to prepare
for the next motion.
On these pose we can clearly
read the anticipation.
The whole body of the
character is leaning backward
with his arm extended backward
before he swings forward.
Anticipation of two proposes,
the first one is gathering energy
or preparing for the next motion,
but it's also a matter of readability
and strength in the motion.
This example I've
removed the anticipation,
the character is switching
from idle directly
to withdraw motion.
And compared to the animation
with the anticipation
it clearly looks less powerful
and also less readable.
So the anticipation as two proposes
prepares the audience to what is coming
and it adds strength to any motion.
Anticipation is oftenly called antic
and it can append any time in a motion.
On this double a kick,
the anticipation occur at this point.
Character jumps from idle into this pose,
raise whole body is
quashed before the release.
When we think of our bond symbol,
whenever it's quashing
when it hits the ground
we could think of it as being
some sort of anticipation.
Anticipation can be used
for any kind of motion.
It's not necessarily connected
to a strong movement.
On this animation when the
character is turning around
to check what is stuck in his back
he has a slight surprise move
and there is a little
anticipation in his head motion.
His whole body and head goes down
before going up to communicate surprise.
When an anticipation is very fast
we can call it a micro
anticipation or micro antic.
On this combo sequence
there are multiple
anticipation on the character.
I'd like to focus on two of them,
when she's moving forward
to give the first punch
she's slightly leaning and crouching
this way she will have
more power into her punch.
So this certain anticipation
fit the jab punch.
When the character is about
to dodge the mannequin falling
she slightly raises her body on two frames
before diving into this curvy motion.
Those two frame where she's
blinking with her eyes
are the micro anticipation
before she dodges the falling mannequin.
To summarize we have seen that
anticipation can be used to
gather energy before any motion.
It generally make the current
animation look stronger.
It improves the readability
of the animation
by preparing the audience
to the next move.
Anticipation can also be used
to emphasize subtle motion.
We can use very short anticipation
called micro anticipation or micro antic.