- [Instructor] It's time
to finally start polishing
our squirrel idle animation.
It will be kind of similar
as when we have been
polishing the run cycle.
We will start with the
most influential controller
of our character like the
torso or the body controller,
then polish the contact paws, the feet
and then all secondary motion
and follow through like
the tail and the face.
You can choose whether to polish fully
each controller one by one
but when I work on long
sequences like that
I prefer to work by chunk,
like working on the first
two paws and polish them
and then go to the paws three and four
and polish them, et cetera.
I think it's a little more motivating
when you do this by chunk
because doing a long shot like that
and polishing only one controller
will show results only on the long-term
and sometime it can be
hard to stay motivated.
But this is really a
matter of personal choice
so you can work the
whole animation at once
focusing first on the
torso and then the legs,
and then all the secondary motion
or do as I will polishing
each segment of the animation.
(air whooshing)
Just a big warning in here
I selected all the key frame
and switch them to busy.
And this is a mistake since my root motion
is supposed to use a linear interpolation.
This is not a big deal, but
it leads to some mistakes
into my transition between the
run cycle and the idle pose,
so make sure you select
your root controller
and press T and switch it back
to linear before going further.
When I play the animation
it doesn't look that bad when
we switch to spline mode.
And this is because we have
detailed a lot our blocking.
But there is definitely
something weird happening
about the head rotation.
The head of our character is twisting
or flipping the wrong way.
This is a super classic bug
whenever you switch to spline
and we will see how to fix this.
I will explain our rotation behavior
in a more detailed video
in the next chapter.
So before we even start polishing class
we'll go into the graph editor
and we will fix it when you
get this kind of bug, it's 100%
because of the curves as we
are using quaternion rotation
for the neck and head, we
have four rotation channels.
And when I frame my curve
pressing the dot key
on the num pad, we can see this
huge drop on the W channel.
And basically what's happening is Blender
using the shortest path to turn the head.
So instead of rotating
with the nose facing the
front part of the character
it's going back because the
turn is short term this way
and this is the common
problem with quaternions.
To fix this I didn't
really fix the curve first
and then try to match the previous pose.
So I will simply push this W curve up
so that it has a better continuity.
And then I will slightly
tweak the other curve
so that the head is getting
back to its original position.
When you get this kind of curve dropped,
you generally have a whole chunk
of your animations that
is slightly offsetting.
So I will select the Z rotation curve
and push it a little up.
So I'm guessing it's the Z rotation curve
because I have a huge drop
on the Z rotation curve too.
And I can see that
between frame 72 and 95,
the head was offset compared
to what I have done before.
So the trick here is to test each curve
and see which one is
bugging and then offset it.
So that it's betterly aligned
with the previous key frame of this curve.
So I'm just tweaking the
position of the curve.
And I just focus on the pose
of my character on the current key frames.
I am fixing the pose.
I'm not thinking about the animation,
the interpolation of
the curve or whatever.
I'm just kind of reshaping
the poses of my character.
And so if you're happy with
the current poses I have
meaning that they are close
to what I have during the blocking stage.
I can move on and start polishing.
(air whooshing)
So this is something that
is becoming very common
into this course is that
the first thing I do
is work on the torso root of my character.
Because as I've explained before,
this is one of the controller
that will add the most
influence onto the character
and to get a good
visualization of the spacing
and the arcs I've
calculated the motion path.
The first thing I'm working on
is the follow through
animation after the landing.
This is why I've pushed my curve down
in an overshoot just
after the contact pose
our character has a huge speed going down.
So we need to absorb the
impact and then it recovered
and we have our Z location
getting stabilized.
So we have just created some kind
of overshoot and now I will
switch on to the Y curve
and I will do exactly the same
as our character is contacting the ground
while we're moving forward
he's absorbing the inertia.
So I do create a slight overshoot here,
so whatever the trend
form channel you are using
you will see this kind of
shape in my curves very often.
This is really the archetype shape
of a curve for a follow
through or an overshoot.
So it doesn't apply for impacts
where the curve will stop
right on the contact pose.
But as soon as you have a
lot of verticality in a curve
that means that the motion is
very fast or very important.
So as soon as it stop,
you will have a bit of overshoot
or follow through animation,
meaning that there is a bit of inertia
and you can apply it to
scaling rotation and location.
The more you will input
and the longer there
will be, the more weight
and lack of control, you will get,
the tighter and smaller those overshoots,
the lighter or controlled
the motion will look like.
As the main body controller
arc start to look decent,
I can now switch to the
rotation of this controller.
I always apply the same rule.
I start with the X rotation curve
because it's the most
influential into this motion.
So I'm kind of tracking the head,
when I'm rotating the whole body
because this is what will
give you the curvature
of the whole body.
And as I polish, the X rotation,
which shows the most from a profile view,
I also rework the Y location.
So when I'm polishing my curve,
it happened that I offset a lot of them.
This way I'm retiming the animation.
If I feel like the landing
animation is too long,
I can offset a bunch of
key frame by one frame back
and it will happen a little faster.
In front view, I'm
working on the Y rotation
which is the twisting of my character.
When he lands, I twist
toward the left hand
which is the first contacting the ground
and where the character
will put his weight
and when he's raising on the right hand
I'm twisting toward this point too.
With the Z rotation curve,
I'm creating the side-to-side rotation
and what I will do here
as I have a drastic
change in the orientation
of my character is input
a very slight overshoot.
So creating those
overshoot, or follow through
in the curve is not an automatism,
but when you see this kind
of shape in your curve,
meaning that it's going
down or high very fast
and then it stopped creating a plateau.
Just try to add a bit of an overshoot
and see if it does fit your animation.
Again, I can't tell you
this is the way to go
because animation, as any form of art,
is about experimentation
and what we work for this
specific squirrel animation,
won't work for all the squirrel animation
you're going to be doing.
This might not fit the type of style
you are looking for into your animation
whether it's super realistic
or it's super stylized.
But what I want to say here,
is that it's a matter of experience.
I'm giving you the foundation
to create this kind of animation,
and then you have to train your eyes
by animating and animating again.
But this is a cool tip
you should keep in mind
and when you get more experience
you will know when you have to dial
the intensity of your
overshoot, get rid of them
or add even more of them.
On the specific pose I'm
rotating the body controller
and lowering it and also
rotating the chest controller
to avoid the right leg
contacting the ground to be overextended.
This is something you can also fix
in the second time using the
little tweaker controller
the small sphere on the
elbow of the character.
Unless this is something
you are looking for
if you're doing on purpose
having a stretch, lean on
your character, very straight,
will look stiffened,
won't look that natural.
So here I'm not saying
that you can't have this leg
fully stretch as I am here
but I will not all the pose
with the lean totally stretched.
So I've done whatever I could
to fix the shape of the arm.
But if I can, then I'm totally
fine using the tweaker bone
pushing it back a little to
have a slight bend in the arm.
Even if in the end, it's a
little longer than it should be,
we won't see it
and the silhouette will look better.
(air whooshing)
When polishing the head,
the first thing I do is to track the nose.
So here I have a controller
for the nose, so that perfect.
I will calculate the motion path onto it.
As usual, I start with the X rotation
because it's the most
influential controller
on this part of the character.
And the idea here is to
make the head dragging
compared to the rest of the body.
So since the head is further away
from the center of
gravity of our character,
that is represented by
the main body controller,
it will kind of drag, it
will be delayed in its motion
but I want to make this subtle again.
We are working on the very light character
so I don't want its head to
wobble all the way around.
It will drag, but just a touch.
The overshoot must be
as short as possible.
If we were animating a baby, for example,
it would lack of control in its head.
So that will be a great moment
to make it drag a lot more,
build stronger overshoot,
and even made the head wobble.
But this is not the case for our character
is currently very agile.
And I want to show that
he's controlling his landing
and his head is more driven by curiosity
than its own weight.
As soon as the rotation are fixed
and I've done it also on the
chest controller previously,
I work on the location curve of the head.
The idea is to squash
the head inside the body
whenever he is raising very fast.
And then when he get curious
or when he hit its final
poses, I push the head forward.
One very important thing
is that squash and stretch
is not only about scaling something
or really squashing it.
It can be represented by the distance
between two controllers in this case,
the head getting more into the body
but the head doesn't get squashed.
The neck does get squashed a bit
but we currently don't
really see a deformation
but the silhouette of our
character overall get shortened.
So it gets squashed a bit.
So here you can see that
I'm playing in the plane
and throbbing through my timeline,
playing with the Y and Z location curve,
just to get this slight head bop
when it comes to its extreme pose,
creating the slight shake of the head
using the location
instead of the rotation,
as we explained before,
won't translate a lack of control
because our character eyes are stable.
He's looking at a point in space.
While if we were doing this
overshoot with the rotation
the eye will be kind of jiggling
in the space, in the screen space,
on what we are seeing in our animation.
And it will then look like
our character is controlling
what he's doing.
As I'm getting close to
having the head polished,
look at how I slightly move
this point on the curve.
So I don't want to get a
perfect plateau of the curve.
I want to keep very subtle movement
that we call moving holds.
(air whooshing)
As I'm pretty happy with my head motion,
I will now be working on
the nose of the character.
The idea here is to
create a secondary motion.
So the nose will simply be dragging a bit
while our character is raising the head.
If we watch the motion path
from frame 14 to frame 17
we can see that we have a lot spacing
meaning that the head is moving fast.
So this is where the nose of our character
will be dragging the most.
And it does show onto the curve here.
So I'm not using the graphing
tool to control the nose.
I am moving it directly into space.
And then I may use the graph editor
just to slightly polish
the position of the nose.
On frame 19, I've created
a little bump in the curve
so that we have some kind of
bouncing motion of the nose
as our character reaches its
highest point with the head
all those little element give
texture to our animation,
small details and I will be
doing the same with the eyes.
I won't be animating the night blink
but then we'll very
slightly close the eyes,
our character is raising his head.
All of these little details
are like squash and stretch.
They are supporting the animation.
So I haven't been using the
squash and stretch controller
on top of the head of the character
because it doesn't really fit
what I wanted for this animation,
but using the eyes and the tip of the nose
and slightly dragging them
backward kind of input
this squash and stretch
feeling of the motion.
I will proceed the same with the ears.
I will make them drag whenever
there is a fast motion
and I will create a slight overshoot
or jiggling of the heels.
Very subtle whenever there
is a stop into the motion.
So I've been animating the nose,
the ears and the eyes using
the straight-ahead method.
And it's ideal for this
kind of secondary motion
where you can't really predict
where the heels are going to be rotating,
where the nose is going to be,
while you have all the other
controllers to polish first.
This is the kind of motion
that is really hard to block
or to predict.
This is a technique that I use a lot
whenever I'm animating
fingers, for example,
I will shape the end
ring, the blocking stage
but I won't necessarily
put a lot of detail
during the breakdowns and stuff like that.
Since a lot of things can
happen in the animation
of the eyes, the fingers, the ears,
the ponytail, whatever,
all those secondary
elements of a character,
I oftenly animate them using
the straight ahead method
meaning that I've blocked my
character, or least most of it.
And then on top of this, I will
add those additional motion
or additional animation
that are currently following the broad
and main animation of your character.
And you've probably,
haven't seen me working
on each curve of those controllers
and that's perfectly fine.
At some point you don't
need to polish each curve.
You can simply watch the
animation and watch the spacing
in the 3D viewport and
see if it does work.
Curved editing is super important
but it's not mandatory
for every controllers.
So I rapidly polish the hips
because it was mainly compensating
the motion of the character
or the movement of the character.
And I can now switch my attention
to the feet of the character.
(air whooshing)
I tend to be kind of
lazy whenever I'm working
on the feet of character.
And that's a very big mistake.
So this is one of the thing
I'm trying to improve in my animation.
Feet tend to have a lot of motion
and a lot of beginner tend to
keep them still on the ground.
So you should avoid it.
Whenever you feel like your
character is losing balance
maybe offset a bit the foot
and create some kind of very small step.
One of the very important
thing regarding walks
and whatever kind of steps you are doing,
is that any character,
whether it's an animal
or a human being will try to put as less
energy into it as possible,
meaning that you will raise
your leg as less as possible.
When we see the original motion path
shown on the screen right now,
we can see that I had
the very eye position
of the foot on frame 14.
This is why I edited the Z curve
of the location of the foot.
And when I update,
you can see that now the
curve is looking a bit better.
The forward spacing is a little weird
because I have a big
acceleration on the Y curve
and then it slowed down.
So I'm kind of flattening
them with the Y curve
and also lowering the foot
just before the contact pose.
When the foot was moving forward,
I edited the rotation of the curve
so that it just drags a bit backward.
And then when it's
contacting on the ground,
I will slightly raise it to have this kind
of slap motion only on one frame.
That's perfectly fine,
but we will feel this
is a very important tip
that will make your animation
looks a little better.
Whenever you are doing a step
whether for a whole cycle
or an animation like that,
you should avoid flat curve
on the rotation channels
during the contact pose on frame 16.
Having it flat on the next
frame is totally fine.
There is always a bit of
control of foot slapping
on one or two frame, and
then the curve get flat.
So as this first step is polished,
I can work on the elbow
joint of my character
as the front leg get over extended.
It seems to be bending the wrong way,
so I will just frame by
frame, push a bit back
this tweaker your controller,
just to get a slight bending.
I don't need to care about the curve here,
I'm just caring about the
shape of my character.
(air whooshing)
All right, let's move
on the left front leg
or left hand if you will.
The first thing I will do as usual
is calculate the path of this hand
and it has really become an automatism
for me to use the motion
path in production.
With it, I can see right away
that the motion of the
foot is not correct.
The arc as in it's shape
where I'd like it to have
more of a C-shape forward.
I'd like to create a foot roll motion
on the next frame from
the tip of the foot.
So from the side view,
I shift right click on
to the tip of the foot.
Then I will switch the pivot point
to be using the 3D cursor.
And I will rotate the foot forward.
Since this is a pose I would spend time
to get right, using the graph editor.
It's better to pose it
directly in the 3D view.
So is that Blender will
write the curves for me.
And then I just need to polish
using this in-between curve
we've just created.
From there, I have enough information
to start polishing the curve
working first on the Z and Y location,
here I'm building a slight
overshoot on the Y axis
so that the character will
push his hand forward.
And then the back as it
reaches the highest point
and they will update my motion path to see
if my arch is looking good.
And then I will slightly tweak
the plateau shape of the Y and Z curve
to avoid having a pure holding here.
I want to add a slight moving hold
so that the hand feels
connected to the body
that is still moving.
The left-to-right motion of the
front foot is pretty subtle.
So I will just smooth out the curve
and input a bit of an
overshoot on frame 20
and a bit up jiggle on frame 25.
So when I polish to location
channel, for example,
I always double check my animation
through different angles.
I also play the hold section.
I'm polishing to make sure
that everything looks
connected and relevant.
From there, I can work on the rotation.
So why the rotation is the
main motion of this front leg
on this part on the animation,
polishing the rotation of
the front foot or the hand
of the character will
really improve the motion.
So I'm just mainly working on the X
but only on rotation first,
adding a bit of dragging.
Then I work on the Y and
Z pattern on rotation
just to add a bit of twisting
and a bit of dragging
on the left and right motion of the hand.
And the here again,
I will bend a slight
overshoot on the curve.
So you can see that curve
wise in the graph editor
you will often get the same kind of shape
the same curve behavior.
So don't be afraid by the graph editor
this is something you will
get used to very fast,
if you practice.
(air whooshing)
Polishing the tail was
pretty straightforward
as it is mostly a follow
through animation.
So I do believe you now understand
that I always work with the channel
that input the most motion.
This is why I stopped
with the X rotation curve.
So this is a pretty different behavior
compared with the run cycle
or the gym cycle we've made before.
Here, I want faster whipping motion,
meaning that the motion of the tail
is not supporting the
movement of the character.
It's not drawing the shape
and the path of the
character through space.
I'm using the tail here with
fast and snapping motion
to show the attitude of the character.
When we watched the reference,
we can see that the tail move very quickly
and then just stop.
So I want those the little wavey
motion to happen very fast.
On the first contact,
the motion of the tail
is here to balance the character.
But as soon as he stop,
the tail motion will be mostly
used to show the character
the emotion of our character
whether he's happy, curious, or whatever.
And having those rapid change
in the shape of the tail
really translate the fast pace
of the metabolism of small
mammals, like the squirrel,
the mouse, et cetera.
If you think of the tail
of a cow or an elephant
it can move quickly, but
it won't stop instantly.
There will be inertia.
There will be follow through animation.
While on this character,
the follow through might be like
on two or three frame maximum
and you just freezing the hair.
So I'm repeating the same
concept again and again
but all of those follow through animation
can translate the weight of your character
or the stiffness.
Here, for example, while
the tail is very flexible
at some point it's full of muscle
and our character can
kind of hold it in place.
Like whip it's tail and it stop it.
And I think this is a very specific motion
of the squirrel tail that
will make it more believable
or at least that will input
this squirrel-like motion
to our digital character.
On those fast-paced motion,
It's pretty hard to get a nice tail shape.
And this is why on this specific part
I'm almost animating on the ones.
It means that I have a key
frame on almost each frame.
This is what animating on ones means,
is that you will have a different pose
or different key frame on
each frame of your animation.
When animating digitally,
we kind of always animate on ones
meaning that our character
has a different pose on each frame
but when animating traditionally
or making 2D drawings
it happened sometime that you
will keep the same drawing
on one, two or three frames.
In this case, you will be
animating on two or on three.
So it's not correct to say
that I'm animating on ones
because I'm putting a
key frame on each frame
but that's kind of a way of talking
or saying that at some point,
you might need to detail
your animation on ones
and insert a key frame on every frame.
And for each of those poses,
especially on action motion
or on very fast motion
like the tail motion of your character.
In the end of polishing the
segment of the animation
I've been working with the
tweaker bone of the back leg
to keep the back leg
slightly bent the right way,
slightly bent forward.
That was kind of a long video
with a lot of information.
I will keep the next one
as short as possible.