- [Pierre] One thing
I'd like to do early on
is to determine the
tempo of the animation.
I'm still using blender
default frame rate,
which is 24 frames per second.
And my ultimate method
to figure out the rhythm
it's to do noise with my
mouth. (mimics bouncing)
So we can argue this is ridiculous or not,
but if you've ever animated before,
I'm sure you've done this also.
And this is currently a very good method
because animation is about rhythm.
So don't hesitate to sing your animation
or to make noise with your mouth
because you will input
natural tempo that fits you,
that is appealing to you.
And when I was doing those
stupid bouncing noise,
I was almost into a perfect
two time per second.
So don't hesitate to record
yourself or do whatever you need
to be able to make the sound
and measure the tempo of it.
So this scientific method
pushed me to set my
animation loop to 12 frames.
So I've set the error
extreme on frame six.
As we are doing a cycle,
our character will move
forward at a constant speed.
So to help us figuring the
position of the root bone,
I can select all its key frame,
press T and switch them to linear.
This is not something mandatory.
If you prefer to go ahead
and move the root bone by eye
and figure out the spacing,
that's perfectly fine,
but it will help us
figuring the foot position
on this first breakdown
that I will set on frame one
and it will be the pushing pose.
Going back and forth
I'm trying to match the
position of the back feet
on frame zero and frame one.
But again, don't worry
if it's not perfect,
because when we will
be polishing the curve,
there are methods to make it match.
Here, the important thing is
to focus on the silhouette
of your character and the
goal of this position.
So I'm currently adjusting
the edge rotation,
but before I was adjusting
the main torso controller.
The idea is to make these torso controller
pointing toward the target,
the target being the
highest point in the air.
So most of the power of the jump
is due to the pushing of the back legs.
So the front legs will be
dragging toward the initial point,
the point where they come from.
And they will drag or
point toward this position,
both in their location and rotation,
that's why I'm rotating
the hands backwards.
I will try to shape a
bit the tail, but again,
I won't put that much in the
energy into it right now.
I will mainly work on the tail
during the polishing stage.
I will also try to break a bit
the position of the back feet
by rotating one of them a little bit.
Again, the idea is to break the twinning.
One of the foot is leaving the ground
slightly after the other.
So there will be a bit of back
and forth with the back legs.
Because even if I want to avoid twinning,
I need to keep them tight timing wise
because they are influencing the bounce.
They are giving power.
Now I'm comparing my new
pose with the next one.
And I see that I need to revise
the orientation of the torso
because my character was diving
or pushing too much forward,
not high enough.
Then I will slightly lean the head forward
because if you watch the reference,
the head is pretty stable.
So we will give it a bit
of overlapping motion,
but we will try to keep it stable,
looking at its target point.
While I've started stretching the hips,
I keep the chest pretty squashed
throughout the middle of the torso.
And since the root interpolation
is a bit annoying to me,
I will switch back to
constant interpolation.
From there, I will scrub
a lot into my animation.
I will try to fix a bit
the feet orientation,
especially the front feet
that need to be oriented a
bit inward in the front view.
So that's also a mistake to avoid
when you are animating a
character, especially cycles,
you will tend to animate
them from a side view
because it's more natural for us
to feel the motion this way.
But don't forget to check your character
from the front view,
that's very important.
You should turn around your
character as often as possible.
When animating a character,
it's like sculpting,
we are sculpting the pose.
So you need to rotate around the model.
When sculpting, you spend half of the time
rotating around your character
and watching how it behave.
This is the same with animation.
If you want to create good poses,
you need to check them
through every angles.
At this stage, you can shape
a bit the ears if you want,
that's not a problem.
It will help reading the
silhouette of your character,
but it's a secondary motion
so you don't need to do it right now.
It's a bit like the tail,
this is something that will
be easier to figure out
when we are polishing the animation.
So I'm still struggling a bit
with the position of the back feet.
I've kept one of them flat on the ground
because I feel like it
looks more grounded,
which is the case, for sure.
So (indistinct) let's
jump into the next pose,
the landing pose.
To start to working on the landing pose,
I will duplicate the last pose
so that I have the position of the feet.
This way I know where
they will be landing.
Then I will roughly give the orientation
to the torso controller.
So I will push it up and I will rotate it
toward the landing point
or toward where our character come from.
Beware as I have made a little mistake
that I will fix later on,
but if you called avoid
it, that will help.
Don't forget to move the
root bone a little backward.
It will offset the whole
character a bit backward,
and then you can place the
feet and the torso as you want.
If you're like me and you forget to do it,
don't worry, it's not a big deal.
That won't be a pain to fix afterward.
So the first thing I will do
is to give the right
orientation of the whole body.
I will also pull it back
so that I get a very stretched pose.
The idea is that the front feet
are just about to touch the ground.
So our character is stretching
between the target point
and the previous position
from where it comes from.
As I did before, if I can't feel the pose,
I will press Alt + R and Alt
+ G on the chest controller,
for example, to cancel any
rotation or move I did before.
And I will just sculpt
the pose of the character.
As for the other poses,
you have the reference on the
target pose we want to match
in the lower right corner.
Since I don't have that much
to comment on this part,
I will see you at eight
minute and 50 seconds.
(serene music)
One thing I've input into this pose
and that we need to input
into the other pose while polishing
is this slight twist on the torso.
So since the left front
leg of the character
is the first that will touch the ground,
I slightly twist its chest
toward this left hand.
And a very common rule that we will see
when we will work on humanoid character
is that when the chest or
the shoulders are twisting
or leaning toward the point,
the hips are twisting or leaning
in the opposite direction,
giving a nice curvature
to your character's
spine and balance.
While working on the pose,
I felt that the timing was a bit off
because the change in pose
between frame 11 and 12
was too dramatic.
So I've offset the pose to the frame 10.
This pose was the hardest
to make right so far.
So I'm going back and forth a lot,
I'm modifying the position
of the legs a lot,
I want to avoid twinning.
I'm reworking the torso orientation,
a lot of different stuff.
There are very little chance
that you're able to
match the perfect pose,
which doesn't exist at the first time.
So don't hesitate to come back on it,
don't hesitate to even
modify the previous poses.
And since we are starting
to feel the motion,
it's a good moment to
display the motion path
of the torso controller.
This give us a rough idea
of the motion of the body
and it makes me confident
enough to shape a bit the tail.
But don't worry, you don't
need to do it right now.
Again, we can do it during
the polishing stage.
Nothing special to
comment during this stage,
so I will leave you and see you
at 11 minutes and 38 seconds.
(serene music)
As I told you a little early on,
I forgotten to move the root bone.
So I will move it backward
in the position it should be.
And then I just need to
select the chest controller
and all the foot controller
and move them all together
to fit my previous pose.
Since all those controllers
are child of the root,
moving them together is
like moving the root bone.
And again, I will fight and
fight refining this pose
until I'm satisfied with it.
And as soon as I am,
I will add a last breakdown
or in-between on frame 11
because we can figure the
position of our character
from frame to frame six.
There will be specific error motion,
but we can track the position of the feet,
the position of the torso, and
try to get a smooth motion.
And this is a big strength
of the graph editor
and the fact that we are using a computer
to do the animation.
It's perfect to create
a smooth interpolation
between two poses.
But since we have a big difference of pose
between frame 10 and frame 12,
you can't let the
computer do the guesswork.
We need to build this new
breakdown or in-between ourself.
So this time I won't do the same mistake
of forgetting to move the root bone.
And since it's supposed to
have a linear interpolation,
it's position between
frame 10 and frame 11
should be right in the
middle of those two poses.
And there is a tool that
we haven't used yet,
because I didn't want you to use it
and it's called the Breakdowner.
You can select it with the tool panel
and with any bone or
group of bones selected,
when you left click and drag,
you will see a breakdown percentage
appearing in the top left
corner of your screen.
It currently gives you
the level of interpolation
you are performing.
So if I left click and drag
or press Shift + E to activate it
and set the interpolation value to 50%,
I'm sure I will be right in the middle.
You can constrain this tool to rotation,
move and scale by pressing G-R-R-S.
You can also concentrate
it to specific axes,
and there are two other tools
under the Breakdowner's menu
that we are going to see later on.
With my root bone position,
I can press I to insert a key
frame for every controllers.
From there, the first thing I will do
is try to match the feet position
so the feet are targeting
the landing position.
It's exactly the same workflow as before.
Then I cancel the rotation and
move on the torso controller
and I rework the pose.
So I did a bit of twist by pressing R,
then Y twice to rotate
on the local y-axis.
And now I will push the root
of the torso toward the ground.
The right leg is the first
to contact the ground
as it is the first one to be
raised when leaving the ground.
So I can have the left arm slightly bent,
and they wouldn't put a lot of squashing,
both in the chest and hips,
by moving them toward the ground.
I also make sure that I rotate the foot
so that the plant is facing the ground.
It's like the food are dragging
so the tip of the food will later
than the base of the foot or the heel.
That's also a form of follow through.
If you animate a hand or a foot moving,
you want the fingers of
the toes to be dragging
to have an overlapping motion.
One important thing I've
learned through my classes
is that says is that you
should track your motion
as soon as possible.
This is why I've calculated
the motion path for the feet,
so that they can see their
trajectory and timing.
And this will be the perfect
tool to double-check ox.
We will talk more in depth
about the ox in the next video.
I will also add a bit
of squashing on the head
by moving it a bit backward.
And to counter this I
will slightly rotate it up
so that our character is
watching towards its next step.
I will also calculate the
motion path of the head bone
and while I'm posing it, I'm
trying to create a smooth curve
between the different
position of the head.
This is the arc of the head.
So try your best here to
get a smooth transition
between the different poses.
But if it's not perfect,
again, don't worry,
we will see that in-depth
during the polishing stage
and by reading the curve,
it will be even easier.
Once I'm done with that,
I can check my animation.
So we really start to have
the feeling of the emotion,
but the problem is that my
character is jumping forward
so I would like to see it looping.
Just uncheck the route
controller so that your character
will be jumping and looping
without moving forward.
Now, as for the bouncing ball,
since frame zero and frame 12 are the same
I will just read the animation
from frame zero to frame 11.
It already looks very good.
But one last thing I'd like to address
is the squashing of the character
on the very first frame.
I think we can push the pose even more.
So I will just push the test
controller a bit backward,
the hips a bit forward,
and the root of the torso a bit lower,
Since we are animating on once here,
meaning that we are creating
a key pose on each frame,
there won't be any specific interpolation.
This is why I use the motion path
to make sure that I have a nice spacing.
With this pose on frame 12 updated.
I'd like to duplicate all
the key frame on frame 12
and move them on frame zero.
But I don't want to
duplicate the root key frame.
So I will lock the root,
press Shift + D with all the
key frames selected on frame 12
and moved them on frame zero.
And that's it.
You've just blocked your
first character run cycle.
It's not something easy so if
you have failed, don't worry,
just restart from the beginning.
I'm here to give you the method,
but it's only through practice
that you will become a good animator.
Don't stress out, watch the video again.
And if you're ready,
I'll see you in the next one
to polish this animation.