In this video, we will start
blocking a new animation.
This is going to be an idle
animation of the squirrel.
But we need our character to transition
from the run cycle into a stop,
do the idle, and then get
back into the run cycle.
At least to make our character
checking the surrounding environment.
And then as it hears some noise
maybe it will go back into the
run cycle to flee the danger.
It is going to be a
very fun idle to animate
and the first step is always
to check out references.
Looking for some specific information.
First one is the rhythm of the character.
You can see how we jumped
from a pose to another
in a very fast motion
and sometimes just stop.
And then it almost stay still.
Those various snappy motion really brings
the fact that our
character is lightweight.
Squirrels use their tails also
to communicate their feelings
and to communicate between them.
So we can use the tail to
communicate surprise or fear,
to our character.
The last thing that really
shines through those reference
is the briefing pattern of the character.
It is really fast paced
and he does show a lot
when the character is
not moving that much.
We'll be blocking five poses.
The first one where our characters stop
and look at the side.
Then it will raise on its back
leg and maybe smell the air.
We will then pull his
attention to the other side.
Then he will turn his head
in a more grounding pose
because he heard something,
transition into a pose
where he will start
running to flee the danger.
Since we are going to
transition from the run cycle
the first thing I will do
is clean the run cycle.
So I will select older
curve and press the Shift+E
and clear the cyclic modifier.
Then I will select the root
bone and I will press Shift+E
and get clear of the linear extrapolation
by choosing constant extrapolation.
Make sure you have all your keys selected
when removing your modifiers
or your character will be
kind of behaving weirdly.
At least it looks pretty fun
but it will be hard to work with that.
So once I'm done, I will
duplicate my run cycle.
So that I have a new action to work with
that I will call idle.
And I will keep the run cycle animation
at the beginning of this new animation.
This will help us creating the transition
between the idle animation
and the run cycle.
We'll have to animate our
character transitioning
from the run cycle to the idle.
But as we did for any
of our animation so far,
I will go on frame 15
and I will stop blocking
the first pose of our idle.
The first thing I do is to
flatten the feet of the character
because they're on the ground
and since you will have
some kind of still pose we
need him to be grounded.
And to make our life a little easier
I will keep the back feet on the ground.
In the same position they had
when he land at the end of the run cycle.
You can do the pose you
want, but, I believe
it will be better for you
to follow what I'm doing
so that you won't be lost
if you're not use to animate that much.
As I block the character
pose I will give you
the key component I'm
looking for when doing so.
I don't want my character
to stay on his four leg
in the straight pose.
If you raise the one of your
leg you will automatically
shift your weight towards the other one.
This way you will keep balance.
And we can clearly see that
on the reference poses.
Our character has turned
to its right side.
His whole chest is slightly shifting
to be right under his front leg.
This way his center of mass
is aligned with the front leg
is aligned with these contact points.
If we were to see our
character from beneath,
we can see that the three contact points
the three legs contacting the
ground are shaping a triangle.
And the center of mass of our character
is more or less centered
with this triangle.
This way our characters looks balanced.
And this is a very important thing
when you are doing these
kind of idle poses.
Since there is no more
inertia like motion forward
as in the run cycle, you
need to make your character
look in balance on each pose.
The other very important
thing to do is to twist
the character to while the contact point.
Looking at the reference again
we can see that the shoulder
are pointing down towards
the contact point.
And as in most cases you want
to create an opposite twist
with the hips.
The cool trick to remember
is to create a V shape,
with the line of the shoulder
and the line of the hips.
We then try to give a nice
curved shape to the tail.
And when I feel like the
pose is looking all right,
I will use the tweak controllers
to fix the shape of the front leg.
On the current pose, the front
leg contacting the ground
is bending forward and
it looks a bit weird.
So I'm using this tweaker
controller to fix it.
Checking the rotation first
and then just moving the
joint a bit backward.
As we did before, during
this blocking stage
I'm absolutely not considering
the timing of the animation.
I'm just setting the key poses
or golden poses every five frame.
I've seen people setting those
key poses, every one frame
and then moving them when they
knew their first timing path.
For the next two poses,
I want my character to
kind of relax and sit.
On the first pose our
character is transitioning
from the previous pose
watching to his right.
And then I want him to watch to his left
so that we have a cool rotation
and the change in the pose.
So, as usual, try to avoid
the twinning in your poses.
Think of the silhouette of your character.
Does it read well?
And think of the balance of your character
and his emotional state.
Is he relaxed, curious,
in danger, stressed?
As I'm building the
very first sitting pose,
I will kind of squash a
bit the character backward.
So I'm watching references from the video
I've linked in the documentation,
to check the curvature
of the body of the character, for example.
So I'm using both rotation
and location of the different controller.
Don't hesitate to move the controllers.
A lot of people, especially
beginners, tend to use
only rotation, especially
for the spine bone
or the arm bone when
using forward kinematic.
And a lot of rig doesn't
allow to move the joint,
using the location channels.
While this behavior can
be physically correct
because you can't really move your bone
you can only rotate them,
animation wise it's not
necessarily relevant.
Because unless you have a
rig that perfectly simulate
the physical behavior of your character,
with the bones, the fat and everything,
you may not get an interesting shape
or a believable shape of
the body of your character
by only rotating the controllers.
Especially with this
kind of fluffy character.
Because you're not currently
animating it's skeleton
you're animating everything
from the skeleton,
the muscles and the bones and the fur.
So as usual, think of the
shape of your character,
think of its silhouette,
and think of what you want to communicate.
Here, I want him to be
chilling on its back leg.
So I'm compressing him a bit.
A reminder, don't forget to set your keys
to constant interpolation,
and don't forget to key
your whole character
to avoid foot sliding and
all this kind of shenanigans.
For the third pose, I
want my character to be
kind of curious to what's
happening in his environment.
So I will turn him the other
side so that we have contrast
between the previous
pose and the current one.
One of the key component of
this next pose is curiosity.
I want the character to be
smelling the air around him,
as if something was
catching his attention.
This is why I will give to
his body a more extended pose.
He's pulling his head
apart to smell the air.
His body is kind of stretched
or pulled by his curiosity.
And since the pose is
slightly bending forward,
I've laid the tail backward
so that the character is balanced.
There is more weight of his
head forward and the tail
is counterbalancing the
weight of the head backward.
From my experience an unbalanced pose
doesn't look right at all.
So, before being appealing,
I feel like a pose must be balanced.
Like, we can feel that the
character is well grounded
and it won't be falling down.
So when creating your pose,
think first of the goal
of your character, the purpose
of the pose, his feeling.
Then, think of the appeal of the pose,
the silhouette, et cetera.
And for any still pose or
pose with very slight motion
where there is not that much inertia,
always think to balance your character.
As I'm getting close to the pose I want,
I can't think to fix the secondary shape
like the elbow orientation,
the knee orientation
and all this kind of stuff.
From there I've made a personal choice.
I'm not sure that squirrel
can really rotate their ears.
Watching the reference, it seems that
there is a slight rotation of the ears.
And watching other video I
can see a bit of rotation,
but I'm not sure how much
they can rotate their ears.
But the ears are a fantastic
feature to communicate emotion,
to communicate curiosity.
Think of the motion of a cat's ears
when they've heard a noise
their ear rotates almost 180 degrees.
They can show also fear,
aggressivity, et cetera.
So I'm perfectly fine
if this motion is wrong
because I'm not here to
reproduce a realistic motion.
I'm here to give life to this
character through emotions.
I feel like, the pose
look believable enough.
Here I'm starting to work on the next pose
and at first I also made a pose
where the character was
staying on his back legs.
But it was way too similar
to the current pose,
so in the end, I've modified this pose.
I wanted the character to feel surprised
by some kind of noise or whatever,
and scared at the same time.
We will jump directly to the next pose
and then we will see how I
reworked the current one.
Since the next pose is the last one
before our character run
again, I have duplicated
all the key frame of the run
cycle and them onto frame 35.
I will also duplicate
the last route motion key
and put it on the first
one of the second cycle.
This way I don't get root
motion on the second cycle.
We will get rid of the
root motion in the end,
but it's important to have
it, for the transition
between the run cycle and
the first pose of the idle.
Here, I'm creating the anticipation pose.
The next video will be a
more in depth explanation
of anticipation, but
basically it's the moment
where the character is compressing himself
to gather energy before jumping
forward into the run cycle.
So I flatten the foot on the ground
so that he's very stable.
I'm pushing the chest
backward and the hips forward
to compress the torso as much as possible.
And I'm also pushing the head inward.
It's like squashing a spring
before releasing to make it jump.
I'm shaping the tail into
a knock because I know
that when he will be jumping
he will whip the tail downward.
So I'm kind of shaping the body
the opposite way it will
react on the next pose.
I'm compressing it a lot
while it will be stretched
When the character is jumping.
As explained before I'm
revising the previous pose
before the anticipation
because I wasn't happy
with him staying on his back
legs while I wanted him to be
kind of scared by some
noise, or something,
just before he decide to run away.
So I want the squirrel to be
well-grounded on his four legs.
Slightly closer to the
ground ready to jump
and with the ears, head and
torso pointing toward the noise.
The tail is counterbalancing the pose
creating a nice curve of the whole body.
Again, I'm making sure that
the character is well-balanced
that's why I moving the right
front leg a bit on the side.
As explained before, as any art form
don't hesitate to try to
improve your animation.
Revise them, change your mind, et cetera.
If you are not convinced
about what you are doing,
then change it.
If you don't feel like you're
communicating anything,
change it.
If it's boring, change it.
But if you can't figure why,
don't hesitate to ask anybody around you.
One of the cool thing
about animation is that
most of the people connect with animation.
And while your mother might not be able
to tell you what you have to
do to improve your animation,
she might point out things
that looks weird to her.
Or what she doesn't like
about your animation.
And then you can make
the choice to modify it,
or it can put you on the way
to improve the animation.
And if you know any professional animator
that can give you
feedback, don't hesitate.
Or put your animation on
forums, that's very important.