- In this video, we will talk
about another principle of animation.
I haven't used the term before,
but we have already used
arcs in our animations
when we have done our
one single animation,
and when we were tracking
the motion of the ball,
we did our best to create
those beautiful curve
in the motion, and those are arcs.
And it does make sense, even for me,
as an arc, in French, is a bow.
But, I'm not sure it will
help for this course.
Let's go ahead.
If you look around, most
of the things that move
move in arcs.
They kind of have a rotation-based motion
and you will barely meet
situation where you want
to animate straight lines
like hydraulics or stuff like that.
If I remove the arcs from
our one single animation,
you can see that we absolutely
don't get the same results,
the same feeling.
It doesn't look natural at all.
Let's have a look at a
little more complex animation
and let's point out few
arcs in this animation.
A common mistake for
beginners is to forget
to input an arc in the head rotation.
But in most cases, it will
bring a bit more personality
if you do it this way.
Next step, if I track the hand,
you can clearly see there is
a big arc on the left hand
and the right hand.
On this new head turn,
look at how the arc
support the feeling of fear
of our character not
understanding what happened
and his back is pushing his head down
between his shoulder while rotating.
On the next move, too,
arc is very important
and well-defined.
And whatever part of the
character I am tracking,
I will find those arcs,
whether it's the motion of the pelvis,
the motion of the hands,
the motion of the head, the
feet, whatever you want.
So arcs are almost everywhere
and it's very important
to track them properly.
That's why we really need
to use the motion path tool of
Blender as often as possible.
To summarize, we have seen
that most motion are done
in arcs.
You should avoid the
straight interpolation
unless it is intentional.
You should use the motion
path tool of Blender
as often as possible.
Track your arcs!