- I will show you a quick method
to double-check your timing.
First we will check with root motion
and then without root motion.
I've already made a quick timing pass
in the previous video
without explaining it,
because it wasn't very good.
The idea was just to check
the follow of the different poses
but you don't need to
work on timing for this.
Now is the timing path
before I switch to spline.
So to check it,
since I have root motion
I've kept my root activated,
and I will now simply use
my quick favorite menu
to calculate the motion
path of the root bone
setting it from frame zero to frame 12.
This way I will be able to see
the spacing of my root bone
between the different
poses we have created.
And since the root bone is
supposed to have a linear motion
since we are doing a cycle,
I can try to make the
spacing match the timing.
If we have a loop to the spacing
between frame three and frame five,
we can see that the position of
the root bone hasn't changed that much.
It means that since we have
a linear interpolation,
those two keyframes should be very close,
one to the other.
So I will offset the frame
five onto frame four.
Now if I keep this mindset
to analyze my spacing
I can see that from
frame zero to frame one,
I have a pretty large spacing
and I have the same spacing
between frame one and frame three.
So I have the same spacing
between those two poses
or almost the same spacing
but the timing is different.
The first one is on one frame,
the second one on two frames.
So I will offset my keyframes
from frame three to frame two.
So in the end I am animating
in those first four poses onwards.
And during the polishing stage
I will be able to revise a bit
the spacing between the
different part of the body.
From there I can evaluate
the distance between the
frame seven and the frame 10,
and the frame three and the frame seven.
And the spacing is quite the same as
between frame zero and frame two,
so timing-wise I think that
I should have two frames
between my airborne pose
and the contacting poses.
So I will move my airborne pose
from frame seven to frame five,
and then I should be moving
frame 10, 11, and 12
on frame seven or frame eight.
Again the timing and spacing of
the animation will be refined during
the polishing stage in spline modes,
but this is a good way
if you can't feel your
timing to check it out.
Try to make it logical.
And it does show case again
that having a detailed blocking
can really help the animation process.
If you have animated your character
without moving the root bone
then use the features of your character
that are contacting the tree trunk
to guess the spacing.
When I check the back-right
foot of my character,
I have the same spacing
between frame zero and one
and between frame one and three.
So I can choose to move
the pose number three
onto frame number two.
And when I see the different of spacing
between the current pose and the next one,
it's even smaller so
this change of position
should happen within one frame,
even less than one frame
so I will move it onto frame three.
Then I want my character to float a bit
so I will keep in airborne for two frames,
for example, I can track
the front hands to see
the different of spacing
between those two frames,
and I believe that this
airborne position will be
the extreme so it will
be quite of right in
the middle of the jump,
so I can move frame 10
and all the next poses
onto frame seven.
So in the end, during our blocking stage
we have created almost
a pose for each frame,
and this is because we are working
on the fast motion animation.
And this will happen when
you work on combat animation
for example, where your character
change poses very fast.
You can't keep an empty frame
if there is a lot movement
that happen in this frame,
you will have to detail your blocking.
The good news here is that
it's going to be way easier
to polish this animation.