- [Instructor] It's now time to switch
to spline and polish our
climbing cycle animation
and then will be to remove the linear
feeling of the cycle and
get this hopping motion.
So as usual
the first thing we will do is
select all of our controllers.
Then in the action editor,
select all the keys.
Press the T key and switch to busiest
so that we are now in spline mode.
You can then press control tab to switch
to the graph editor, enable
the display all filter,
press alt+H to make sure
that there is no curve hidden
and press shift E to apply
the make cycle modifier.
Now the animation will be cycling forever.
As we have seen in the previous cycle,
we need to clean the root spoon, meaning
that we want a linear
interpolation of the root ball.
The first thing to do is to
select all the key frames
of the root bone and remove all of them
but the first and last.
Then you can either press the T key
and switch to linear interpolation
or select all the key frame
press the V key, and
switch to vector handles.
This way we will also have
a linear interpolation.
To enable the linear extrapolation,
we first need to get rid
of the cyclic modifier.
Select all the keys of the root bone
press shift E clear cyclic modifier.
Then press shift E again, and
choose linear extrapolation.
Now our character will be moving forward
in a linear fashion.
At this stage, you probably
have some foot sliding
and that's perfectly normal.
We will fix and place the feet later on.
As explained in the
beginning of this video,
the big deal here will be to get rid
of the linear feeling of the motion.
All contacting frames for the
feet will still be linear.
Also the root motion will be linear.
So we need to play with the body,
the chest of our character,
to input some hopping
and contrast into this climbing animation.
As usual, I'm working with the
main controller of the body.
I will start with the
location channels first.
And while I generally start
with the Z location channel,
the up and down, here I will start
with the Y location channel
because since our character
is rotated upward,
the Y rotation channel kind of become
the up and down channel.
And this is the one where we must input
as much contrast as possible.
So the first thing I had
done was to push the pause.
Push the Y value higher
so that the character
is pushing backward more.
Since we are working on
the cycle, I make sure
that I always duplicate
the first key frame
and move it onto the last key frame.
To bring contrast to the motion,
the thing to avoid is to create
a perfect sinusoidal shape.
This is why I have almost a plateau
between frame zero and one.
And I will also push
from eight to slightly higher.
This way I'm pulling my
character back upon eight frame.
And then I transition
forward on the other frames.
I can even increase the contrast
by lowering the value of
the curve on frame three.
In the end, we get the fast variation
from frame two to frame four,
then some kind of lower plateau
and then it transitions
smoothly to frame nine.
And these back and forth
motion will be amplified
by the back and forth motion
of the chest, head, and hips.
Regarding the Z location curve,
the amplitude of the
motion is more subtle.
I'm mainly cleaning the shape
of the curve so that
it's a little smoother.
And don't forget that when your character
is pushing forward his body
is getting closer to the tree trunk.
So he's losing altitude.
And when he's grabbing back the tree trunk
then he's getting more altitude.
At some point, I flattened
the curve to make sure
that the belly of the character
wasn't clipping with the
surface of the tree trunk.
For the X location channel,
I just got rid off any variation
by flattening the curve.
I will input a little bit
of twisting on the chest
of the character in the
final stage of the polishing.
The rotation motion is also pretty subtle.
As usual, I'll start with the X rotation
because it's the most influential.
And I've mainly been polishing the curve,
making it smoother, and making sure
that the character is
diving down into the jump.
As you go along again
don't forget to duplicate your frames
in row on your last frame.
And don't forget that
when you're ready to curve
you might be going back onto
it whenever you are polishing
other controllers, because
everything is connected.
So modifying the torse
now might quite have
changed the behavior of the
chest, of the head, et cetera.
And when you're polishing a
specific part of the character
don't forget to isolate it
to check the motion this
way you will get rid
of all the visual noise
and will get something more readable.
The animation now looks
less linear than before,
and I'm slowly getting the "oomph"
of the pushing of the character.
Another way to see it is
obviously to calculate
the motion path of the main
controller of the body.
And from there, we can clearly see
that the spacing is
getting bigger whenever
our character is pushing
forward on this straight line.
And then I have a tighter spacing.
The character body is kind
of slowing down in space.
Whenever it's catching up.
I can now switch to the chest controller.
I'm first clearing the motion path
from the main controller to
have a cleaner workspace.
And as I oftenly do with
the chest controller,
I will work first on the X
quaternion rotation channel.
I won't be polishing the Y and
Z quaternion on rotation yet.
This is something I
will do at the very end
of the polishing stage,
based on the contact pose of the feet.
To get a better readability
of what I'm doing,
I will select the neck bone
and calculate the motion path.
The neck controller is
directly attached to the chest.
It makes this motion path relevant.
The idea here is to
emphasize the previous motion
we have created with the main
body controller, making sure
that our character is kind of
sliding along the tree trunk.
And making sure we emphasize
the pushing motion.
If we watch the final cycle
again, just check the distance
between the hips connection
and the shoulder connection.
This way we can clearly
see how I stretched
the body of the character to show
that he's curling his whole
body using his shoulders
and his chest.
And this is something I've achieved
by reworking the Y and Z location curve.
I advise you to work on both
curves at the same time time
because we are working
on the chest controller
which is a child of the main controller.
So we are working on local space
so you will need to play
on both curves to get a straight motion.
The Y location curve will
have the main influence
on this animation.
I have, I can trust that
frame zero to three,
this is the pushing
motion or pulling motion
as you wish, where the body is stretching.
Then as the character is airborne
the main body is slowly
catching up with the chest.
So I'm reducing the stretching
by lowering slightly the curve.
And finally, we have a
more radical squishing
or compression of the chest
when our character is contacting
with the tree trunk.
And I get a fast modification
of the curve value.
The Z curve is mainly here to correct
the orientation of the chest.
Finally, I flattened the X location curve
because I don't want the chest
to move left to right yet.
Next I've placed the head controller.
So it's a pretty classic workflow again.
And the curve editing from
the head will be very close
to what I just did for the chest.
As I always do whenever I'm tracking head,
I will use the nose controller
to calculate the motion path.
The idea, as usual, is to keep our arc
as smooth as possible.
Again, I'm starting by working on the X,
what's our normal
rotation of the character.
The idea is to make the
head slightly diving
or dragging into the jump forward.
But as explained during the run cycle
I try to avoid too much rotation
because I don't want the
head to wobble up and down.
This will communicate a lack
of control from our character.
And since he's very light and
agile, we don't want this.
I play on the Y and Z
location curve early on
because I do want to get this compression
and stretching of the
head as soon as possible.
And I'm using the X quaternion rotation
to fix the arc of the nose.
In the end, I get almost the
same curve as for the chest
but with one frame of offset.
In the end, I was going
back and forth onto the head
and the chest controller to get rid of
this little glitch on the
motion path of the nose.
Since I have a bit of physics lag
on the last frame of the motion path,
I spend some time
on the three last frames
to try to smooth this out.
Then I add the loop to my
animation in front view.
And I saw that I got a
slight rotation left to right
on the motion path of the nose.
So I've made a first pass
of polishing onto the
chest and the head rotation
on the left and right axis,
the Z quaternion rotation.
Those are very subtle modification.
I've kept the curve pretty smooth.
And the idea is to rotate the torso
toward the contacting point.
And when the character
is pushing, for example,
with his right hand, you push the chest
in the other direction,
in the opposite direction.
So when he's contacting
with the right hand,
you push the chest toward the right hand.
And when the hand this pushing,
or pulling in this case,
to get up there, the chest
is getting moved away
from the hand, just make it super subtle
and keep the curve as smooth as possible.
On this specific animation,
the hips are very important.
Hips controller is generally
something you have to
spend time on because it
really defines the way
a character is contacting with the ground.
The way he's gathering energy,
pushing and pulling his body
off the contact surface.
Think of the hips as a
catapult for the legs.
Starting with the X rotation
curve I will make sure
that when the character is
projecting his leg backward,
I have a very aggressive
motion of the hips.
And I tried to push the curve as much
as possible sometime
it kinds of look weird
so I will tune it down a bit.
But I want really to push
the paws as far as possible
because we do need to see this rotation
of the hips backward whenever
the character is pushing.
And then when our character
is contacting with the ground,
the hips are really rotating
inward toward the contacting frame.
And these very contrasted
motion does translate
on the curve.
You can see that the curve goes
down and up pretty quickly.
The next channel will obviously be
the Y and Z location curves.
We have already seen our squash
and stretch was important
into this animation.
So I will just emphasize this.
And then we do need an
offset between the stretching
and squashing of the hips
compared to the chest.
The hips are dragging backwards.
So on the first two to three frames
the hips are kind of squashed.
And as our character is jumping,
they get stretched a lot
and they will slowly catch up
during the airborne position
but mostly on the contact frame.
The hips curves shape
are slightly smoother
than the chest and the head
because since the head and
chest are leading the animation
this is where we need to
bring the most contrast.
And as the hips are kind
of following, are dragging
and catching up, we can give
them a slightly smooth curve.
They are kind of following
the main body controller
chest and head motion.
With have the whole body
of how our character
polished the animation does
look way better already.
So in the next video
you will have a full time
lapse of this polishing stage
and then we'll start polishing
the legs in the next video.