- [Instructor] Before we start
working with the NLA editor,
we need to clean up our
character animations.
First get back to object mode,
get rid of the cylinder,
select our character rig in object mode
and press Alt+G Alt+R Alt+S.
On the current claiming action,
reactivate the roots motion.
And for all our animation
we need to get rid of any
animation of the root boom.
So I will switch to show only selected
and then with my root boom selected
I will get rid of the last key frame.
I will press CTRLl+Tab
to switch back to the action editor,
open the temporary action I
created for the idle animation,
hold shift and click on the
cross icon to close the action.
Holding Shift will remove
the action from the file.
Now the closed action as zero users.
And when I will rebuild the file
it will be removed from
our action library.
I will also make sure
that I have no root motion
on my idle animation
and Alt+G Alt+R and Alt+S
to reset the position of the roots.
Then I get rid of all the
other key frames of the root.
I will do the same for the run cycle
making sure that my character
is cycling on position
without any root motion
and remove all the temporary actions.
In the end I only kept the keying,
the run cycle,
the idle and the climbing cycle.
All the other action have no users.
Hence the zero in front of their name.
Now I can go to file, click revert,
it will reload the current file
and the zero users
action have disappeared.
From there, I can double
check each actions
and if you want to make it even cleaner,
you can duplicate the
first key of the route
and move it onto the very
last key of the animation.
This is not necessary.
So don't do it if you don't want.
So let's get started with the NLA editor.
So, I will push a bit
my action eight window,
expand the timeline and
switch to the NLA editor.
By default, you will find out an NLA track
for each of the object
you have in your scene.
So we can see a track for
our squirrel mesh object
that also include a track
for the shape key used
to animate the eyes
and a track for our squirrel rig,
including a track called keying
because we have our keying action opened
in the keying editor.
Most of the shortcuts
and filters are the same
as in the graph editor
and the action editor,
so I won't go over them again.
Since I'm working only on the rig,
I will click the show selected only.
If I open the different
actions in the action editor,
I will see them appearing onto
the track of the NLA editor.
But I can't use them in
the NLA editor this way.
To use them in the NLA editor track,
I need to convert them to strip
by clicking this icon
or click the same icon
in the action editor
and push down the action into the track,
converting it to a strip.
Think now of your action
as an audio or video strip
that you can move in time using the G key
as you will do in a DVD auditor.
In the action editor near the push down,
there is another button called stash.
This is something I never use
but I will show you what it's made for.
If I click it, it will
create a new NLA track
with a new strip idle finished.
The NLA track is locked and disabled,
so it does no influence
on our character rig.
It is basically here to
replace the fake user we create
when we click on the shield
icon in the action editor.
If I remove the fake
user from my idle finish
and close the action
or open another one and save the file.
When they will revert
or reload my document,
the idle action is still there
because the NLA track is
considered being a user.
That's why we have two users
whenever we are opening the
action in the action editor.
But I think it makes the NLA editor messy
having all those additional tracks.
So I prefer to protect my
animation using the fake chooser
and getting rid of the track
by simply selecting it
and pressing the X key.
If I select the run cycle
strip and press the Tab key,
the trip will turn to green
meaning that the current
action is in edit mode
and I can see the action
loaded in the action editor.
I will close the idle
action in the action editor
so that we only have our
current NLA track available.
If I press shift+D, I
can duplicate the strip.
And if I press Alt+D, I can
make a link to duplicate
as we will do with any
object in the 3D viewport.
So as for an object,
you can consider this
strip as a container.
So if I press N or I click
the arrow icon to expand
the properties panel,
going into the strip tab,
I can see where the current
trip starts and ends
among a lot of different
options that we will be covering
in a few minutes.
But also the action used,
the same way will add with a mesh object,
the object is a container
and we have meshed data.
So we can see that the third strip
is using a new run cycle action
with the suffix tag 002.
The second one, another action
and the first one, our original action.
When I press Tab to enter edit mode
and modifying the current action,
we can see that the third strip
that we have created using
the linked duplicate action
is colored in red.
I will make a quick
modification to the action.
I will then go back into the NLA editor
and press the Tab key
and I can see that I am
playing the modified animation.
But if I scrub over the second strip,
we can see that he's
playing another animation
the ones that hasn't been modified.
But if I scrub over the third strip,
we can see that it's
playing the same action.
as for the first one.
Since the action are linked,
modifying one will modify the other.
You can add a new strip to an NLA track
by pressing Shift+A and
choosing the action.
But at least on this version of them
they are all at the time
I'm recording this video,
you have to make sure that
your NLA track is active
by simply clicking it to select it.
I guess it will be cool
if blender automatically
add a new track if you don't
have any tracks selected.
In the meantime, just
remember this little tip.
Let's have a look to the different option
available in the NLA editor.
When I duplicate NLA strip,
by default blender will
create another NLA track.
Double-clicking on the
track will allow you
to rename the track.
You can reorder the track
position by right clicking on it
and choosing whatever you want to do
or using Page up and Page
down or Shift+Page up
and Shift Page down.
With the idle track selected,
I can press Shift+A and
select the idle action,
it will create a new strip
using the idle action.
The numerous strip will be created
where the play head is positioned.
To create a new track,
I have to create a new action
in the properties panel.
By default, the action is empty.
So I need to create a
key frame on the bone
to be able to push it down
and add this new track.
Or I can simply browse
through my action library,
choose one and push it down.
The huge power of the NLA editor
is to allow to combine different actions.
As I told you before,
I asked you to think of it as video clips.
So as my first run cycles comes to an end
I should be able to see my idols strip.
But nothing happened.
And this is because of
the extrapolation mode
of our first run cycles strip.
As it is set to old forward
when this strip it's N,
it will keep our character
in the latest pose
or in the latest read key frame
of the action containing the strip.
This extrapolation is displayed as
low Pacitti yellowish
background or grayish background
when the strip is not selected.
Setting the extrapolation mode to nothing
will get rid of the old forward
and idle animation with play.
Sitting the extrapolation mode to hold
will work as the hold forward.
It will extrapolate the latest pose
and it won't allow us to
read the idle animation.
The subtle difference is that
if I choose old forward
you can see that the
influence of the strip
doesn't occur before it
but while it will override
any strip that comes after
and is not on the same NLA track.
It wants to override any strip
that is available prior to heat.
So in the end, it is useful only
if you don't have any strip before.
You can see that my character
is in the run cycle pose
while if I choose old forward,
it is in the rest pose
if it has nothing to read
prior to this NLA trip.
By default, our blending
mode is set to replace.
It means that any strip
that has these landing mode
and is super in the NLA track stack,
will replace any other strip
on other analytic tracks,
exactly as a video editor will work.
If I set the blending mode to add,
we will get a totally crazy results.
And this is because, in the NLA editor
the blending mode applies
to the keyed value.
So in this case, all of our controller
that are all keyed in each action
are added one on top of the other.
So currently, the scaling of
one from the first action,
is added by the scaling of
one on the second action.
And it's the same for the
location and rotation.
This is why we get this crazy
Frankenstein transformation
of our squirrel character.
If I switched to substructure,
it will mostly set all the scale to zero.
So our characters will disappear.
And if I use the multiply blending mode,
we won't have any problem with the scaling
but the rotation and location
is pretty hard to predict.
So those blending modes are generally used
in very specific cases,
but there is one mode that is super useful
is to combine mode.
If I try to combine the run and the idle
it will still look weird
but let me prepare something for you.
I will push the idle animation away
regroup my boyfriend cycle.
Then unselect the track,
click on the new action
and I will simply move my route boom.
So I will key its location on
frame zero and unframed 24.
I will move it by 1.4 meters on the y-axis
as we did, when we were
doing the run cycle.
I will then select those keys
make sure that they are
into linear interpolation.
And now when I play the animation,
we can see that the motion of the root
is combined with our run cycle.
And if I now put the idle
at the end of this strip,
since I will root
locomotion strip is on hold,
our squirrel character will stay in place
and we will have a perfect blending
between the run cycle
and the idle animation.
So now, just imagine what we could do
if I was to edit the locomotion,
add a bit of rotation,
switch left to right,
and then add also a bit of rotation
on the root of the body of our character.
This way, from a base run cycle,
I can input variation into
my characters locomotion
into his behavior
and this can be perfect to
rapidly prototype a shot
for example or to iterate
on different variation
of the same animation.
You don't really know
where your characters
are supposed to go,
you want to test different
poses different animation.
That's a good way to do it
without reanimating everything.
This is why NLA editor
is often the compounded
to the layers tool in Maya.
And they was able to
create these variation
of our animation in three minutes.
So it's not perfect
but that's a good pace.
To make our life easier,
there are also blend in and out options.
I will create a new
action for our character.
It will be a simple rotation
of the ed controller
that will hold for the whole animation.
I will suggest extrapolation to nothing
and the blending mode to combine.
Now when my character is
executing its run cycle
he has his head turn towards us.
The blend in and out option
are pretty straightforward.
If I add the 10 frame on the blend in,
it will take 10 frames
before our character
as his head turned.
And the blend out will work the same
whatever the value I
will put in the blend out
it will these number of frame
to reset to his initial posts.
It's like playing with the influence
of the head rotation track.
And since the influence is a value,
we can animate this influence.
So I will set it to
zero on the first frame
and to zero on frame 24.
Open the graph editor
and now I can access to curve
of the influence of this layer
and create the blending by myself.
Within the values that
goes from zero to one,
I can tell blender how much influence
I want this NLA track to
have on top of my run cycle.
So here it doesn't look like
something really beautiful,
but that's very handy.
Enabling the auto blending
will automatically create
the blend in and blend
out based on the position
of the strips on the top
track and the bottom track.
We can see the influence curve appearing
on the blending strip.
Here it's blending in,
but if I move the ed terms
strip before the other strips,
it will blend out.
Another fantastic
feature of the NLA editor
is to be able to manipulate time.
If I select my run cycles
strip and press S to scale,
the strip will be currently
scaled from the play head
and it will basically affect
the frame start and frame end.
Doubling the size of this strip
will play the action twice slower.
If I increase it to 44 frames for example,
I will almost be playing
it in a slow motion
four times slower than
the original animation.
So that's a fantastic tool
if you want to create slow motion effects.
If I make this three plank shorter
then the animation will be accelerated.
The reversed option will simply
play the current animation
in reverse.
I've made some research
and some experience with
the cyclic strips time
and I absolutely don't
know what it's made for.
If I change the length of the action clip,
it will automatically change
the length of the active strip.
And since we have a cycle
modifier on our curve,
our animation is repeating
even beyond the frame 12
but we can make the animation repeating
by simply increasing the repeat value.
Even if I go into the graffiti task
select all my key and
clear the cyclic modifier,
the animation will be repeating,
so it will be cycling.
If I shorten the action clip
not the strip the action clip,
then the action won't be played entirely.
Pressing the Y key will
split the active strip
where the play ed is positioned.
The thing cyclic option will automatically
reset the wrench of the action clip
based on the first and last
key frame within the action.
If you modify the action
length within the action
and edit all through the tweaking,
then clicking this button
or enabling cyclic,
will automatically reset the
wrench of the action clip.
One of the super cool
feature of the NLA editor
is to be able to animate the strip time.
I have made my actions clip longer,
I will enable the animated strips time
and insert a key frame.
Now in my graffiti tall, I
have a new curve available.
I will duplicate the created key frame
and move it on frame 12
and it's value I will input 12
and switch everything to vector.
It basically means that
I have created a curve
that treated 12 frame over
12 frame in a linear fashion.
So my animation is playing at real time.
Now, if I offset value,
it will play at a slower time.
I think a curve that allow
us to modify the speed
at which we are reading
an action into a strip,
will allow us to create
incredible slow motion.
So instead of scaling the whole strip,
I can choose whenever I want my action
to be played at real time
or to dance slow down.
And if I reduce the value of the curve,
I can even play the action in reverse.
You can create tracer overwatch effects,
super easily with this kind of thing.
This is why the NLA editor
should we not be overlooked.
Because even if you want
to use those everyday,
it can owe you to do tons
of thing with a lot of ease
and with incredible results.
There's a last couple of
things I'd like to show you
in this video.
Pressing Shift+T will all you
to add a transition strip,
but you need to have two
active strip selected.
It will create a strip
that will automatically
blend one action to the other
creating a linear interpolation.
You can add those strip
through the ad menu.
If you are using speakers in
your 3D scene to play sound,
then you can add sound strip,
pressing the Shift+K shortcut,
or going to the ad menu.
You can group multiple
actions strip pressing CTRL+G
allowing you to manipulate them all at ons
and you can ungroup them
pressing Ctrl+Alt+G.
To summarize, we have
seen that the NLA editors
allows us to combine multiple strips
as if we where working
on the video editor.
We need to push an action
to make it an NLA strip.
The stash option can be used
to replace the fake user.
We can duplicate, clone
or add an action as a
strip into the track.
We can use extrapolation
and blending options
to combine different
strip on different tracks.
Action in the NLA tracks
affect only the keyed channels.
You can blend multiples strips
from different tracks together.
Scaling this trip will accelerate
or slow down the bound action.
You can split a strip pressing the Y key.
You can edit the timing of
an animation using the curve.
You can create transition
strips with shift+T
and finally you can
group or ungroup strips
with Ctrl+G and Ctrl+Alt+G.