- [Instructor] In this video,
we will see how to use a curve as a path
as in the tree climbing sequence.
In the corresponding file,
I have two collections, one
including a simple arrow
and the other one including
our squirrel character
and the tree.
Getting back to the arrow collection,
I will press Shift + A
to add a curve, Bezier curve.
As any other object added to your scene,
it is spawned onto the 3D cursor.
It has an origin point
and if I press Tab to enter edit mode,
I can access the handles of the curve.
It's pretty close to the handles we have
in the graph editor.
Curves have an orientation,
meaning that they have a starting point
and an ending point.
To see it, we can go into the overlay
and display the normals of the curve.
Arrows will be displayed along the curve,
showing you the orientation of flow
of the curve, also called
normals of the curve.
In edit mode, you can
manipulate the handles,
as I explained before,
using G, R and S.
You can change the handle type
as you will do in the graph editor,
pressing the V key.
Then you will get the same behavior
as the one we have in the graph editor
but this time for a 3D object.
And with any curve point selected,
you can press E to extrude a new point.
As any object, we can access the curve
that are in the properties panel.
You can give a bit of thickness
or geometry to your curve
going into the geometry panel.
The simple extrude will
generate a rebound-like shape,
while the bevel will allow you
to create some kind of pipe.
While we don't need
geometry for animation,
it makes the curve more
readable in the 3D space.
In object mode, I can
select my arrow object,
then select the curve to make it active.
Press Control + P and choose Follow Path.
Now if I scrub into the timeline,
I can see the arrow following the curve.
In the path animation option of the curve,
we can see the value frames.
And it is set to 100 frames.
It means that the object
that is parented to the curve
with the follow path option
will take 100 frames to get
from the beginning of the curve
'til the end of the curve.
Switching to 50 frame value,
you can see that now
my arrow get to the end
of the curve on frame 50.
As our arrow object is currently a child
of the curve, we can move it at will.
It will still follow the path.
And we can see that by default,
our arrow object will rotate
to follow the curvature of the path.
If I go into the option of the curve
to the path animation and uncheck Follow,
the object is no longer rotating
to follow the orientation of the curve.
The curve path only affect
the location of the object.
Let's restart from scratch.
I have removed any
influence from the curve.
I will reselect the arrow,
then the curve, press Control + P
and this time, choose Path Constraint.
This will add a path
constraint to the arrow
that we can see in the Constraint tab
of the properties editor.
From there, if I scrub into
the timeline, nothing happened.
Our object gets stuck on the initial point
of the curve.
If I click the Animate Path button,
now our object is
traveling along the curve
and you can see that
it takes it 100 frames
to follow the curve, as before.
It still use the frame's value
from the curve properties.
Let's go back onto our arrow object
and check out the constraint.
We can see the forward
axis and up axis option.
To better understand it,
I will display the axis on my object.
So we can see that our arrow
is pointing in its y direction
and the up axis is the z-axis,
exactly as set into the constraint.
So if I now click the Follow Curve option,
the orientation of the arrow will change.
It will follow the curve.
Its y-axis will be aligned
with the curve path
and the z-axis will still be pointing up
as set in the constraint.
If I switch the orientation to -y,
it will flip the arrow but it
will still follow the curve
and so if I choose the
x-axis, for example,
logically you can't use the same channel
as a forward and up axis.
It will deactivate the constraint
and it will no longer work.
The offset value have
two different behavior.
Let's move to frame 20
and in the offset value,
set the value to 10.
Our arrow is moved back on the curve.
Its current position is
frame 20, -10 frames.
The offset value is how
we delay the position
of the arrow in time.
Basically, we are
subtracting the offset value
to the frame's value of the curve.
So if I set it to -10,
it will currently move the arrow forward,
10 frame earlier in time.
Exactly as if I was on
frame 30 without any offset.
If I now enable the fixed position,
our arrow object will be stuck
to the beginning of the curve.
Now the offset value is
no longer a value in frame
but a value that goes from zero to one
and indicate the position
between the beginning
and the end of the curve.
Finally, if I enable
the curve radius option,
our constraint object scale
will depend on the curve radius.
So if I now go into edit mode
onto the curve and press Alt + S
with one of the control points selected,
I will be able to change
the radius of the curve
and this will influence the scale
of our arrow objects.
Finally, in edit mode,
when working on the curve,
with a control point selected,
I can change the tilt value
and I will see my curve
twisting or tilting.
And so will the object
that is constrained by the curve,
creating very nice animations.
We can tilt the curve with
the Control + T shortcut.
Let's now see how we can use this trick
to animate our squirrel character.
I will display the squirrel collection.
I will move the current curve
into the arrow collection
and I will press the
Shift + A in object mode
to add a new curve.
This is going to be our squirrel path.
This time, instead of
constraining the squirrel object,
I will constrain the root
bone of our character.
In pose mode, I can go
to the bone constraint,
not the object constraint
and add a follow path constraint
and source our curve.
Now the root bone of
our character gets stuck
at the beginning of the curve.
If I click the Follow Curve option,
I can see my character
getting align with the curve
and if I now scrub, I can't see it moving
because we need to click
the Animate Path button.
And by default, our character
will follow the curve and
reach the end on frame 100.
To give a proper orientation
to our character,
we need to switch to -y
as being the forward axis.
Now our character is
properly following the path.
A big warning here.
Whenever you are using a curve modifier,
make sure that the constraint object
has its origin aligned with world space,
meaning that its origin is reset
because if you offset the object,
the constraint will behave weirdly.
You can move the curve as you want.
The constraint object will follow
but make sure that the constraint object
has all its transform channels reset.
Now that you understand
the curve constraint,
you can go into edit mode
and start building your motion path
for your character.
I'm doing it into a little time lapse
because I'm using a simple rotation scale
and extrude functions.
My main advice is use as
less point as possible
and try to have your curve
as smooth as possible.
Also, you can use the bevel option
to give a bit of thickness to your curve
so that it's easier to
read along the tree trunk.
The less control point
you set onto your curve,
the easier it will be to keep it smooth
and so the animation of your character
will also be smooth.
If you create hard
angles or too curvy path,
then the animation of your character
will look weird unless you
heavily edit the animation
on top of the cycle.
When you're satisfied with the path,
you can zoom in and tweak
the tilt and position
of the control point
so that your character
feet stick to the trunk
and you avoid the clipping.
Don't forget to double
check from camera view
because sometimes, even if your character
is a bit floating, that's perfectly fine,
'til it looks good from the
camera point of view as usual.
Back to object mode,
we need to set the correct speed
for our character to climb the tree
and we can do it by
modifying the frame's value
into the curve's option.
As the feet are moving backward,
it means that our character animation
is faster than the locomotion.
So I need to reduce the frame's value.
With a value of 70, it
seems that now the feet
are sliding forward.
So our character locomotion is too fast.
So it's just a matter of trial and error
to find the correct value.
A value of 85 seems to work well for me.
And it depends on the curve length.
So you may not have the same value.
Another way to control the speed
at which our character is moving
is to use the offset.
We can enable the fixed position.
Now our character is no longer moving
and insert a keyframe
on the offset factor.
I'm setting a value of zero on frame zero
and on frame 85, a value of one.
If I now go into the graph editor,
I will be able to see the curve
of this animated value
and we can see that there is easing in
and easing out,
so our character is slowing
down and accelerating.
What I do need to do
is whether change the
interpolation of the curve
to linear or select all the handles,
press V, and switch to vector.
The cool thing about choosing this method
is that I can insert a keyframe
whenever my character is about to jump.
Then another keyframe
when he's just landing
and then I can offset a
bit the landing keyframe
if I want my character
to make a larger jump.
The only thing not to forget
is to also offset the latest keyframe
so that the interpolation
between those two keyframe
doesn't change, and so our
character speed remain the same.
But between frame 22 and frame 29 here,
the speed of my character
is no longer the same
and it seems he's doing a bigger jump.
This is a little trick that will allow you
to break the rhythm of your animation
and make it more appealing.
At least, less linear.
This is the end of this chapter.
You now know everything to be able
to create the same shot as I did.
Don't forget that failing
is a part of the process
but giving up is not
a part of the process.
Stay strong, repeat
and I will see you in the next chapter
where we will learn new
animation techniques.
To summarize, we have seen
that we can use a 3D curve
as an animated path for
an object to follow.
We can use parenting or path constraint.
The frames' value determines the time
to travel along the whole curve.
We can use the offset value
to delay the path animation.
We can use the curve to scale
and tilt the constrained object.
We can use the constraint on a bone.
Make sure the origin of
the constrained object
is reset to world origin
before applying the curve constraint.