- [Instructor] And you
work on an animation
and get back to it with fresh eyes,
it's pretty common to have
a less satisfying feeling
about what you are seeing.
And I was feeling that the
animation was too fast.
I wanted to show more the
effort made by the character
to climb the tree.
Bring more contrast,
I need to make the
cycle a bit less linear,
and add some Hold on one pose.
And I wanted to add one frame
into the elbow and pose.
Why I got back to the action in it all,
I can select the frame of five to nine
and offset them by one frame.
Then it instantly feels better,
because we have this
moment where the character
is clearly squashing together energy
and then is holding a beat in the air
with its stretched pose.
And this little contrast in the timing
and the shape of the character
make it feels better.
And since our animation was very detailed,
meaning that we almost have
a key frame on each frame,
the offset looks almost okay.
So the first step is to
revise in sliding issue
since we have increased
the animation by one frame,
and we still have a linear
interpolation of the bone.
To fix the speed at which
the feet of our character
are sliding on the tree trunk,
we just need to slightly adjust
the value of the Y location
of each feet of the character
using the same method as before,
just make sure that the first key frame
and the last key frame are the same.
And you can use the 3D cursor as a marker
to know where the foot
is during the motion.
Most of the work
is just about going
through every controller
you have already polished
and kind of slightly fixed the curve.
Honestly, that's very fast.
It took me like 20 minutes
to fix the whole character,
because the pose we have chosen
to be extended a bit in time
is kind of a hold in the air
where the motion of the character,
the pose of the character
doesn't change that much.
So I'm slightly rotating the curve
and the angles just to get a nice
and smooth curve.
In the end,
adding this little frame really helps
also polishing the foot and
getting a better motion path.
The previous version of
the animation was good,
but this time adding this little detail,
this little more range to work on
really helped smoothing
out the whole animation
and contrasting the strength
put into it by our character.
You can watch the whole process
in the next time lapse video.
I will see you in the video after,
where we will add all the secondary motion
like the ears the nose
and also polish the tail.