- [Instructor] In this video,
we will work on the first shot.
I've already added a camera rig
and I've already created a keying set
for the different controllers
but also the camera
properties you can access,
pressing the N key.
I have keyed the focal length
and the focus distance.
I will now move my mouse cursor
onto the 3D view we have on the right
with the camera view.
Press Z and switch to rendered view mode.
I'm using the Eevee render engine
and the scene is pretty light.
Is it should render properly
on almost every graphic cards.
Let's now have a look to the organization
of the scene.
All the assets are organized
into the scene collection
and there are sub-collections.
All the collections tagged in
green includes all the assets
for the environment
so that you can deactivate them
whenever your computer is
slowing down, for example.
The set collection
includes all the lights,
the lights effect and the camera.
The particle emit collection
includes all the particle emitters
that generates the falling leaves
but also the birds flying
that we can see in the
beginning of the teaser.
I won't show you how to
create all those assets
because this is not the
purpose of this course.
All the bushes and trees
are currently instanced.
As when we link an asset
from another scene,
you can instance an asset into the scene.
So you can see,
those are empty object
instancing a collection.
Those collect are under
the asset main collection.
So if you want to modify the tree model,
you have to do it in those assets
but I advise you not to do it.
But if, for example, I scale down one
of the trees, you can see that
now the trees are very small
in my main scene.
So you can easily duplicate
and change the orientation
or scale of the objects that are available
in the scene to create
your own environment
or tweak this one if you will.
Let's now import our character.
I will make sure I have
my main scene selected.
Go to File, Link, insert for
the squirrel finished file.
I will go into the collection
and link our squirrel collection.
I can move it on the y-axis
so that we can see it.
From there in the outliner,
I will expand the squirrel library,
search for the collection, right click.
ID Data, Add Library Override Hierarchy.
It has created a new collection,
including our rig and
our character centered
in our scene.
So we can now select the source
and get rid of it.
I can now select the
armature of my character
and place it wherever I want in the set.
From there, let's check
if we have all our animation available.
Select the character armature.
I advise you to use the
outliner to select it
because on complex scenes,
selection can be a bit messy.
From there, in the 3D
view, press Control + Tab
to switch to pose mode
and in the action editor,
have a look at the
different linked animation.
Logging set can be useful,
so I will duplicate it,
so now I have a new
copy of the keying set.
I remember I have named
my final run cycle animation Runcycle.
So as I find it, I will duplicate it
and since I'm missing the idle animation
we have created in the previous videos,
I will go to File,
choose Link, but you can
append the animation,
browse into my Blender file
and go to the Action folder
and choose the idle.
If you have append it, it will be added
as a new animation.
If you have linked it, just
browse in your library,
select it and click on the icon
to make it a new action.
To create this shot,
we will combine the run cycle and the idle
and we will layer some root
motion using the NLA editor.
We can now switch back to object mode
and we will position our
character more or less
where he has to land where
he jump out of the bush.
Don't worry, we will be able
to fine tweak its position later on.
Since we have a pretty noisy ground,
you don't really care if your character
is perfectly contacting the ground.
Just raise him a bit
so that we can distinguish its feet.
To make my life easier, since
I will be mainly working
on the character, I will make sure
that I will make all the
other collection unselectable
by clicking this icon.
If it's not available for you,
just go in the filter and activate it.
Now I will go back in
pose mode on my character.
I will load its keying animation,
duplicate it and rename it to
create a locomotion action.
This is the action we will
layer on top of our run cycle
and idle to move our character in space.
Now we can open the NLA editor
where we will combine
those different actions.
I will enable the show
only selected option
and I will get rid of all those NLA tracks
that are not used.
We have a first NLA track
that is available called run,
so as seen in the NLA video,
if I close my action,
then the NLA track will be rigged.
And we can see one cycle of the run cycle.
I can press Shift + A
and add an idle action
so that our character
will make one run cycle,
then jump into the idle
and then I can add a more run cycle action
after the idle or you can
duplicate the current one.
I will duplicate it three times
so that our character
will make three cycle.
Or you can simply change the strip length.
Since there is a cycle
modifier on the curve,
the character will repeat the run cycle.
But this might not work
since we have linked the animation.
And it might create conflict,
so the NLA editor won't
allow you to do so.
But we will see that later
as it's a bit complex
and we don't need to dive into this topic.
Now I will select the first NLA track
and press Shift + A and add
our locomotion animation to it.
The strip is almost empty
because the action is only
one frame for the time being,
so let's open it in the action editor.
The idea is to key our first move.
If you remember well, our run cycle
was performed within 12 frames
and our character was moving by 0.7 meter
in the negative direction.
My root bone selected in post mode.
I will type in -0.7 meter
in the y location channel
and insert a keyframe.
Remember to enable the
autokeying in the timeline
and the keying set to available only.
I can add a keyframe by simply pressing I
in my action editor.
Then I will select my
root keys and press V
to switch them to vector.
Since I already have a track
with the locomotion action onto it,
I can close the locomotion
action in the action editor
and my character is still moving,
reading the locomotion track.
If I disable it, the character
will read the next track
with the idle in the run.
To combine them, we need to
change the strip blending mode.
And this is where it's a bit tricky.
At the time I'm recording this video,
I've tested it on Blender 2.91 and 92
and we can't edit the strip behavior used
by a linked data,
which is a bit weird
since we can modify the action
but we can't modify the
way the action are used
with the NLA editor.
To fix this, and I believe
this is a temporary fix,
and the behavior will change
with newer Blender versions,
we need to make our rig fully local,
breaking the link between the
scene and the original file.
Simply left click on the
override icon near the name
of your object.
From there, the strip option are available
and we can change them,
making this run cycle action, for example,
longer and repeating over time.
Or more important in our case,
selecting the locomotion action
and switching its
blending mode to combine.
This way we get both the locomotion action
and the running cycle
action combined together.
And since we are using Alt + forward,
our character keep the last position
of the root bone we have keyed,
exactly as shown in the NLA editor video.
So now that we are able to
move our character in space,
let's position hin properly based
on the camera position.
I will also clean up a bit my file
by renaming the locomotion
track, locomotion.
From there, select the
armature of the character
and make sure that you are in object mode.
The goal is not to animate
the position of our character
but just properly frame
where he'll be standing
while performing his idle animation.
So by moving the armature
object in object mode,
I'm kind of setting where
the animation starts
and the idea here is to do it in top view
and double check in my
camera view how it looks.
The character goes through the bush
and kind of land in the
middle of the screen.
So it looks great to me
but you are free to move
the bush a little bit
and then we will edit the camera position.
So now I'd like to make my character move
once he's escaping.
So we need to edit our locomotion action
and we can press the Tab key
to enter tweak mode and
automatically access our action
in the action editor.
We can duplicate frame 12 and move it
on frame 104.
This way, the root of our
character doesn't move.
Now for the next 12 frames,
I'd like to move my
character by 0.7 meters.
So I will input a value of
-1.4 meter on my y-axis.
And Blender should
automatically write the key.
But it doesn't and when I try to force it,
pressing the I key,
I get an error message.
Blender tells me that this action
is used in the NLA editor
but the NLA editor has no
influence to using this action.
But when I check the NLA strip
and I check the action influence,
it's set to one but what's happening here
is that our locomotion strip
on the locomotion track
is too short.
So it has no influence
beyond the frame 12.
Hence Blender doesn't allow
to insert the keyframe.
To fix this problem,
we can ask Blender to
automatically update the length
of the strip.
We just need to go to
the action clip option
and enable synchronize length.
Now if I change the value of the y-axis
of the root bone,
Blender will automatically
insert a keyframe as usual.
I will select the newly created key,
press the V key
and switch its handle type to vector.
So that we have now fixed this problem
and we can move our character in space,
I like to give some
variation to the animation.
Instead of making our character moving
in a straight line, I
like him to rotate a bit
on the second jump.
So I will go into top view
and I will disable the bush collection
so that we have a better
overview of our character.
I will rotate it a bit
and offset it a bit on the
side, only using the root bone
and being on frame 160.
Then I will move the
playhead 12 frames later
on frame 128
where our character will
land for the next time
and I will offset its position.
It doesn't have to be super accurate.
I'm just trying to offset
my character by 0.7 meter
in the same direction.
Since our character is
jumping out of the frame,
it doesn't matter if it's
not perfectly accurate.
The motion might look a bit
robotic from the top view
but from the side view or the camera view,
it does look pretty cool.
That's another thing
we haven't tackled yet
is that you generally
animate to camera view,
meaning that it doesn't
matter how it looks
from other angles.
The thing is that it has to look straight
from what will be outputted in the movie.
So now if you want, you
can add some extra motion
to your character.
To keep things simple for this animation,
we will only add a bit of rotation
in the main torso controller.
Add a keyframe on all
channels on frame 104.
From there, I will try
to have a better angle
on my character and select the
main root torso controller.
We will go on frame 109,
more or less in the middle of the jump
and the idea is to slightly
twist our character
toward the direction he's jumping to.
So the idea is to slightly
rotate the main controller
on the local y-axis.
So I will switch the pivot point to local,
press R and then Y to
constraint on the local y
and slightly lean our character.
Then on the frame where he's landing,
I will press Alt + R
to cancel the rotation.
This will just add a little twist
to the character body while
he's changing rotation,
making it look more natural.
What I want to show you there
is that you can fine tweak your animation
at will using this method.
If you want, you can lay
a bit of head rotation
or tail rotation
and this is a very good method
to get high-quality results
without spending too much
time on the animation.
So it's a perfect method for beginners
or if you are tight on the time budget.
Now is the perfect time to
work on our camera animation.
If you press Tab or select
another action strip,
Blender will automatically
exit the tweak mode.
And the length of our locomotion strip
has been updated thanks to
the synchronize length option.
From there, I can press Control + Tab
to get out of pose mode
on our squirrel armature.
Make sure that I make
my collection selectable
and I will select the camera rig
and press Control + Tab.
The dolly rig action
should already be assigned
to this armature.
The first thing to do
is to frame our main shot.
I think it's easier to keyframe first
where you want to go
than where you come from.
So I will go on a frame
where I can see my character
and I will lower the aim
controller of the camera
to better listen to the character.
Then I will increase the
focal length of the camera
so that we are a bit more
zoomed onto the main subject
of our animation.
This is going to be my default pose,
so I will move the keyframe on frame zero.
I will then select all those keyframe
and move them away in time.
It doesn't matter where I put them.
So let's now create our first framing
by moving the aim controller of the camera
towards the sky.
I will also slightly move
up the camera controller.
It will just add a bit more texture
to the camera animation.
Just imagine you have the
camera on your shoulder
and you're raising and looking at the sky
at the same time.
So there is a bit of
translation and rotation.
For the time being, this
shot is pretty blurry,
so I will search for the focal distance
and I will increase it's value
until I get a sharper result.
So now we have our camera
going back to the ground.
It will stop here for a few frames,
then have a look to the bush
where our character is hidden
and then follow the character.
So we can select the keys on frame 60
and duplicate them on frame 78 or 80.
So there, I will go on frame 94 or 95
and I will move my end controller
toward the main bush.
Then I will go into the action editor,
press I and insert a keyframe
on every controllers.
The base animation of our camera
is now what we need to do
is to synchronize the movement
of our squirrel character
with the current set we have created.
And with the NLA editor,
it's gonna be very easy.
Let's press Control + tab
to get out of pose mode, select
our squirrel character rig
and in the NLA editor,
I just need to select all the strips,
press G to offset them onto frame 100.
If we uncheck the show
only selected option,
we can see also our camera action.
And if we play our animation,
we can see our camera getting low
and our character jumping out of the bush.
So now let's select back our camera rig
and press Control + Tab
to get back into pose mode.
I will move the last keys for our camera
whenever the camera is framing the bush
by two keys so that I have
a slightly smoother motion
and then I will duplicate those keys
and move them on frame 109.
This is the moment our camera will start
to rotate to follow the character.
So I make sure there is a slight delay
between the time our
character jump out of the bush
and the time our camera
is starting to rotate.
It will look more natural.
Do not make your camera
anticipate the motion
of your character.
That will look fake or CG.
Now we can duplicate
our keys from frame 60,
which are the frames that
are focused on the character
and move them around frame 125.
From there, we need to increase the length
of our animation.
So I will set the end on frame 250.
To do so, position the
playhead on frame 250
and press Control + End.
Now I can duplicate
the keys from frame 125
to the frame 203.
This is when our character
is preparing to flee.
And since I want a bit of
delay for the camera reaction,
I will duplicate or
offset those keys on 209.
Now I can move on frame 227
and offset the aim controller
toward the bush on the right
where our character is disappearing.
Now if we check the animation,
we can see that our camera is trying
to follow the character
but we have a bit of delay,
which looks pretty natural.
Now the final touch on
the camera animation
to make it look less robotic
is to add a very slight overshoot
through the graph editor.
I'm not really good at animating cameras
but what I can tell you
is that try to keep your camera motion
as simple as possible.
With that being said,
just switch to the graph editor
and with the aim controller selected,
I will expose all the different channels
and hide the rotation channels
since they are not used.
And now what I will do,
whenever a curve hit a
keyframe before a hold,
where the camera is not moving anymore,
I will slightly rotate the handles.
That will create a very subtle overshoot
that will make our camera motion
way more believable and interesting.
From there, we will
just add the final touch
to our animation, making the bush move
and adding some particles.
So I will make myself a bit of room
in the different editor.
Get back to pose mode
and select the bush our
character is jumping from.
I will position the playhead more or less
just before the camera is
rotating toward the bush.
And with the bush selected,
I will insert a keyframe on its rotations.
From there, I can switch
to the action editor.
We don't need to use the
graph editor for this.
And to make the bush shake,
I will go just two frame later,
slightly rotate it on the left.
Go two or three frame later,
slightly rotate it on the right.
Repeat it two or three time
and finished with its original keyframe
by simply duplicating the
first keyframe we have set.
I will then offset those keys,
create a hold by duplicating the last key
and move it whenever the
character is jumping out
of the bush.
And I will repeat the process,
making a slight shake
whenever he's getting through the bush.
From there, I will just
offset the first group
of keys just before the camera is rotating
toward the bush.
The bush shakes, the camera turn.
Now we need to adjust the particles.
In object mode, go into
the particle collection,
select the bush emitter.
Our character is jumping out of the bush
on frame 104.
Knowing that, let's go
into the properties editor,
select the particles property
and under the Emission tab,
change the start and end value to 102,
two frames prior our
character is jumping out
of the bush.
It's basically a simply plane
emitting leaves particles.
So you can adjust its position if you want
and I've just shown you how to modify
when it emits the particles.
I won't go further
because this is not a
course about particles
and particle system could
require a full course.
When you're happy with your particles,
if you want to make sure that
they will render properly,
go to the Cache tab,
check the Disk Cache option,
and whether click the Bake button
or Bake All Dynamics, it will
bake all the particle system
in the scene.
If you need to tweak the particle setting,
just delete the bake
and bake again after you
have tweaked your settings.
If you want to adjust
the birds in the sky,
it's the same system.
Just unzoom a bit
and you will find a particle emitter
for the birds or you
can select it directly
into the collections.
Then you can offset the
start and end values,
even before frame zero
so that those birds will be emitted
before the animation start
and they will be in frame on frame zero.
So for this current shot,
a value of -64 and 0
is currently good.
And when you're done,
don't forget to bake the dynamics.