- In this video,
we will have a quick overview
of the different sequences
and how to render and edit them
in the Video Sequence editor.
The second scene or second
shot of our short animation
is super simple.
The camera is simply
moving in a linear fashion,
using linear interpolation on the x-axis
following our character
until it disappear into a bush.
The character itself is simply
using it's run cycle
animation that is looping.
And on top of this I have
layered simple locomotion action
in the NLA editor that move
by 0.7 meters every 12 frames.
And then choose an extrapolation filter
set to linear extrapolation.
(wind woosh effect)
For the next shot,
when our character
start climbing the tree,
the root of the camera is
still moving left to right,
but this time I have a bit of
easing in the camera motion,
and then the camera stop.
In the meantime,
I'm using the Aim controller
to create down to up motion.
Particularly the camera
is following the squirrel
and there is a slight easing
until the end of the shot
that the camera looks a little more alive.
Also the character is not full frame.
He appear on a third of the camera
and is facing the closed side of the shot
so that we do feel like he's escaping.
For the character motion it's as usual.
I've combined this time,
the climbing cycle with locomotion action
using the NLA editor.
For the locomotion animation
I've only animated the
root bone of the character.
Since his motion is not
as linear as before,
meaning that it's likely
changing direction on each bounce
but still as a constant speed,
I've made sure that I
add linear interpolation
between each frame switching
every handle to vector.
And then on each contact
pose of the character
I will slightly change its orientation
and moving following the tree trunk.
You can see that from a side view
it might not look perfect,
but it does work very well
from the camera angle.
So that's perfectly fine.
(wind woosh effect)
On the next shot there is no camera motion
so it's just about placing the camera.
Again, our character is framed
so that it follows a
third of the camera view.
I am still using the
climbing cycle animation
we have created,
but this time you can see
there is no locomotion action.
Instead, I'm using a path constraint
on the root bone of our character.
We will see how to create it
and use it in the next video.
But particularly our character
is simply following a curve
and we can animate the
speed at which the character
is following this curve.
While we should use a linear speed
I slightly edited the
speed of the character
using the Graph editor,
inputting a bit of variation.
so that it looks a little more dynamic
from the camera angle.
And that was it.
(wind woosh effect)
For the very last sequence
of our character animation
the camera doesn't move
until our character
settle in the shot.
Then the root of the camera
is slightly moving up and forward
and I've animated the focal
length and the focus distance
so that we are progressively
focusing onto the horizon.
For the character animation.
I've used one cycle of the run cycle
combined with the locomotion,
which is a simple forward
animation on 0.7 meter.
And then I've used our idle animation.
And I've cut the idle
animation on frame 68.
What I did do on the very
final version of the trailer
was to add a couple of additional
animation on the very end
so that the character is still moving
while it's getting out of focus.
I haven't recorded the
the animation process
because that will be redundant.
And you will still have a lot
of animation content to watch
in this course.
But the process was exactly the same
as when we have made our idle animation.
So it's also time for you
to try to do it on your own.
(wind woosh effect)
As you are done with animation
we need to render those shots.
If you are using the provided file,
I've already set up the render.
You just need to go to Render
and click Render animation
or press Control + F12.
As you do, Blender will
render the animation scene
with the camera view.
It will start from the start
frame till the end frame
and using the resolution
set into the dimensions.
We don't care about frame rate,
unless we are exporting a
movie like an MPEG sequence.
But I do advise you to render PNG files.
If you run in movie file,
there is big chances
it will be compressed.
Plus, if Blender crashes before
the end of the rendering,
you will have to re-render
the whole sequence.
While if you are using image sequence,
you will just have to re-render
from the frame it has crashed.
I've set up my render
output so that Blender
will create the folder, "RENDERS",
and the subfolder,
"SCENE-05", 4, 3, 2 or 1.
And the image sequence
will be called, "Scene-05",
in this case.
And Blender will automatically
add a suffix number
corresponding to the frame number.
(wind woosh effect)
Since I generally use After
Effects to create my sequences
and work on my compositing,
I won't do an in-depth video
about the Video Sequence
editor in Blender,
but they will give you the foundation
that will allow you to
use it without problem.
So let's convert both
our 3D view and timeline
to the Video Sequence editor.
It's pretty straightforward.
We have different tracks
and pressing Shift + A
I can add different items.
It can be text, sound, whatever.
Let's choose image sequence,
browse our render folder,
and press A
to select all the PNG file
of the first sequence.
And press, Add image sequence.
Blender has automatically
added all our image
as a sequence on the first track.
If I want to extend the
end of the animation
to a further frame,
I just need to position the play head
and press Control + End
as we do in the timeline.
The image sequence is read
at the speed of our general frame rate.
To be able to preview
our animated sequence
we can switch to Sequence Preview.
It will display our sequence
track so we can collapse them
and also the current
frames that is being read.
If I press the Space
bar to preview my video,
we can see that the frame
rate is not very good,
but this is because Blender is
currently caching the video,
meaning that is kind pre-calculating it.
The cached sequence is
shown into a brighter red
beneath the tracks.
Once the images are cached
if we play it again,
it will play real time.
So what I will quickly do now
is repeat the process and
import the five image sequences
I have created for this shot.
Since there is no blending
between sequence one and two,
I can left click and drag
sequence two on the first track.
I can do the same with sequence three,
moving it on the first track,
but I will need to cut it a bit
because there are some repeating frame
between the previous
sequence and the current one.
To cut it I simply need
to place the play head
wherever I want to cut and press K.
Then I will scrub through the timeline
to watch out for any repetition
and remove any content
from the selected strip
by cutting it and then
pressing X to delete it.
Now I'd like to blend the
next sequence onto the other,
creating a fading.
The first important thing is
to find out the right timing
between the moment our character
is getting out of the frame
and when he's getting back into the frame.
Here I feel that the
time we wait is too long
before we see the
character back into frame.
So I will remove a part of the sequence.
Then I will move it on
top above the other,
so that we have overlapping sequences.
Pressing the N key
I will be able to open
the Properties panel.
And in this Strip tab,
in the Adjust panel,
I have an Opacity option.
I will click on the little dot
icon near the opacity level,
and it will automatically
insert the key frames.
It means that on this frame
our strip will be fully opaque.
I can scrub back to the
beginning of the strip
and then set the opacity to zero
and click this icon to
insert a new key frame.
And we've just animated
the opacity of the strip,
creating a natural fade.
From there, I can select
our last sequence strip.
Left click and drag, or press G,
to move it just after
the current sequence.
From there,
I advise you to cache the
animation and double check it
to see if it looks natural.
To cache the animation just play it once.
The final touch will be to boost a bit
the contrast of our shots.
So we press Shift + A and
add an adjustment layer.
I will move it on top of everything
and then I will left click
and drag onto one of the side
to extend it till the end of the movie.
Just think of it as an empty strip.
But whatever adjustment
modifier I will add on top of it
will be applied to any strip
beneath this adjustment layer.
So if I go to the Modifier tab,
I can add a new modifier
and I will choose the Curve modifier.
If I now left click on the
top right corner of the curve
and move this value up,
this will make the bright
color of our picture
even brighter.
So just push it ever so slightly.
And I will then click somewhere
in the bottom left corner of the curve
and just drag it down a little bit
so that the darker tone
will be a little darker.
So in the end,
we have kind of boosted a bit
the contrast of our picture.
If you click back and
forth onto the eye icon,
you can see your picture
with and without this curve modifier.
From there, you can add
another modifier if you want.
For example, a tone
mapping or a color balance,
and change a bit the colors of your shot.
To make it warmer, for example.
I won't go any further on this topic
because I'm not a
specialist of compositing.
Just experiment a bit with those modifier
and see how they behave.
From there to render your movie,
simply choose a file path and output.
Then I advise you to
select a movie file format
like ffmpeg.
I generally choose mp4
and then switch to h264
and use a loss-less quality.
Then go into the Sequence editor,
View, Sequence Render Animation.
Wait, and enjoy your movie.