- As the body is now polished,
I can work on the feet of the character.
Will start with the back legs
since they move the most.
First thing is to fix the Y location curve
on the contact pose.
Now I have a proper linear root motion
switch all the angles of the contact frame
of the feet to vector,
get rid of any intermediate frame,
and tweak the value
before the foot take off
to make sure that I don't
have any sliding effect.
Since the leg looks too
overextended on frame three,
I've decided it will
be the take off frame.
From the side view I worked mainly
on the Y location
and then the Z location.
As for a run cycle,
I don't push too much the foot away
from the tree trunk.
And forget that our character is pushing
toward the sky is not pushing
against the tree trunk.
If he does, he would fall.
So from the current point of view,
it's better to push the pose
of the foot downward,
than pushing it on the left side.
And when you reach the end of the cycle,
make sure that again the
contact pose are in vector,
then I'm fixing any sliding
issue by moving the frame eight.
Because if I was moving
the value of frame nine,
then I would have to duplicate
this value of frame zero
since this is the latest frame,
it would break the fix I did
in the beginning of the video
between frame zero and frame two.
Because the value difference
between frame two and
frame zero will change.
Regarding the X location axis,
what I've done is that
as the leg is taking off,
it will be pushing slightly inward
and then as it comes forward,
it will move on this side,
as if the character was going
to embrace the tree trunk.
This is something I will try to do
on both the hands and the
feet of the character.
Because as you climb the
tree trunk you're trying
to bind the trunk to your body in a way
But we do need to feel
that there is a side to
side force being applied
onto the tree trunk.
And the larger the tree trunk,
the wider our character
will open his arms.
As usual when I'm done
with the location curve,
I can work with my rotation curve.
When the foot is taking off,
I make sure that I have
a fast rotation back one,
so that we can feel that
the foot has just pushed,
and is kind of wiping in the air
And then as it catch up,
I will just make the
tip of the foot dragging
So I will use the rotation to do this.
Then I have my impact frame where I want
to open the foot just before
it lands on the surface ,
on the reference,
we can barely see,
that the character is currently
grabbing the tree trunk
with his toes.
But our rig definition
doesn't allow us to do this.
So what I did
is I just created a slight foot slap
as we did for the run cycle,
landing on the foot bone
and then flapping the toes
against the tree trunk.
I have used exactly the same
process for the left foot.
First make sure that you
don't have any sliding effect
Fixing the Y location on frame zero
until the frame where the foot take off
and repeat the process on the frame,
where the foot is
contacting the tree trunk
until the end of the cycle
If you want to push the
pause favorize the Y location
because the Z location
will take the foot thunder
away from the tree trunk,
and it won't match a climbing locomotion.
Then don't forget to work
on the X location curve
Spreading the leg on the
side as the character
is pulling it up before the contact pose,
so that we feel that the character
is catching the tree trunk,
not simply contacting with it,
but really grabbing the tree trunk.
And the final important detail here,
is to avoid twinning.
I've made both feet
contacting the tree trunk
at the same time and that's fine,
because we have very
few frames on the cycle.
But whether you're looking
from the side view or
from the front view, you can see
that my feet are never aligned.
Once the feet are polished,
you can rip onto the pole controllers.
They will allow us to fix
the orientation of the knees.
I won't be using the graffiti for this
I will just check frame by frame
and move the pole target if needed.
The idea is to push the knees inward
while our character is pushing,
And then reopen the legs as
he's pulling his feet apart.
For example here I add a bit
of a glitch in the motion of the knee
where I have a big modification
of the shape of the leg.
I'm just looking at the shape of the legs,
and moving the pole target,
so that I get a smoother
motion of the knee
I will apply exactly the same
process for the left leg.
When you are done with the pole targets,
use the tweaker controller.
To avoid any reversed
bending like this one.
Just scrub frame by frame,
and fix any weird the shape of the knees.
In the end,
I think I just needed to
fix a couple of poses.
Once I was done with the back leg,
I've worked with the ends of front leg
of the character,
I've used exactly the same process.
First fixed the Y location
to avoid any sliding
avoid to make too big
change on the Z location,
and made the hands getting
too far away from the tree trunk.
You will see in the next video
in the full time lapse that I've
initially really widely open
the arms using the X location,
and then I've tightened them because it
was looking a bit too weird.
Just remember that it's perfectly fine
to revise your poses
during the polishing stage.
I've initially posed the four arms
to be very tight to the body
and in the end using the x axis,
I've spread them on the sides
Forget to break the twinning also
on the arms.
And when you are done
polishing the arms controller,
you can use the joint
controller to fix the position
of the elbows.
Again for this process,
it's better to do it frame by frame.
Just make sure that your elbow
is bending in the right way.
So don't forget to rotate
around your character
and you will be done.
The next video will be a time lapse
of all the points we've just seen.
And in the video after,
I will change the timing of the animation,
because I wasn't satisfied
of what I add here.
Don't worry, it's not a big deal.
It will take only few minutes
but it will really improve the animation