- [Instructor] This is the final video
of this climbing animation.
It is now time to polish our tail motion,
so I will start with the root of the tail.
There are a couple things
you have to think of.
First of all, our character
is climbing vertically.
It's the tail has weight,
it should be hanging a bit downward.
Plus, since our character
has a vertical momentum.
The tail should also drag
in the opposite direction.
As usual, I'm starting to
work on the X rotation curve.
The idea is to avoid
any big flapping motion
because of the twin formation
we have seen before.
The root of the tail is moving in reaction
of the hips motion.
As the hips are raising from frame zero to
frame five to tail is going
the opposite direction
with one frame of delay.
From there I just need
to polish the curve,
make sure that the frame
10 and zero on the same
and that I get a smooth transition
between frame eight to frame 10.
This nice change in the curve shape
from frame one to frame three,
supports the drastic
change in the hips pose
while the character is pushing.
From there I will work on the next joint
in reaction from the first joint.
So you can see that my
curve is pretty noisy
because I've tried to make this animation
during the blocking stage.
So don't be afraid to destroy everything
and reshape the motion.
In the end the curve of the second joint
will look like the curve
of the first joint.
But with a bit of delay maybe one frame
and a smoother shape.
Cause the further we get
from the roots of the tail,
the more absorption of the
heaps motion we will add.
Since we are rebuilding
the whole tail motion,
I can get treated off any
of the next joint motion
because they are currently disturbing.
I can get treated of the
intermediate key frame
for the two controllers
or the tip of the tail.
So that it stays straight
and I have less difficulties
reading the motion of the tail.
As soon as I get a satisfying motion,
I make sure that the cycle
is transitioning properly
and I can jump on the next joint.
Can now rework the
motion of the next joint
by simply duplicating the first key frame
and reshaping the curve at will
based on the motion of the previous joint.
It's pretty straightforward.
The idea is to create a slight
waviness in the tail motion.
So if you want to create
a nice tail motion
for this animation,
make sure that the root of
the tail is moving properly.
And then you just create
this animation fall off
along the way.
From there we can start
working on this Z axis
for the left to right motion of the tail.
It's the same process as
for the previous motion
but we'll keep it a little
more subtle this time.
Since I'm rebuilding this motion,
I will get rid of all
the existing key frames
and will start by
duplicating the first key
Based on the hips motion of the character
I will create the follow-through
when the hips are going right
I will decide to rotate
the tail to the left
to create the dragging
motion of follow through.
Usually I make sure that
frame zero and frame 10
are the same and that they are align
are transitioning smoothly
with the next key frames.
I will then repeat the
process on the other joints.
As usual, you can see the full process
in the time-lapse video.
So the finer parts of this animation is
to work on all the secondary details
like the ears, eyes and nose tip.
I will use the straightforward method
meaning that I will be
animating along the way.
With both ears controllers selected,
I will get rid all the key frames
between frame zero and frame 10
Two thing we have to think of.
The first one is to avoid twinning.
That's why I pulled the
bit back the right ear
from the side view,
so that when we read the
silhouette our character.
We can see both ears.
And the second thing is to
keep the ears a little back
since our character is coming verticality
the ears of a bit of weight.
So they are pointing downward
and the momentum make them
also drag a bit backwards.
So when you enter the follow-through path
whenever the car car is contacting
with the ground and the
ears are moving forward.
Don't push them too far forward.
On some with those base poses,
I can slightly polish the curve.
Don't forget that you
are working on the cycle.
So you need the curve
to transition properly
from one cycle to the other.
This is why I was missing the keys.
I will also offset the motion
of the ears by one key frame
by duplicating the first
key frame onto frame one.
And then I rework my transition,
rotate my keys, duplicate them.
So that frame zero one
frame 10 are the same.
Do the same on the Z
rotation and Y rotation
even if the interference is very subtle.
I want to avoid any
glitches in the motion.
We need smooth transition
from one cycle to the other.
Then I worked on the eyes.
The idea is not to create an eye blink
as explained before.
You should not make your characters blink
during a cycle, because it
will look super repetitive.
It is to add subtle
follow through animation
by slightly closing the eyes
while the head is going up.
Here I don't care about
twinning since both eye I
will barely be seen at the same time.
So I can work on both
curve at the same time.
To tackle the nose motion
as I did for the ears.
Animating with with the
straightforward method.
Making it drag based on the
head motion, then make sure
that the curve transition
properly during the cycle.
And this is the final touch
to this climbing cycle animation.
To make sure that our
cycle is properly made.
I will display all the controllers curve
with the show hidden filter enabled.
Don't forget to press Alt+H
on top of this to make sure
that you unhide every curves.
Then I make sure that the
root channels are disabled
because they are not
using a cycle modifier,
but linear extrapolation.
Then they will select all
the keys on frame zero,
press V and switch the
Handle Type to free.
As explained before with this Handle Type
the current key frames
are no longer influenced
by the next or previous key frame.
So from there I can duplicate
them and move them on Frame 10
and I'm sure that the handle
orientation won't be changed.
This is a guarantee that your animation
will cycle perfectly.
This is the last animation
we have to create
of this character.
Congratulation if you got so far,
if not don't give up and
rework your animation.
The next video will be a time-lapse
of what we have just seen.
And then I will show
you all we can combine
all the action we have
created with our character
into the NLA editor.