- [Pierre] In this video,
we'll see how to append
or link our character
into a new Blender scene.
At the time I'm recording this video,
the linking system is
still under development.
So I will just give you the very basic
to be able to input your
character in a new scene
to create whatever shots you want.
You can use two different methods.
The first one will be
to append our assets.
I have a new Blender scene open.
I will get rid of everything,
go to File, Append.
From there, I can search
into the file folder
for the final squirrel file.
Blender files are containers,
and as soon as I will select it,
a bunch of folders will appear.
You can contender the
blend file as zipped file.
You will find a hierarchy of folders
containing all the assets you have
in your original Blender file.
Wherever it's your mesh
data, the scene options,
the materials, the world, et cetera.
And it also includes the collection.
So if I click my collection
and import my squirrel collection,
Blender will append
the squirrel collection
including the squeal
object and the armature.
And it will also append
everything used by this collection
whether it's the material of our squirrel
or the widget object I've
used to create the rig.
So I can select all of those
objects in the collection
and in the 3D viewport,
press X to delete them.
From there I can use the rig
and the squirrel character,
as we will do, in the original file.
If I open the action editor now,
Blender has imported the
run cycle only animation
because it was the one
that was used in the file.
Since all the action were
not assigned to the armature
on the origin file, they were not used
and hence not imported.
So I can go to File and Append again
and browse for the action
in our squirrel file.
And I can choose whatever
action I want to import.
Now I can find them in my action library
but they have no users.
So remember, if you want to keep them
while saving and closing your file,
you need to add a fake user.
So basically, appending an asset
is like copy and pasting
it from another file.
Let's now have a look to linking.
In an empty Blender file,
I will go to File, Link and
browse for my original file.
Go into the collection
and link the collection.
I get something pretty close
to what we had when I've
appended the collection.
I can see my squirrel, I can see the rig,
when I go into preview mode
to material seems to work.
In the action editor,
there seems to be the
animation in the library.
The main difference we can here
is that our characters seems
to be attached to an empty
and it's currently an empty object.
And this empty object
is currently instancing
the collection of our squirrel.
So it's not an independent
copy of the collection
but currently some kind of a clone
where I can't edit in, I only
have access to object mode.
And it's the same for the action.
If I unfold it,
you can see that the key
frame are not exposed
and I can't modify them.
To be able to access our rig,
we need to go into the collection
and find our collection under
the collection instance.
This little chain icon is here to tell us
this is a linked data.
Right click on it and under ID data,
go to add library override hierarchy.
It has created a new
collection called Squirrel
with a new icon showing a
chain across by an arrow.
Those are still a linked asset,
but we can now access our squirrel object
and also our squirrel armature.
So I can get rid of my squirrel instance.
The cool thing is that I
can now go into pause mode
onto my armature and they
can manipulate my character
as we will do in your original file.
But if I want to edit
my character, I can't.
Blender will output an error message
because I can't did the data of my object
nor the data of the mesh.
We can see that the data are grayed out.
So basically, they don't
belong to this Blender file
but to another Blender file.
So we can use those data,
but we can't modify them.
And it's the same with the armature,
I can't go into edit mode.
And it's also the same
with animation data,
we can't edit the current animation.
But since we can access our rig
we can create new animation if we want.
And the cool thing
is that we can make the
current animation local
so I can import all the link an animation
we have made previously,
make it local So is that
it's currently a copy
of the animation and we
can modify it at will.
To make it local, just select the action
and click on the chain.
It will become a local action,
or you can simply duplicate the action
and it will create a local action
that is exactly the
same as the linked one.
The big benefit of used linked assets
is that if the asset gets
modified in the original file,
it will be updated in our scene.
To do so, I just need to
go in your original file,
modify the color of the
character for example,
or its shape, save it.
Then in the Blender
file where we are using
those linked data, We can
save this file for example,
and just revert it or reload it
so that it will update
all the linked data.
So while, as animators,
we want to be able to create
a new animation, which we can,
we may not want to mess up with
the rig all with the object.
And if in the meantime,
the character artist is
updating our character,
Whenever we go back to the
scene to continue on animating
it will update automatically.
So using linked asset is
super powerful in production.
To summarize, we have seen
that when we append data
from one Blender file to another,
it creates an original copy,
it's like using copy and paste.
When we link asset it will
currently create an empty object
with an instance of the asset.
To be able to use those assets
we need to create a library override.
The big benefit of library override
is that we can use the
data from those assets
but we can't edit them, so
they are kind of protected.
And whenever the source
file is getting updated
our current file will be updated too,
making it perfect for team work.
So using a linked asset library
is perfect for teamwork
or large-scale projects.