In this video, we are
going to use the constraint
We've just seen before
to animate to different
parts of the robot character
using the base motion
we have created before.
To do so we will use a method
called space switching.
This is an often overlooked technique
but it is so powerful.
I've been introduced to this
technique and learned a lot
of things through the
Animation Sherpa course
by Richard Lico.
He's one of the coolest person I know.
And beyond that, he's one
of the best animators
in the game industry.
I will just show you the
very basic of space switching
but if you enjoy it
and get comfortable with
this animation course,
I truly advise you to take his
animation course afterward.
So let's start with a simple
up and down animation.
What I'd like to do is
make bone B react to bone
A having a bit of overlapping animation.
And instead of doing it by hand
as we did for the bouncing
ball or our scleral character
we will use constraints.
DID is to source the motion
of bone B in the work space
and slightly offset it in time.
Don't worry.
This will make sense in a few seconds.
Let's select a bone B press shift S
and snap the cursor to it.
Let's switch to object mode and add an MT.
We wanted the MT to behave
exactly as bone B to
do so I will select the MT,
go to the constraint panel
add a copy location panel
and source the armature.
Then I will select the bone B.
Now our MT is following
the bone B in space.
It is coping it's location in ward space
and I can no longer move
it, but we don't have
any animation information
we can play with,
the graph editor is empty.
So what we need to do is to
comfort the current motion
of the MT that is due
to the constraint in an actual animation.
And we can do this through baking.
To do so let's just have our MT selected
press F3 and search for bake.
We will choose the first one
object animation, bake action.
The bake action panel will open.
Here we can set the length of the action
we want to bake from
frame zero to frame 25.
I always used visual keying,
so that I'm sure that all
constraints are applied
when writing the action,
and we want to get rid of the constraints.
So I will enable clear constraints.
I won't choose override current action
since our MT don't have any action yet.
As I press okay Blender will
get free of the constraint
and I do now have an action
input into my graph editor.
If I played the animation, I can see
that the MT is kind of following bone B
but it's no longer constrained to it.
It's animation is just similar as bone B.
I will clean up the channel I don't need,
and keep this delocation on.
Now we have data.
We can edit.
We can offset the key frame or edit them.
And since those animation
data are assigned
to a single object, they
are using world space.
While bone B has no motion
in its local space, it is not animated.
It's just following bone A,
our MT does have an animation
but it is visually doing exactly
the same thing as bone B.
Now to see the power of space switching
let's select our MT.
In the curve, press shift
E add a cyclic modifier.
You find now select all the keys
press G and X and offset
them a bit in time.
You can see that now the
MT seems to have a formal
through animation compared to bone A.
So if I now select my armature
going to pose modes like bone B.
We can access the bone constraint.
So be very careful.
We are not constraining the
armature object, but the bone.
So we need to go into the bone constraint
not the object constraint.
From there,
we can add a copy location constraint
and then source the MT.
Now bone B will follow the motion
or the location of the MT.
From there, we can press
F3 and search for bake
or in my case, I've added
the bake action functionality
to my quick favorite so I can press
the Q key to access it.
I will use the same option
visual keying and clear constraint
and I will add overwrite current action.
Now bone B is no longer a constraint
but it's following the
same motion as the MT.
We can now get rid of MT and
shape the curves of bone B.
All channels have been written
but only the Z axis channel
is interesting for us.
You have just performed your
first space switching exercise.
Let's now see what we can
do with copy rotation.
In the example file, you
will find a second collection
with the copier rotation example.
It's a simple chain of three bones.
With bone A being animated.
It's a simple backend for
rotation on its X axis.
Bone B and C are simple
children without any animation.
Let's go back into object mode
and add two MTs.
For the sake of presentation,
I will add on the first MT a
copy, transform from bone B.
Go to the constraint,
add the copy transform.
Source the second armature and bone B.
Now our MT is snapped onto
bone B for the second MT.
I will add a simple copy
rotation and so it's
the same armature and bone C.
The first MT is now coping
both the location and
the rotation of bone B.
But in the end, what is interesting for us
is only the rotation.
If I was to isolate the
motion of the first MTs
that is also copying the location,
he will be rotating as
the one above, but it
can be a bit confusing to see
only the rotation of the MT
whenever the bones are currently childs
of another one and their
location is also changing.
But in this case, we will
only affect their rotation.
So I will switch to a
simple copier rotation
and so it's bone B.
And I will select both
MT, press my Q shortcut
and bake the action.
Now both the MTs have
lost their constraint
but we have animation that.
So we can now use those
two MTs to constraint
bone B and bone C.
But first let's make sure
that we have all the curves selected
for both MTs, press
shift E and make cycle.
Now let's select the armature
go into pose mode, select bone B,
go to the constraint panel,
add a copy rotation constraint
and source the first MT.
Big mistake here.
We've added the constraint
on to the object
as explained before we need
to use bone constraints.
So let's add the copy rotation source
the first MT select bone
C add the new constraint
and solves the second then from there,
when we played the animation
nothing changed since those
two bones copying the rotation
of something that was coping
their rotation previously.
But if I now offset to curve
of the first empty by one or two frames,
you can see the chain of bones changing.
And if I now also offset the second MT
by three or four frame,
I will get an overlapping
motion of my whole chain.
So the idea is to offset
by one or two frame,
the first MT,
then the next one by one
or two additional frame.
So three to four frames
and we'd get our
overlapping motion for free.
From there, we can select the armature
go back into pause mode,
select both constraint bone,
and bake the action and choose
overwrite current action.
And we can get rid of MTs.
And then we have our animation done.
Let's see a first example.
We've aimed space.
I have the sweeping motion,
but I don't want B and C to get
through this plane to create
the trucking constraint.
We need first to add a couple of MTs.
And then to those MTs
we will add a copy transform
so that they follow each bone.
So I will source bone B
for the first one and bone C
for the second one this way
both MTs are perfectly aligned with each
of their targets now to be able to get rid
of the constraint, but
keep those transform.
We can press control A and
choose visual transform.
I will do this for
both MT and get rid of their constraints.
But the cool thing is that now
they are transformed channel
as the same transformation
as bone B and bone C, but in ward space.
So if I go into my MTs
properties editor and switch
to arrows as a way to display them,
you will see that there are now aligned
with bone B and bone C.
They are sharing both the same orientation
and position in ward space.
We now need to offset them.
So I will switch the pivot
point to local with both
of them selected press G
and moved them on the Y axis
so that they are still
align with bone B and C,
but they are further away
on their local Y axis.
Now for them to follow
the motion of bone B and C
I need to make them become
child of those boards.
And we can use a new constraint such
as the child of constraint.
It's a very handy constraint
that will make the owner behave
as if it was a child of the target,
as a target let's source the armature.
And then bone B, we can
see that the MT got offset
just click set, inverse
to reset its position.
And let's repeat the process
with bone C and the second MT,
solve the armature.
Choose bone C and click set inverse.
Now, if we play our animation,
we can see both those MTs.
Following both bones,
let's select both MTs
and bake the action or bake the animation.
As before, whenever we
are baking the action,
we can choose to remove the constraint
and we can see our MTs
still following the motion
but now they do have an emission data.
We don't need any rotation or scale here
so we can get treated of the
rotation and scale curve.
You don't need to do it.
It's just to keep the
graffiti top cleaner.
Now, go back on the armature in post mode
go to the bone's constraint
select dumped truck constraint
and source the first MT.
Then repeat the process with bone C,
add dump truck constraint
and source the second MT.
When we played the animation as usual
nothing special happened, but
if I select the first MT press shift E to
make all the curve cyclic
and then offset them
by one or two frame, we can
see our bone chain offset.
And if I repeat the
process with the second MT,
but offset it by two frame.
Now you can see the chain
animated with a bit of overlap.
It seems
that the make cycle function
didn't work on this curve.
So I will fix this.
Now, if I want my chain to avoid
getting through or clipping
with the plane we have
created, I can simply work
on the curves or the animation
of the different MTs.
So I will select the first MT,
and work on it's Z location curve.
I will try to spot the key
where it goes under the ground
and I will select the key
and offset it a bit on the
Y axis in the graffiti.
It also is that it gets a little
we then go further whenever
it's leaving the ground
and I will duplicate the frame
I've just adjust on top of this one.
Those two keys represent our ground level
and I can get rid
of any keys that goes under these labels.
I can now repeat the process
with the second MT isolate to see location
curve spot, the moment
where it goes on the ground
then align its position with the ground.
Go even further duplicate the key frame
and get rid of any keys
that are under this label.
And when I played the animation now,
it seems that this whipping
motion is stuck to the ground.
Then as usual, we can go back
onto our bone chain and bake the action.
And if there are any
glitches in the animation,
you can remove a couple
of frames to get a smooth transition.
Using aim space is a
super powerful workflow.
Don't worry if you get
to be close to at first
we will repeat this process a lot of time
on the robot and you will
get very familiar with it.
Now, in the last example,
we will see all we can combine a
both the copy location
or location switch with this in space.
To do so I've created another armature
with another animation.
It's a simple up and down motion,
with have a little bounce,
so it's pretty close
to what we have between the body
and the cannon of our robot.
We will start with the location offset
with my bone B selected.
I will press shift S to snap the cursor
to it and add an MT.
To this MT I will add a
copy location constraint
sourcing the armature and the bone B.
Now the MT is following the motion
of the bone B in ward space.
I can press my Q key to get
to my quick favorite and bake the action.
I can get rid of all the curve,
but the Z location curve.
Press shift E and add a cyclic modifier.
From there I can slightly
offset the curve in time
by one or two frames to get
a nice overlap in motion.
I will then select back my armature,
go into pose mode
go into the bone constraint,
add a copy location,
so it's the MT and now bone B,
get this overlapping motion.
I can press Q and bake the action.
I won't delete the MT
because we will need it to
currently create the aim space constraint.
So the first thing to do is
to align the MT on the bone.
So let's add a copy transform concentrate
to the MT and source
as a target to bone B.
Let's press control A and
apply the visual transform.
We can get rid of the
copy, transform constraint.
And if we want, we can go
to the MT option and
switch to arrows to see
that it is oriented the
same way as the bone.
I will offset it along its local Y axis.
And now we need to add a child
of constraint to it, sourcing the bone B.
Click set inverse to reset its position.
And it's now following the motion
of bone B as if it was a child of it.
Let's bake this animation.
We can cleave the curve if we want,
getting rid of the curve
that doesn't have any animation.
Then press shift E and make
the current curve cycle.
Then we can use E to
constraint the bone B,
using a dump truck constraint.
If we now select back the MT,
an offset it's curved in time
we will have a bit of follow through
animation in the rotation.
So we have offset the motion
of the bone B using a location offset
and now also using a
dump truck constraint.
The cool thing about the
dump truck constraint is
that it's very easy to smooth a curve.
If, for example, I don't
want that much bounce
onto my bone B
and I want a smooth transition
as if it was very heavy.
I can get rid
of some key frames offset
to beat the lower key
and it will still follow
the original motion
of the bone B location wise.
So the base of the bone is
still have pretty crispy
and sharp bones while it's steep,
that is pointing
to what the target or the MT
get a smooth sort of motion.
The last thing we haven't seen
regarding any constraint is
that we can reduce the
interference of the constraint.
If I want to reduce the amplitude
of the rotation of the bone B.
It would have worked the same
with any other influence,
such as the location constraint
the bounce would be the same
but with a lower amplitude.
From there, we can bake
the current action on
to the bone B.
Don't worry if you're a bit lost at first
just try to redo the
exercise you've just seen.
We will repeat this a
lot through this chapter.
So you will get familiar
with this technique very fast
Learning those techniques
will become a huge time saver
for you later in the course.
To summarize,
we have seen that we can use constraint
and animation baking to source
data from a specific motion
and transferred them on to another bone
or another object.
We can use copy location
and copy rotation to create nice follow
through animation with ease.
We can have even more control
upon rotation of the target
using tracking constraint
such as dumped truck constraint.
We can use multiple constraint
to create complex mechanism
in a few clicks.
And finally, we can use the influence
of the different constraint to add more
or less amplitude to the
motion we are creating.