- [Instructor] In this video,
we will continue on using space switching
to finish the animation of our character.
I will slightly speed up the video
since it's going to be
very repetitive based
on what we have done just before.
We will start with the antenna.
They can only rotate on one axis
and they can't move.
So we will directly use
a tracking constraint.
First, we need to align our empty,
so we add a copy transform.
We source one of the antenna,
apply the visual transform,
get rid of the constraint
and then offset the empty
on the y-axis.
Then add to it a child of constraint,
source the rig and source
one of the antenna,
click the set inverse
and bake the animation.
From there, select the first antenna,
add a locked track
constraint, source the empty.
The track axis is positive y
and we want to rotate around the x-axis.
From there, we can get rid of
all the undesired channels.
Make the Z location curve cycling
and offset it by a couple of frames.
Then you can play on the
influence of the constraint
if you want to reduce the
amplitude of the motion.
Remember that offsetting the curve
will change the timing
and changing the influence
of the constraint
will change the spacing or
the amplitude of the motion.
From there, we can bake
the action onto the bone,
get rid of the useless transform channels
and since both antennas
were originally aligned,
we can directly constraint the big antenna
with the empty.
Just go back into pose
mode on to the armature,
select the antenna, go
into the bone constraint,
add a locked track constraint,
source the empty, track with y,
rotate along x and check the animation.
Since this antenna is slightly bigger,
it will have a bit more motion
and I've also decided to
offset the empty curve
by one additional frame.
This way, the big antenna will
be slightly delayed compared
to the motion of the small antenna.
And we will have a more
interesting motion.
Then I've baked the action
and cleaned my curve.
Now that the antennas are done,
I will unhide all the controllers,
select my visibility property bone
and display the arms
and we will work on both arms.
The idea is to input a
slight rotation delay
on the shoulders of the robot.
To do so, we will again use aim space
and a locked track constraint.
I will first align my empty
by adding to it a copy
transform constraint.
To work a little faster,
I've just copied the name
of the arm controller.
This way, when I'm adding
the copy transform constraint
to the empty, I can source the rig
and then just paste the
name in the bone field.
As the empty is now aligned
with the arm controller,
I will apply the visual transform,
then get rid of its constraint
and offset it on the x-axis on the side.
Then as usual, I will add
a child of constraint,
source the armature, then the arm.r,
click the set inverse
to reset the position
and bake the action.
I will get rid of the useless curve
and then for the remaining one,
I will make them cycle,
pressing Shift + E, click make cyclic.
Then we will get back to our controller,
go to the bone constraint
and we need to add a locked
track constraint pointing
toward the negative x-axis and
rotating around the y-axis.
So in the constraint, I
will source the empty,
choose the track axis minus X
and choose the locked axis y-axis.
Now I believe that you
do know the process.
Whenever I move the empty,
the arm will follow.
So I can offset the
animation curve of the empty
and then bake back the motion.
Don't hesitate to play a bit
with the animation curve of the empty.
If you scale it on the y-axis
using the bounding box,
you will increase the
amplitude of the motion.
Don't hesitate to experiment again.
If you fail, you just
need to rebake the motion.
So as I'm happy with the result,
I will bake the action onto
the arm right controller,
get rid of the transform channels
that are useless and I
will repeat the process
on the left arm
and also the connection
between the rocket launcher
and the left arm.
So I will leave you there
with a little time lapse
and we'll go ahead at 7:54.
(tranquil music)
Now we can work on the mini gun.
It has already a track mechanism.
So we can go ahead with
a simple copy location
of the empty, source the mini gun target
and bake the motion.
As the action is baked on the empty,
I will select the mini gun controller,
add a copy location constraint
and source the empty.
As we did for the head,
I'd like to remove a bit
of the bounce we have
on the Z location axis
for the mini gun
because it looked like
it's not very controlled
by the robot.
So having a bit of
follow-through motion is okay
but too much make it looks
like it's very clanky
and not a very reliable weapon.
So what I'm doing, I'm first
smoothing the Z location curve
of the empty.
Getting rid of the bumps.
And since we have two up and
down motion over the 72 frame,
I can work on half of this curve
and then remove the second half.
The cyclic modifier will take care
of repeating the curve seamlessly.
So what you need to understand
is the time you will
save using this method
for this kind of motion.
We will use space switching
later in the course
to smooth some animation
but for this kind of robotic motion,
that's so handy.
I will repeat the process
on the X location curve
to kind of remove a bit of the
noise we have in the motion.
So this time, I will have
to work on the whole curve
because the left to left motion uses
the 72 frame of the whole
cycle to be performed.
The idea is just to get rid
of the few glitches we have on the curve.
What is so powerful about aim space
and this technique
is that even if the root of the mini gun,
the point where it is
attached is very shaky
because we add a lot of
noise and secondary motion,
if we have a smooth motion of the target,
then the tip of the gun will
have a very smooth motion
and so you can create very
complex animation with ease
while that will be almost impossible
to counter animate in a classic fashion.
For the rocket launcher cap motion,
I will simply use a
locked track constraint.
It's gonna be the usual process,
so I will repeat it for you.
First, we need to add a
copy transform to the empty,
apply the visual transform,
get rid of the constraint,
offset it, in this case, on the y-axis,
add a child of constraint.
As a target, choose the armature
and the cap controller, set inverse
and then bake the action.
Get rid of the useless curve.
Again, you don't need to do it.
I prefer to do it for
demonstration purpose.
Then onto the controller,
add a locked track constraint.
From there, I get back onto the empty
and make the Z curve cycling.
Offset it in time and see happened.
The only little difference here
is that our controller
has already a constraint
that belong to the rig.
So this time when I will bake the action,
I will uncheck the clear constraint box.
It will bake the action as usual
but now I can manually get rid
of the locked track constraint
without losing the original constraint
that has been put there
by your lovely rigger.
The last step is to work
on our artillery piece,
so using the visibility bone,
I will enable the
visibility of the artillery.
It can move up and down and rotate a bit.
So what we will do is
that we will first use
our copy location constraint
to create the up and down
follow-through motion
and then a tracking constraint
to get the rotation.
With my empty selected,
I've added a copy location constraint.
I've sourced the armature,
then sourced the
artillery pivot controller
and baked the action.
We can then reverse the constraint,
meaning that I will select the controller,
add a copy location constraint
and source the empty.
Now I feel like I've repeated this enough
but I will go ahead either way.
I will slightly offset
the Z location curve
just after I've made it cycling.
I like the result,
so I will bake this action
onto the controller.
So I need to select my armature,
select the controller, click bake action
and this time, I can get
rid of the constraint
by checking the clear constraint option.
Let's now work in aim space.
So I will select back the empty,
add to it a copy transform constraint
to align it with the controller
of the artillery piece.
Then as usual, I will
apply the visual transform,
get rid of the constraint
and offset it on the y-axis.
Then we need to add a child of constraint,
source the armature, source
the artillery pivot controller,
click the set inverse to rest the position
and bake the action.
Then I need to use a
locked track constraint
onto the artillery
since it can only rotate around its x-axis
and the forward axis will be -y
and the rotation axis will be x.
From there, I will
repeat the process I did
on the mini gun.
I want to show that this piece
of artillery is very heavy.
So I don't want too much glitches
and too much bounces onto its animation.
Since we are using the up and down motion,
we can work on half of the curve
and then what I will do
is that I will remove
as much keys as needed to smooth the curve
and get a very smooth motion of the tip
of the artillery cannon.
Again and again don't
hesitate to remove keys.
Don't hesitate to fail
because you can just rebake the action
and start over again.
That's very fast.
It's a very iterative process
until you get to the results you want
and that's a very easy process.
So in a way, that's very creative.
What is super interesting about this piece
is again the root or the pace
of the artillery is shaking a lot
while the tip of the artillery
will be moving in a smoother fashion.
This bring a lot of
texture to your animation.
And while it can be very subtle,
all those little variation
in the motion of your character
will make this robot believable.
And while it's a piece of machinery,
it's also a way to put
life into this character.
What makes it alive
is that this robot is
communicating something.
Weight, strength, power,
that's some kind of dreadful
character we have here.
So as we are almost done
with this animation,
take the time to watch it entirely.
I feel like the head
motion is a bit too strong.
So what I can do now is simply
take the head controller
and reduce the amplitude
of the curve I want.
In this case, I feel like
the up and down motion
is a bit too strong.
So I will head up to the Z location curve
and I can see that my 2D cursor
is currently aligned with the value zero,
which means no motion.
So I can switch to the 2D cursor pivot
and scale the curve down on the y-axis
and it will reduce the amplitude
of the up and down motion of the head.
And since we've baked all the motion
of all the other parts
in their local space
and they are kind of
attached one to the other,
whenever we modify one piece in this way,
the other follow.
So if I want, I can select
the cap of the rocket launcher
and increase the amplitude of the rotation
and get more motion.
I can also offset the whole curve
on the y-axis and change the
whole orientation of the cap.
And here we are, in a very short time,
we were able to animate
this full character
with a lot of variety, texture
and interesting motions.