- In this video, we will
quickly create the foot roll.
Meaning that we will
input a bit of rotation
in the foot and slightly
adjust the whole motion.
This is going to be
pretty straightforward.
I will select the foot
roll controllers that is
in the back of the foot.
I will first select the correct controller
the one I'm working on,
and I will rotate it a bit forward.
As the foot is kind of under the torso.
It's tough to raise
during the passing pose.
From there, I can go a few frame before,
and I will cancel the rotation
by pressing Alt + R in the 3D view.
From there, I will go
forward into the animation
to the contacting pose.
I will cancel the
rotation of the controller
and then I will rotate it backward
so that the heel is currently
touching the ground, first.
As you can see those rotation
from the side view only
affect the X rotation channel
of this controller.
I will flatten the foot, couple of frame
after the contact pose
by pressing Alt + R in the 3D view.
When the heel touch the ground
the foot get flat pretty fast.
It's now refined a bit to curve.
I will slightly offset the beginning
of the raising of the heel to frame 16,
and I will make it lean
forward a little more
on frame 43 so that we have some dragging
of the front toes while
the foot is moving forward.
This will serve as our base motion.
And from there, I will just adjust
the amplitude of the curve,
making the contacting pose a bit wider.
Then, I will adjust the
roll of the foot forward.
So, I will slightly
increase frame 43 amplitude.
So that the food is bending
backward a little more.
I am basically slightly pushing the poles
by pushing those curves up
by contrasting the curve,
as we have seen just before.
Now, I'd like a bit of a kicking motion
whenever the foot is
reaching its forward position
by simply duplicating the extreme key down
and offsetting it back
by a couple of frame.
It's a bit like when
we are holding the foot
up in the air before
it touches the ground.
It brings a bit of contrast.
It make it a little more mechanical.
From there, it's just a
matter of tweaking the curve
Can spend your whole lifetime
adjusting those curve
without getting a perfect motion.
But with a couple of adjustment
and a bit of dragging,
we can get a satisfying motion.
Here, I feel like the foot
is too close to torso,
so I will select my torso controller
and offset the whole D curve
on the y-axis in the graphic (indistinct).
This is one of the cool thing
about this method is that we can play
with the different channels
to adjust the animation.
I have a slight clipping between the torso
and the thigh that I will
probably fix later on.
If needed, you can also
adjust the foot position
and the timing whenever
it's falling compared
to the body motion.
Here, I'm slightly offsetting the timing
of the foot so that it
cleanse slightly sooner.
And so that then the torso is falling.
So this is the kind
of thing I will continue
on tweaking during the animation.
The idea is to get the torso route right,
and the feet right before going on.
In the next video, we
will animate the toes.