- [Instructor] This is the last video
to create the base motion of our robot
where we will add some side to side motion
to the torso and the
beat of hips rotation.
So I'm starting with the root top.
So controller selected and the
X location curve available.
The motion is pretty simple.
When the character is
raising one of its leg
and putting its weight onto the other,
its whole body will shift to towards
the foots that is in
contact with the ground.
So basically if we have
a look to the curve
the weight will shift to
what the robot left side
until frame 14 and which
is the passing pose
where the right leg is in
the middle of the robot.
On frame 14 to frame 22, the
body will slightly move back
to the right by the
weight of the right foot.
And we have an acceleration
of the right foot contact the ground
and the whole body is falling down.
It's also shifting rapidly to
wild the new contacting foot
transferring it's weight
onto it's right leg.
Since we have a symmetrical cycle
we can then reproduce this
motion in the other way.
Again, there is not that much more to say
and to get this concept about
rhythm and weight shifting.
It's just a matter of
playing with the curve
to get the right momentum,
to get the right motion.
Then with this method,
the layer and method,
just try to keep your
curves as clean as possible.
Not adding too much key frames
especially if they are useless,
is that you can easily tweak
and adjust those values later on.
When you're happy with
the result, don't forget
to align the very first
key and the very last
so that you get a proper cycle.
To create the rotation motion of the hips,
I've used the same method.
I've started from the front view
working on the Y axis of the hips.
It's the left to right twisting motion.
When you are putting
your weight onto one leg
as you straighten this
leg, your hips will raise.
So the hips doesn't only react
to the weight of the body
but also to the contact
of the foot on the ground.
So we could think that they
are following the motion.
But they also lead the animation
since they are used to pull the foot up.
When the robot would be on one foot
the hips will tilt towards this foot.
And as the opposite foot
will leave the ground,
the hips will start rotating
towards the raising foot.
But still farther raising
the foot on the ground.
And as our robot character hit the ground
with the opposite foot, then
the hips will rapidly shift
to one, the foot that just enter
in contact with the ground.
And what I did is that
I had a little bounce
in the curve to create an hip shake
that make our robot who came
more clunky and robotic.
As we did before with the toes.
When they was done with that,
I worked on the rotation curve.
I kept it very simple,
just imaging the hips, pulling the foot.
So when the right foot is forward
and hit the ground into its contact pose,
the hips controller is rotating
towards the other foot.
And has reach it's extreme
pose a couple of frame before
because it's leading the
animation, pulling the feet.
So the hips rotate toward the
left to pull the right leg
and as the right foot contact
the ground, the hips has
already started rotating
the other way a little bit.
The next video will be a short time-lapse
showing you those steps.
I've just explained if needed.
And then we will see different techniques
on all to use the base motion.
We have created to add it
to the different parts of the robot.