- [Instructor] Welcome to chapter four.
In this chapter, we will
be using another technique
to animate the robot character we can see
in the second teaser of the course.
While in the previous chapter,
we have been blocking,
detailing the animation,
then going to spline and polish it,
in this chapter, we are going
to use the layered approach.
The idea is to pose the robot
and then directly work into spline
or using the graph editor
onto different part of the body.
We will start with the torso root motion,
creating the up and down
and then we will work onto
the feet of the character.
The idea is to animate the other part
of the character in reaction
of the previous part we will animate.
So I will animate the torso,
then the arms, reacting to
the motion of the torso.
In this chapter, we will
also learn the fundamentals
of space switching
and using constraint when animating.
With this method, we will be
able to use the base motion
of the torso and the legs
to drive the other parts of the robot,
creating very realistic
animation very easily.
We will use all those methods
to create this walk cycle,
an artillery shot with a cool recoil
and finally, combining the walk cycle
with a rocket shot.
This is a super exciting chapter
with a lot of technique
that we are going to use
later on in the course.
Let's get started.