- With the layered approach,
we focus on building the
motion channel by channel
The idea is not to go
through a blocking stage
then detailed blocking,
spinning, and polishing.
We will directly work
in the graph editor on specific
parts of the character.
We will start from the
root of the character
and in reaction, we will animate the legs.
This is the whole concept
about the layered approach.
We will first work on
the up and down motion
of the root of the torso
and in reaction the legs
and then the left to
right motion of the torso.
With the file opened and
the King set selected,
I've duplicated the action
and then will rename it: walk.
Will activate the fix user
to make sure we don't
lose what we are doing
and activate the auto key framing.
First controller will walk
with is the tussle route.
As for this scleral character,
it's the main controller of the torso.
So we start with selecting
the property's bone
and set to zero, the
follow arm properties.
This might be something we
will change along the way,
reset it to one or to zero,
depending on our needs.
First motion we will work on
is the up and down motion of the torso.
And we will work on
the Z location channel.
The goal is to focus on
one channel at a time.
So selecting the visibility
bone, I will hide everything
but the torso so that we can really focus
on the motion of the torso.
For this animation
I will work with a frame
rate of 30 frame per seconds.
You can stick to the 24
frame per second rhythm,
if you want.
It's a matter of personal preferences.
So normally like to work
at 30 frames per second
because I'm used to animate for games.
And a lot of movies are now set to 25
to 30 frame per seconds.
But we will cycle range of 30 frame,
in the end I've used a 36 frame
cycle for the up and down motion,
but you can choose to
do it faster or slower.
Here I want to create a very
slow pace and heavy walk cycle.
But you could do a run
cycle with the same method.
With my roots torso selected,
I will directly jump
into the graph editor.
The controller is aligned with world space
so we can work directly on the Z location.
I have an up and down motion
for both the left step and the right step.
So on the one whole work cycle,
the up and down motion will repeat twice.
I will arbitrary go to
frame five and raise about here.
The idea here is just to get
an extra key frame on our torso.
The motion will be pretty simple.
If we want to make our character heavy,
we need to make it raise pretty slowly
because it has to push a lot of weight
and whenever the torso is getting down
it will kind of fall pretty fast.
And we can build a pretty
strong overshoot to
communicate this weight.
And as I said, tall
I've inputted a very
slight up-and-down motion
on the few frame to create
some kind of vibration
or bones of the whole torso
as if the body was bouncing as
it touched its lowest position.
This will bring a pretty
clunky or robotic motion.
I will keep on showing
the Z location curve
so that you have a reference.
As any animation process,
it's a creative process,
so I wasn't planning on doing
this on 36 frame at first.
To be perfectly honest,
I wasn't knowing all
mini frame would take
an up-and-down motion.
It's just about playing the
animation, making sounds
with my mouse to feel the
weight of the character.
And in the end, a little
more than one second per step
looks slow enough to
communicate the weight
of the robot character.
A couples of details
regarding the curve shape.
At first, the character
is raising pretty fast
and when it's reaching its top position
it's slightly slowing down.
Then we have some kind of
plateau shape on the curve.
This will make the robot
hold a bit in the up position
for a few frames, and
it will kind of serve
as an anticipation before the fall.
Note that the curve is
not perfectly flat here.
I've slightly rotated the handle,
so that even if you took
still, it's still moving a bit.
This is a moving hold.
If you have a perfectly flat curve here
it won't look natural.
As your character will stop moving.
Here is my up and down
motion of the torso root.
In the next video, we
will add the foot motion.