- [Instructor] Before we get started,
let's have a look to the rig.
By default, the character
is presented with a MatCap
and the preview of the texture.
You can enter material preview mode
to see the robot at its best
but you should stay in showing mode
for animation performances.
(whoosh)
By default, you should have access
to the different rig layers.
If it's not the case,
open the text editor.
You should have the script open,
if it's not the case,
select it in the list
and press the play button.
Then select the rig
and go into pose mode.
The first thing to check is this eye icon.
It's a bone that holds
some custom properties.
The Bevel option allows us to re-enable
the Bevel modifier that is on the robot.
It will make it look a little better
but it will also increase
the number of polygon,
hence reducing the performances.
Activating the Bevel modifier
tend to triple the number of polygons.
Enabling the subdiv option,
will enabled the subdivision
modifier on the robot,
increasing the number of
faces to almost a million.
So it will largely slow down
your computer performances.
If I press the space bar and
try to play the animation,
even if our robot is not animated,
you can see the number of
frame per second dropping.
Note that those option only
effect the viewport display.
You don't need to re-enable them
if you want to render your animation.
Getting back onto this view property bone,
you can see that there are options to
mask the artillery piece, the legs,
and both the mini gun,
and the rocket launcher.
Just, as we add on the squirrel
character allows us to focus
on specific parts of the character.
Next to these bones,
we have another one that
is our properties bone.
It includes a lot of different properties
but they almost all do the same thing.
The first ones allow us to switch
between the forward kinematic
and inverse kinematics
for the right leg or the left leg.
By default, they are set
to inverse kinematics.
Moving the inverse kinematic controller
would allow us to animate the whole leg
exactly as we did with
our squirrel characters.
If we change the value to zero,
now the leg is moving in another position.
It will now follow the
forward kinematic controllers
that we can access
by activating the forward kinematic layer.
Now the leg is moving
using forward kinematic
and we can control each
segment separately.
We will be mostly animating
using inverse kinematic
so you can switch it back.
The next properties allows
up to enable or disable
the rotation follow of the
different parts of the robot.
By default,
the arms are following the
orientation of the body.
But if I disable this flow rotation,
you can see that now they stay
or (indistinct).
They don't follow the rotation
of the body anymore.
You will find the same option
for the artillery piece
and the head of the robot.
By default, the follow
rotation is disabled
but if I re-enable the
follow head rotation,
you can see that now the
head is leaning forward
and is aligned with the body.
The follow leg rotation will
only affect the leg behavior
whenever you are using forward kinematic.
This is pretty common when
using forward kinematic
for the arms or the leg
to isolate their rotation
from the hips rotation,
or the shoulder rotation.
The next option, mini gun speed,
will allow us to set
the speed of rotation of
the mini gun cannon so that
we don't need to animate
the rotation of the barrels.
The mini gun follow and the sensor follow,
allow us to isolate the targets
from both those items.
The mini gun and the sensor
will follow their own target.
And by default, those targets are parented
to the body of the robot.
If we disable or set to zero
the value of the follow option,
the target are no longer
following the motion of the body.
And so you can see the mini
gun adjusting its orientation
toward the aiming point.
And so does the sensor
on top of the robot.
(whoosh)
The controllers of the robot
are pretty straightforward.
The root bone allows us
to move the whole robot
the torso root allows us
to move the whole body.
Then you will find controllers
for the different parts.
All targets for the legs,
IK controllers,
allowing to move and rotate the feet.
On the back of the foot, you will find
a very useful controller that
allow us to perform steps
or rotation around the ball
and the heel of the foot.
When you rotate it from the
front view or on its Z axis,
you will get a nice contacting
left to right motion.
Both arms of controller,
the rocket launcher as a
door opening controller,
each body part as a separate controller as
on the body of this squirrel character.
Each rocket as its own controller
that allows us to move
them in space at will.
And they also have a secondary
controller that alow us
by a simple one axis
rotation to deploy the wings
of those rockets.
The antennas have a simple
one axis rotation control.
The artillery as a first controller
that allows us to create
the recoil motion.
And we also have a nigary
controller that allow us
a bit of up and down motion
and also to slightly rotate
the artillery back and forth.
So it's a pretty simple yet versatile rig.
Let's animate this beast.