- In this video, we are going
to animate the rocket shot.
The main difficulty is to isolate
the motion of the rocket
from the walk cycle.
Let's get started.
First thing I'm going to
do is to make sure that
our walk cycle is currently cycling.
So I will display all the bones.
I will go into the Graph Editor.
Click the Show Hidden option.
Press Alt+H to make sure that
all the curves are displayed
and then I will press
Shift+E and Make Cycle.
I will then set the end of my animation
to an arbitrary value of 400 frames
because I don't know yet
how long it will take
to the rocket to touch
or hit
the cube further away.
Now we have a looping walk cycle.
So let's go ahead and
work on the rocket shot.
(rockets whooshing)
The first thing we can do
is to display our rocket layer in the rig.
We will have a controller for our rocket.
I will select the very first
one on the top left corner.
And I will get rid of
all the key frames but the very first.
Then I will go on frame
40 and insert a key frame.
This is again, pretty arbitrary.
The idea is to set this key frame
as being the beginning of
the shooting animation.
It's a lot better to have a
few frames in the beginning
so that our brain can
analyze what's happening.
Like, the robot is
walking and then shooting.
It is if we were creating some staging
for this shooting animation.
Add a key frame on frame 40.
Now, using Local Space,
I will go on frame 50
and I will get the first rocket out,
moving it along it's Y-axis.
If we now frame our curve or zoom on it
we can see there is a repetition
because of the cyclic modifier we added
in the beginning of the video.
So I will select all my rocket curves,
press Shift+E
and choose Clear Cyclic.
We can see that all the
curves are straight and flat
while the Y-curve is
slightly bending downward.
We can hide all the curve, but the Y-curve
so that we can work on the forward motion
of the rocket while it's
getting out with ease.
We just scale up
the initial key frame handle
so that we get more easing
whenever the rockets
start to get out of the rocket launcher.
And then I will just go
to a further key frame
again, arbitrary
and move the rocket further away.
The idea here is not to build the motion
but to show you the current issue we have.
The rocket is a child
of the rocket launcher.
Hence it inherits any motion
from the rocket launcher.
So we will need to find a
way to isolate the rocket
from the rocket launcher.
We'll delete the last
key frame I have created
so that we just stick
with the two key frames
where the rocket is getting out
of the rocket launcher and stop.
I will rotate the tip of the curve handle
so that we don't have any
easing out of the rocket.
From there, we will need
to use space switching
to be able to animate the rocket.
So I will go back into Object Mode
and add an Empty.
In the Object Display option
I will make sure that it shows In Front.
(rockets whooshing)
The idea is to bake the
motion of the rocket
while it's getting out
of the rocket launcher,
on the Empty.
So on our Empty let's add a
Copy Transform Constraint.
Source the armature,
and then source the ROCKET-1 bone.
And when the Empty is constrained
we can bake the action,
choosing the Initial
Frame as being frame 0
and ending on the current
frame of frame 50.
We'll press Q to get
to my Quick Favorites.
Choose "Bake Action."
As usual, enable Visual Keying
and Clear Constraint and set.
You can check the Override Current Action,
even if there is no action for the Empty.
Blender will create one.
Set the Start Frame to 0
and the End Frame to 50.
We can get rid of the
Scale Transform Channels
since we won't be using them.
And if we now play the animation,
we can see the Empty following the rocket.
Now, the idea is to reverse the constraint
so that the rocket is
constrained by the Empty.
So I will select my rocket controller,
go to the Bone Constraint
add a Copy Transform Constraint
and solve the Empty.
And now the rocket is
following the Empty motion.
Since the Empty motion has the same motion
as the rocket initially
it will fall, but since the Empty is not
the child of the robot,
we can move the rocket freely
or we can move the Empty freely.
So now it's just a matter
of creating the animation
using the Empty.
What I want to do for this rocket launch
is to have it in two-time.
First, they get out of the rocket launcher
as if they were pushed away
and then they will fall.
The little wings will open
and then the rockets will fly away.
So what I've done is that
I've set a first key frame
where I want the rocket to kind of fall.
And then the next key frame
is where the rocket
will hit our cube shape.
Since it's a pretty simple motion
just work with pose extremes
as if you were animating
a regular character.
We just set the first extreme
which is the "down" pose of the rocket
and the next one
which is when it hits the target.
From there we will just tweak the curve
to get the right motion.
Again, now, it's a matter
of creative process.
If you want the rocket
to go straight forward
to the target, you can do it.
I do like the idea that the
rocket gets shot in two-time.
First, it gets out.
Then the wing opens
and then it goes toward the target.
I think it adds a more interesting
rhythm to the animation.
And while I'm recording this video
I'm planning to use them
to create the teaser
for the course.
And I want to launch three rockets
so that it will bring us even more rhythm.
I have the shot going in three parts.
The rockets gets out,
then it falls,
and then it flies away.
And I will kind of multiply that
three-times, using three rockets.
Animation-wise, what I did
is that there is a slight slowing down
on the Y-axis of the rocket,
so that it kind of floats
before the reactor of the rocket ignites.
And then it accelerates
on the Y-axis until the impact.
This is why I'm using vector handles
on the very last key frame
so that we are sure we don't get
any easing in the last position.
In the end, I spent most of the time
tweaking the rotation curve to get
the rocket pointing at the target.
While we could use Aim Space,
with a Tracking Constraint,
you could add an Empty
object onto the cube
and use it to add a Don't
Track Constraint on the Empty
that is used to manipulate the rocket.
That could save you a bit of time.
But in the end, this is not
a very complex animation.
We are manipulating only
one rotational axis.
So it's a good exercise
to do it by hand, too.
So I will let you there
until the end of the video.
You can double check the
curves on the example file,
but at this stage
you should be able to
animate this on your own.
Don't forget to then
get back to the rocket
and deploy the little wings
using the Rotation Controller.
I will see you in the next video
where we will shoot with
the artillery cannon.
(somber electronic music with
rising piano progression)
(music fades)