- It's now time to bring some details
to our feet by moving the toes.
Again, it's gonna be
pretty straightforward
since we already have the
base motion of our foot.
We'll first work on the
front toe controller,
and I will try to find the movement
the foot is leaving the ground
and duplicate the key Frame.
Dissuade the toe will
remain flat on the ground,
from Frame zero to Frame 30 foot.
I will set the end-all type two vector
for this new key frame.
Go a little further in the animation,
and simply rotate the toes backward
so that they will drag during this motion.
I will then adjust the end (indistinct)
of the first key frame,
so that it doesn't clip with the ground
whenever the foot is going backward.
Then I will adjust to dragging motion
as the foot is moving forward.
I want the toes to point
downward because of its weight,
but also because of the
forward motion of the foot.
She's the kind of motion we have practiced
with this key role.
Whenever we were moving the limps,
we were making the hands
and the feet dragging.
As we are done with this,
we can go forward to the compacting frame,
where we will make the toe raising.
As the foot fall down,
the toes are still dragging
or there is a full of full motion.
So there are pointing
up (indistinct) emphasis
the flap of the foot.
So as the foot is getting
flat on the ground,
I will make sure that the toes are almost
at their highest position.
And then two frame letters,
I will make the toes flat on the ground.
Here, I will slightly offset
the foot roll controller
by one frame at back.
I will then re-adjust
the toe extreme position
just before it hits
the ground to frame 60.
I will go to frame letter and
press Alt+ R in the 3D view,
to flatten the toe on the ground.
Whenever I create a contacting post,
I generally set the
end-all type two vector.
As the current motion,
is kind of stop brutally
as it hits the ground.
So there is no easing
before the curve gets flat.
(indistinct) tell that
will make the difference
is to create a slight bounce of the toe,
when it hits the ground.
To do so, I will duplicate
the current key frame,
and move it two to four frame later.
And we then duplicate the post key frame,
lower rate and put it in between.
This way, we have a more clunky motion,
and we finally get something
that looks like an animation for the foot.
It's indeed a robot,
but we are kind of briefing
life into it if you will.
From there, we can repeat the
process with the back toe.
Beware because these toe has two joint.
One at the base of the foot on the heel,
and one for the current back toe.
I will create a motion
for the first joint,
that really looks like the
front toe but in reverse.
And I will keep the motion pretty slight.
Whenever you are working
on a chain of bone,
we've Arrow Key,
the more you move the
roots to more the deep tip,
and the other controller we move
and it might look a bit too extreme.
So keep it subtle.
It's easier then to amplify
the motion if needed.
Remember that you have
to make the toe drugging,
so whenever the foot is moving forward,
each will point backward a little down.
And whenever the foot is falling down,
this will drag so it will raise.
I didn't input any bones
on the contact bones,
because it was a bit too much
since I will input a bit of bouncing,
on to the tip of the toe.
So on the curve, the back
to root is kind of phrasing
just before the contact pose,
and whenever to contact pose occur,
it will flatten on the ground.
So I have canceled in your rotation.
I've used a Vector and (indistinct)
because I don't want anything,
but I didn't input any bounds.
I did input the bones in
motion on the tip, the toes.
So on the next joint into the animation.
So I did animate the tip of the back toe,
as I did for the front
toe, making it drug,
so that we feel like there is
a bit of delay in its motion,
and then adding some bounds,
as it contacts the ground.
Be careful not to make it
clip through the ground.
When that was done,
I repeat the process
with the outer side toe.
And since the foot is
not tilting in space,
I could then simply copy the
curve of this outer side toe,
onto the inner side toe.
Again, nothing crazy here.
It's pretty simple.
So you will be able to watch me
kind of animating those
toes in the next video,
that will be a short time
lapse of this process.
As all the toes were animated,
the foot animation was done,
and we now need to copy
it onto the other foot.
To do so, it's very simple.
You just select all the
controllers from the left foot
we just animated.
Open the graph editor,
and press Alt+H to make sure that
all the curve are available.
Press A again to select them all,
Press Ctrl+C to copy those curves.
Then Select all the
right foot controllers.
Go on frame zero and press Ctrl+Shift+V.
Since our rig is symmetrical,
Blender will Paste the curve
taking care of the symmetry for us.
Now, both foot are moving
in the same fashion with the same rhythm.
We now just need to offset
the motion of the right foot
in time so that we get
an alternate motion.
To do so, simply select all the curve,
Press Shift+D and offset
them by the whole cycle.
In my case, 72 frames.
Then I will select again all the curve,
and I will offset them back in time
by half of the motion, 36 frames.
We now have both our feet motion.
Since I have now a better
vision of the motion,
I feel like the foot are two forward.
So what I will do is that
I will select both foot main controller,
isolate the Y Location
axis by inputting its name
in the Search bar, Select
all the available keys
for both to (indistinct)
location channels.
And then I will slightly offset them up
on the Y-Axis in the graph editor.
This will push both feet backward,
and it will look a little more natural.
From there, you can adjust the eighth
of the up-and-down motion by
simply offsetting dizzy curve.
You can also scale it on this Y-axis,
so that we'll have more up
and down motion if needed,
or if you scale it down
you will reduce the
bounciness of the motion.
From there, it's really a
matter of personal taste
and experience to make it look good
but you have the whole method.
Now we just need to get rid
of the unused key frame on the right foot.
To do so, we simply need to Select
all the controller of the right foots.
Go onto the Frame Zero,
Press I to insert a key
frame on all the channels
then Press V and set those
new key frame to Free.
From there we can get rid
off any previous key frame
and then, Select all those
key frame on Frame Zero.
Press Shift+D to duplicate them,
and move them on the very
last frame of our cycle.
Frame 72 for me.
Then I can get rid off all the key frame,
after this frame 72.
Our foot animation is done,
the next step,
will be to input some left to right motion
to the toss or root,
and animate a bit the feet.