- [Pierre] In this video,
we are going to create
the artillery shot animation.
Again, we will rely a lot
on the space switching
to achieve it.
We can start from our cling
action and duplicate it.
The idea is to have our robot standing
with its two feet planted in the ground.
I've renamed the action
and I will click the little shield icon
to make sure that I
won't lose the animation.
Since the rotation range of
the cannon is a bit limited,
I will also select the
head of the character
and slightly rotate it back.
The process is the same
as for the walk cycle.
I will first create a base motion
and then we will propagate
each using space switching.
The shot is a very fast action,
so I will jump on frame four
and I will pull back the recoil control.
What I noticed while playing the animation
is that it was repeating,
there is probably a cycling quantifier.
So I will select all the
keys of all the controllers
and press shift E and clear cyclic.
From there.
I will directly jump into the
graph editor and I we'll work
on the curve of the record controller.
Since it's kind of an instant motion
I will select the first
key frame of the recalling
controller and convert it to vector.
The idea is that the
controller is pushed back
at full speed
right at the beginning,
the moment where we shoot
With the artillery, it gets
Very fast to its extreme on frame four.
And then I will duplicate the
very first frame onto frame 10
so that the controller gets
back into its position.
Then I played the
animation a couple of time
and tweaked the curve.
In the end, I set the extreme on frame two
and reset the position of
the controller on frame seven
Played the animation a
couple of more time, and then
decided it was better
to sit in final position
on frame nine.
So we have the base motion of the Canon.
Now we need to move the root
of the torso of the robot to
keep the exercise simple.
I will just walk on the Y axis.
We've my torso root controller selected.
I will directly jump into
the graph editor and hide
everything but the Y location axis,
since the recall controller,
or Canon controller reach
it's extreme on frame two
I will take the very first
frame of the route controller
and duplicate it on frame two.
The ideas that the record
motion start when the Canon is
pushing the whole body back.
Now we can add a key frame on frame 10
and move the curve up so
that our character torso
is moving back.
Then I will reset the pose of
The character around frame 23.
Again, this is a creative process.
If you want, you can use other values.
I'm here to teach you in
the method, not all to
make this specific animation.
I will create a more
easing on the back position
by scaling the curve.
And I will make the first angle
to be vector because again
I don't want any easing into
the recoil, the recoil start
at full speed.
Then it eases into frame
10, and it finally gets back
with easing onto frame 23.
As I watch the motion, I feel
like the robot is a bit out
of balance, so I will
select the whole curve
and slightly offset it down.
But the character is positioned
more forward onto his feet.
When he's going to shoot,
it's important to watch out
for the center of gravity
of your character, so
that it looks balanced when shooting.
And so the shot looks more believable
(Wooshing Noises)
Before we start animating
the head of the character,
I will just add a very
slight rotation to the Canon.
In the end, we will use
also space switching to
add more emotion to the Canon
but the idea is just to have some kind
of passive motion or rate.
I don't think it's necessary
though, but it's very fast.
It's just one key frame on
frame four or five, to get a bit
of rotation back and switch
the first handle to vector.
Then I will dial the angle
by reducing the amplitude
of the curve and we are done
and we can jump onto the head controller.
In this video, we are
going to repeat a lot
of thing we have done
during the walk cycle
meaning that we will use a lot
of copy location and a lot of end space.
The only things that will change is
all we offset the curve in time.
Instead of creating a delay
we will make the curve move back
in time so that the head motion
occurs before the bud in motion, this way
we will fake the fact that
the motion is led by the head.
First let's work with the location of yet.
I've added an empty, I will make sure
that it's displayed in
front and on the armature
in the armature viewpoint
display, I will enable names
and axis it will just help us
identifying the bone with ease
Back on my empty, I
will add a copy location
as usual source our armature,
and then the head controller.
I will bake the action
For this specific animation,
I've used 30 frames on it.
Then get rid of the user's
curve, If you want a gain.
It doesn't matter.
DMT is following the add motion.
Let's now reverse the constraint
go to the head bone inputs mode
add to it a copy location,
constraint and source the empty.
We can now get back to
the empty and instead
of offsetting the curve to
the right filtering time
we'll offset to the left back in time.
And now the head moves before the torso.
I will offset it back by one key frame.
So is that there is a bit
of delay between the shot
and the head motion, but
the head motions still occur
before the torso root motion,
as I'm happy with the result
I will bake the action
onto the head, boom.
And now we can work on the head rotation
since the Canon is a child of the head
whenever the head will rotate,
the cannon will rotate too.
And I don't really want that
because the Canon was supposed
to lead the animation.
So what I will do is that I
will create an aim constraint
or tracking constraint for the gun
and we will keep this constraint
to the end of the animation
so that the gun will always
be pointing at the same target
while we are working on the
different part of the robot.
So you should know the process now
but I will repeat it either way
first, add a copy, transform
to the empty, then press control-A
and apply the visual transform.
From there, We can get treated of the copy
transform constraint and move
the empty on its local Y axis.
Then we need to make it a
child of the artillery pivot
so that it will follow its current motion.
So I will select it.
Use a child of constraint,
source the armature
and then the Archer re-pivot controller.
We will click setting verse
to reset it's position
and bake it's action.
Now I will select the
artillery pivot controller
and I will add to it a
locked truck constraint
targeting the empty.
The gun is pointing
On it's minus Y axis
and rotating around its X axis.
As soon as I saw the empty, the gun
We'll always aim an empty
and whatever the motion
of the head cannon will point a DMT.
We've the limitation of the hydraulics
and the rotation angle of its controller.
So we can keep this constraint
and now work on the rotation of the head.
Since this is something
we have done a lot of time
I will slightly speed up the video.
I've created a new empty
I will add to it, a copy transform.
Source the armature then source
the head controller apply
its visual transform and get
treated of the constraint.
But the trick here is that I
won't be upsetting it forward
on the y-axis since we don't
have any upended motion
but I will offset to down.
As the body moves back and
forth, it's better to get
to this pendulum motion based
on the Z axis from there
the process will be exactly
the same as what we did before.
During the walk cycle.
First, I will add a child
of constraint to DMT target the armature.
Then you hit controller set inverse.
They take the action, then
select the head controller
add a dumped truck, constraint
and target the empty.
But this time I will use the minus Z axis
of the head controller
instead of the minus Y axis.
And now I can offset the curve in time.
So as usual, you have to
experiment, try offsetting
to the left so that the rotation will
occur before the translation of the head
or try the other way, offset
the curves to the right
so that the head rotation
is based on its translation.
Plus the position of the target, our empty
with variants under or,
upon the head will kind
of change the behavior
sometimes, delaying the curve.
We'll make the head kind of moving
before it's current translation.
Why if DMT was upon the
head and we were targeting
toward the positive Z
axis in the constraint
offsetting the curve the
same way we'll kind of
reversed the head rotation.
So you have to experiment the
reason, no like golden method
try offsetting the curve left to right
check out the behavior of the controller.
And then just guess all you want to
work the final touch here
was to edit the empty curve
to get a slight overshoot
of the head rotation
and this loose motion of the rotation.
So I've used the baked curve as a guide.
And then I reworked the
curve by removing most
of the key frame and
smoothing the curve shape
as we did during the walk cycle.
So as usual, it's a matter
of spending time on to your animation
but the location motion of
the head is the snap here.
And then since the rotation
is kind of reacting to this
I've made it quite smooth.
Now you also want to show
that this robot is made to
shoot with the artillery.
So I bring a bit
of smoothness to the motion
showing more control than
If it was wobbling all around.
From there, I've repeated the process
for the body controller, the
arms, the hips, et cetera
this way I've slowly
propagated the recoil motion
from the gunshot on to the
whole body of the character.
The final touch was to add a
very subtle up and down motion
to one of the feet as if
the robot was pushed back
by the recoil and kind of
losing a bit of balance.
I've made this motion only
on one foot to break the
twinning in the animation.
and make it look more natural
more random in a way to do so.
I've just walked a beat
on the Hill controller
and then animated the
front two in reaction.
This is very simple.
So I will let you there
with this animation.
And in the next video
you will find a slow paced
time-lapse of the whole process.
This is something we have repeated a lot
in the previous videos.
So if you don't feel comfortable
do not hesitate to rewatch
the work cycle process
as we are using exactly the same process.
And don't forget to check
out the axis I'm using
depending on the controller, I'm moving
for these specific animation
regarding the body controllers.
I was mostly using in space, downward
and space downward on the minus Z axis
so that I can source the back
and forth motion of the body.