- [Instructor] In this video,
we will have a quick look
to the Wiggle bone add-on.
Activated, the add-on gives
you access to the wiggle option
that has to be activated pair bones.
To get the add-on, you
can simply check the link
into the documentation of the course.
A latest version of the
Wiggle bone add-on by Steve.
Then in blender, simply install it
by going into Edit preferences.
Add-on, click the install button.
Browse and find the .pi file
of the wiggle bone add-on.
Click the install button
and then make sure
that the Wiggle bone add-on is activated.
There is another add-on
called the Spring Bone add-ons
by Artel, creator of Auto Rick Pro.
But the add-on is still experimental
and it only works on
chains of parented bones.
For this demonstration,
I provided one file with
two different animation.
The sliding and rotating
animation called whipping action
and a second action with some jumpy bones.
Only the lower bone in the
chain is currently animated.
Let's select the free bones in the chain
that are the children of this one
and activate the Wiggle
bone add-on on this
and press the play button.
By default, the reset on
loop option is activated.
To enable or disable this option,
you do it for all the bones at once.
When using the add-on on the cycle,
it's better to disable the option
so that the simulation continue at runtime
and we don't get the popping frame
at the beginning of the motion.
Wiggle bone add-on simulate
physical behavior on your bone.
We can access different properties
of those physical behavior
through the panel whose
properties are editable.
Pair bone, let's see in detail
the different properties.
The amplitude rotation
option will increase
or decrease the rotation
angle of your bones.
With my three bone selected,
I will enter the value one,
hold Alt and press enter.
This way, all the selected
bones values are set to one.
With the value of one,
we can see that we almost
have no rotation on the bones
while if I set it to 180 degrees,
you can see that the
rotation gets pretty wild.
The stiffness value will kind
of change the reaction speed of the bone.
The higher the stiffness, the
more rigidity you are breaking
making the bones reacting
as if it was a metal spring
while with a very low stiffness,
it looks more organic like hairs or cloth.
So damping value greatly changed
the behavior of the bones.
The higher the damping value,
the more absorption you will have
in the motion of the bones.
If you drastically decrease
the value of the damping,
you will have a very jittery bones
that will react to any of
the motion in the chain.
You should keep the damping
value between zero and one.
If you enter a value beyond one,
it will likely creates bugs.
And one of the big
issues of this add-on is
that once the simulation is bugging,
you kind of have to revert
your file or reload it.
So be cautious with this.
It's the same for the Stiffness.
Don't go over one.
You won't have any change of behavior.
And at some point, it might bug.
In this specific case,
changing the translation
value won't do anything.
And we will see why later in this video.
For the time being, let's
increase the stretching value.
As expected, the bones are now stretching.
While it won't generate bugs,
I advise you to keep the value pretty low
and play in the range of zero to one.
The gravity value, as expected,
will kind of change the
weight of your bones.
If you get to a pretty high
value, like five or 10,
you will see your bones like falling.
While using the gravity value
in a pretty broad range,
I didn't meet any bugs.
So as you have understand, you
have to be kind of creative
and experiment a lot
with the different values
for the different bones
until you get the simulation you want.
Convert those simulation into
an action or an animation,
we need to bake.
To be able to bake the
action of the bones,
you have to make sure
that they are selected.
By clicking the select
wiggle bones button,
you will select all the bones
that have the wiggle bone option enabled.
You've seen in the previous video,
baking an animation is done
through the NLA editor.
When opening the NLA editor,
I can see my current
weeping action being used.
By now, click the bake wiggle button
in the wiggle bone panel.
It will bake the wiggle simulation
on all the selected bones.
And we can see that it
does create a new NLA track
including the weeping action.
And on top of this, we can
see our new baked action.
Let's push it down into the NLA editor.
And if we deactivate it,
we can see that our bones
are no longer rotating.
Thus, when we click the bake wiggle,
it will remove the wiggle
option onto those bone.
So what we see are currently
the animation of those bones.
Additive bake option
simply create an NLA track
including the original action
so that the bake action can
be layered on top of it.
If we deactivate the additive bake
and then bake the wiggle action,
we will only see the result of the wiggle.
Since the root bone wasn't
choosing the wiggle add-on,
it's not moving anymore.
This, we then need to
manually add those action
into the NLA editor.
When both the weeping action
and the baked action are enabled,
we can see the whole
animation we have generated.
So particularly, I advise you
to keep the additive bake enabled.
I will reset everything
and I will select the second animation.
The jumping one.
As you can see, we have some
amplitude on the translation
but the bones are not offsetting
and this is because they
are connected in the rig.
So I need to go into edit mode,
select those bone and press
Alt + P to unparent them
or keep them parented but disconnect them.
And now we can see that they
are getting offsetted based
on the translation value.
If we increase this value,
there will be more jittery
and they will move in space a lot more.
I advise you to keep this
value between zero and one.
It's a very powerful
tool that can allow you
to get very nice results fast
but you may need to edit to beat the rig.
So let's now try the add-on on our Mac.
I've just reloaded the base motion file.
We have the work cycle
enable in the action editor.
I will select the Bodhi
controller and I will enable
then we go add-on.
As soon as I activate the
add-on on the Bodhi controller,
we can see our character
shaking on each step
which is kind of cool.
I have a drop in performances
which is kind of expecting
since it's running a
simulation in real time
but it's definitely okay
for me to work on this
increasing the Stiffness and the dumping
to get a more natural motion
or something I like more.
But there is a little issue
or at least limitation compared
to the previous method.
Here, I can't choose what part
of the body is currently leading.
And as you can see, whenever
the character is dropping down,
the front part is dropping down also.
So it's the back part of the body
that is currently dragging in the motion.
So Blender kind of assumed
that the back part of the body
is currently heavier than the front part
which is not what I did in
my animation previously.
And this is not something I can change.
I have no option to deal with this.
It depends on the base orientation
of the bone in the rig.
But as an animator, you may
not want to edit the rig.
Whenever you want to use this,
you will break everything for sure.
And another big limitation is
that we can't constraint
one rotation angle.
Here, you can see that the
antenna is currently rotating
along all its axis even
if the axis are locked.
So this is a fantastic add-on
but if you want to
create precise animation
or precise motion along a specific axis,
it might not be the best choice
but for any organic propose,
it can be a huge time saver.