- [Instructor] Before we
start animating our character,
I'd like to talk a bit about rotations
and how Blender and 3D application
in general, and all them.
One key component to understand
is that orientation and rotation
are two different things.
Rotation is the action or the motion
of rotating around an
axis or multiple axes
while orientation is the
result of those rotation
at a specific moment in time.
In this example, the orientation
is where the arrow is pointing at.
It's currently oriented straight up
because it has no rotation values.
So what we see per frames
are just orientation.
And when we have different
orientation in sequence,
we can simulate a rotation.
In this example,
I have a bunch of different arrow object
with different colors,
and they all have different orientation
and they will appear only
on one frame at a time.
But if I played the animation
and I displayed those different arrows
with different orientation in sequence,
we feel like there is a rotating arrow.
Don't worry, you don't
need to think about this
whenever you're animating.
What I'm just pointing out here
is that you can bring
the feeling of rotation
or rotating motion in different ways.
And sometime your graph editor
might not exactly reflect
the sensation of rotation you have
playing in your animation.
In this next example,
I have two arrows with
exactly the same orientation,
but one is rotated by a
360 degrees on the X axis
while the other one has no rotation.
And if I insert a keyframe
for the rotation channels
of those two arrows,
we can see that for the same orientation,
we have two different values.
So the rotation motion
would be a variation of
those values over time.
But if in this case I do a 360 degree turn
over only one frame,
I don't see any rotation on screen.
So it's kind of a stupid example,
but my goal here is to show you
that even if the graph editor
is outputting a rotation motion,
the feeling on screen or in
your output might be different.
And so it's very important
to check your motion path,
your arcs, and your spacing
whenever you are animating a rotation.
In the end, when we are
manipulating rotation curve,
99% of the time it does
make sense and it's logical
but sometime, especially with quaternions,
it won't be logical at all
and it's better to focus on the output
than how you got there.
Let's have a quick look to
the different rotation types
and when to use them.
You can change the rotation type
of most item in the transform panel
by clicking in the rotation menu.
We will find quaternions rotation mode,
different Euler rotation,
and finally the axis angle mode
that we won't be talking about
because I never ever use it.
Eulers are very cool
because they are very easy to understand
especially when
manipulating only one axis.
You can input the value you want
on the rotation axis of your choice
and the object will
rotate around this axis.
For example here, around the X axis.
And the cool thing about
Euler rotation on one axis
is that it's very easy
and logical to read in the graph editor.
To illustrate it, I will create
a full revolution animation
around the X axis.
A revolution around one axis
is a 360 degree rotation.
In this case, around the X axis.
I will then add an empty that
I will parent to the arrow,
placing it on the tip of the arrow
and calculate its motion path
so that we can see the spacing
of our revolution motion.
When we now watch the result,
we can clearly see the
difference of spacing
around frame 15
where the curve has the
most value variation
while around frame 0 and frame 30,
we have some easing.
So single axis Euler rotation curve
are super easy to read
and they are the perfect choice
whenever you are using a controller
that need to rotate only on one axis
like elbows, finger joints,
foot roll, or knees.
Since Eulers are awesome,
why don't we use them all the time?
Let's input a bit of Y
rotation into our arrow.
With this 30 degree
rotation on the Y axis,
I changed the orientation of the arrow.
So how will be its motion now?
Will it still rotate around its X axis?
Well, not exactly.
It's still doing a revolution,
but the axis has changed.
It's like we have given
it a new orientation
before we start the revolution motion.
When we input a Y value,
it's like we are changing
the initial orientation of our arrow
and while the arrow, it's still
doing a revolution motion,
it's not doing it anymore
around the same visual axis.
So why is that and how can we handle this?
Basically, to define the
orientation of the arrow.
Blender is reading the Euler
rotation value in sequence
and this is why we can
change different type
of Euler rotation.
It will simply change the
order of the sequence.
When I say in sequence, I mean that,
Blender will first read in this case,
the Z rotation axis,
then the Y rotation axis,
and finally the X rotation axis.
So basically, it start by the end.
For the XYZ Euler rotation,
it will first read Z,
then Y and finally X.
For a ZYX Euler rotation,
it will first read X then Y and finally Z,
and this is why, in a way,
we feel like the Z axis and the Y axis
are giving a different orientation
while we are executing the
revolution around the X axis.
But this is not exactly true.
And what happen if we input some motion
onto those two axes?
If I get rid of the rotation on the Z axis
and I'll input some rotation
motion onto the Y axis
while maintaining the rotation
motion onto the Y axis,
we can see we get a very weird motion.
And if I track now the tip of my arrow,
it's super strange.
I will get rid of the
interpolation of my curve,
so that we have a linear motion,
and now if I mute the Y axis,
I see my classical rotation
but as I mute the X axis
and have only the Y rotation,
we can see that the rotation
or revolution on the Y
depends on the value on the X
and it totally changed
the behavior of the arrow.
So this is one of the main
issue regarding Euler rotation
and it's linked to the gimbal lock.
To illustrate the gimbal lock,
we will use this Suzanne head.
I have three different rotation object.
Each object can rotate
only on one single axis.
Red is X, green is Y, and blue is Z.
And I will parent the
monkey head to the red one,
the red one to the green one,
and the green one to the blue one,
so that we can rotate them
in sequence as with Eulers.
So rotating the X object
will make the head rotate.
If I rotate the Y object,
both the head and the red one will rotate,
and finally, rotating Z
will rotate everything.
I can easily create revolution animation
or any rotation animation
around the X axis.
If I rotate a bit Y,
it will change the
initial orientation of X,
thus, the revolution axis of the head.
The problem is with this
evaluation of orientation
through sequence, if I
rotate Y by 90 degrees,
then X and Z will be aligned
and from there, rotating whether Z or X,
won't change the behavior of our head
and this is what we call a gimbal lock.
We have isolated one rotation axis
in this case, the original X axis.
So to keep things simple,
whenever you are using Euler,
just forget about the
middle axis in the sequence
and use Eulers only for one or two
axis rotation controllers.
If your controller is
supposed to rotate freely
around the three axes,
we will favorize quaternions.
When I need to choose
which type of Euler
sequence I'm going to use,
I make sure that the first in the sequence
is the most important axis
the one that will rotate the most.
The one in the middle is
the one I want to isolate,
the one I don't want to use,
and the third one is
kind of a secondary axis.
On the foot roll controller, for example,
I will favorize the X axis,
and the Z axis will
come in second position,
and I don't want to
rotate around the Y axis.
For the shoulder, it's a bit the same.
The X axis will be the main rotation axis,
the Z the secondary.
I keep the Y axis available
because I know we can
do find the tweaking,
but those are going to be
very low angle adjustments.
Let's have a look to quaternions.
With my arrow selected,
I will choose in the
Rotation Menu, Quaternions.
We now have four channels.
When I changed the value on X, Y, or Z,
the arrow rotate around
the X, Y, or Z axis.
So it seems to behave as it did before,
but that's not exactly the case.
We generally use quaternions
from a value of 1 to minus 1.
If I set the value on the Y axis to 1,
I will see my arrow rotated by
90 degree around the Y axis,
and minus Y will be minus 90 degree.
But if I want to do a 180
degree rotation on the Y axis,
I will get stuck.
As I go beyond a value
of 1 which I can do,
the arrow will go beyond
the 90 degree angle
but there is a lot of easing
and the closer I get to 180 degree,
the more and more I need
to increase the value
and I won't be able to get
to this 180 degree angle
even if I push the value to the infinite.
If I now try to reach
this orientation manually
instead of using the value inputs,
we can see our Y value
changing as expected,
but also the W value.
These values that was 1 got to 0
and is now getting to minus 1,
while the Y value is also
changing at the same time.
And this is because those
are not rotation values,
but each channels equal an orientation.
And the values we are
manipulating are the quantity
or the weight of each of those
orientation we are giving
to set the final
orientation of our object.
This is something that
was super well explained
on the sociamix YouTube channel,
and I will put the link
in the documentation.
Here, I have four different object,
each one has a value of 1
on one of the quaternions input.
If I set a value of 0.5 on W and on X,
you can see our object pointing down.
It's half way the orientation on W,
and half way the orientation on X.
I can repeat the process with W and Z,
and now the object will be facing us.
So I believe it can be
a little bit abstract,
and it is also for me.
The benefit of quaternions
is that it will take the shortest path
from one orientation to another.
So if I use my initial arrow,
and I will key different
orientation in space,
and I will then set my curve
to linear interpolation
and calculate the motion path,
you can see those clean arcs
going from one position to the other.
While if I switch to Euler rotation
and key exactly the same
orientation at the same time,
you will see that my curve change,
and it is kind of zigzagging
in a smooth manner.
So the big strength of quaternion
is to not have any gimbal lock
and being able to go to one orientation
to the other flawlessly.
It's perfect for any tracking motion
like the head, the arm, the
wrist, or even the spine,
but it has some limitation.
You can't do a proper
revolution with quaternions,
it's very complicated to
read the curve interpolation
since it's generally a
mixture of all the channels
at the same time.
So the best way to deal with quaternions
is to track your arcs
whenever you are polishing your animation.
A classic bug with quaternions
is when you're trying to do a revolution
and see the orientation flipping.
This can happen often
especially if you don't go
into a very detailed blocking,
and the simplest way to fix it
is to animate on once
whenever you are transitioning
from one orientation to the other
and you have these flipping problem.
We will probably face these issues
in the incoming chapters.
Don't worry if it's a bit confusing,
you don't need to know all these theory
to become a good animator.
To summarize, we have
seen that the orientation
is the result of any rotation
at a specific moment in time.
A sequence of different orientation
can give the impression
of rotation motion.
You should use Euler rotation
whenever you are rotating
around one or two axis maximum.
Eulers are awesome because
they are very easy to read
and edit in the graph editor,
and you can do a full
revolution with them.
But they can have confusing behavior
whenever you are trying to manipulate
multiple axes at the same time,
and you may also encounter
gimbal lock trouble.
Quaternions won't have any gimbal lock.
They have a consistent behavior
no matter the orientation
you are trying to reach,
but the graph editor
can be a bit confusing.
You can't, or it's very hard
to execute in your
revolution using quaternions.