- Let me present to you the new character
we will be using called Tridents.
You will find in the
chapter five file folder,
the file called Trident rig final.
It's a new character rig
that is quite more complex
that one we add before.
Fortunately, the UI has
been properly organized
by my friend, Fin.
If you don't get this specific UI,
just open the text editor,
open the TRIDENT_riggy.py
search for the file in the library
and press the play button.
The register option under
text should be enabled.
You will find a UI that is
very close to what we add from
the squirrel character and the Mac,
allowing us to show our ID,
the different controllers
of the character.
Starting with the root bone as usual.
But before, let's have
a look at the outliner.
We have a master collection
called Trident character,
including two secondary collection.
One including the rig and the other
including the different
parts of the character.
The character himself,
but also the weapons he has.
By default, the character
is shaded in solid mode,
showing its diffuse texture.
You can switch to previous mode
to see the full rendered character.
If at some point you
see a bright pink color,
it means that one of the texture is lost.
All the character's textures can be find
in the textures folder
of chapter five folder.
The texture path is set to relative,
so if you keep your blend file
close to the texture folder,
you will never lose them.
Let's have a look to the rig.
For this rig, I've created
two different roots.
One master and a secondary root.
It can be useful in certain cases.
Let's have a look to the torso.
We have a master controller
as for our squirrel character
and then the controller for the hips
and a controller for the chest.
You will also find a
controller for the neck
and the head.
All those controllers
can be freely rotated,
scaled, or translated.
When activating the torso tweak layer,
you will be able to access
those yellow round controllers.
These are tweaker bone that
will allow you to modify
the shape of each joint of the character.
It's perfect to fix some poses
or create squash and stretch effects.
All the yellow controllers
on the character
are tweaker bones.
This torso tweak layer
also give you access
to secondary controller of the torso
that uses a forward
kinematic for each joint.
Splitting the hips
controller into two parts,
the chest controller into three parts,
the neck and head in one part each.
The face layer will give you access
to the main face controllers,
including the jaw,
the nose, the mouth, the cheek
that can be moved individually
to shape the face of
the character at will.
The eyes and eyebrow of the character
have automated shapes.
They can be moved up and
down or on the local y-axis
to get to different
shape, like a happy face
a frown, a surprise,
following you to rapidly
create different stereotyped
expressions for your character.
The face secondary, will give you access
to all the face tweaker bone.
Allowing you to shape the eyes at will,
rework the brow shape to
draw whatever you want.
By default, the legs of the character
use inverse kinematic mechanism,
meaning that if you move the foot,
the knee will automatically bend.
It's the same behavior we had
with the squirrel character controllers.
The poles controller will allow you
to orientate the knee at will.
There is also a forward kinematic layer
and we will see or we
can switch from inverse
to forward kinematic a little later on.
You will also find our
yellow tweaker bones.
The biggest one on the main
joint, like the ankles,
knee and hips will allow
you to reshape the whole leg
based on its natural joint.
While the secondary controllers
will allow you to completely
modify the shape of the
leg to create rubber limbs.
Very nice for cartoony animations.
There are also a couple of controllers
to reshape the butt of the character.
And we will find the
same kind of arrow key
on the arm of the character.
We will find the shoulder bones
as being the root of the arms
and then forward kinematic controllers,
tweaker bones, etc.
It's also possible there to switch
between the forward kinematic
and inverse kinematic.
We will check that in a few second
when looking at the rig properties.
The finger controller are
pretty straightforward.
Near the pinkie, you will
find this master pan bone
that will allow you
to curve the whole palm of each hands.
the same root will allow you to orientate
the thumb and each finger
as its own master bone.
On each finger, rotating
the second joint bone
will allow you to bend both
the second and third joint.
Finally, each joint
can be rotated, scaled,
and moved at will.
The different weapons,
are all both the same way.
You will find a master
bone that more or less
have the shape of the current weapon.
Allowing you to orientate
Eaton's space and move it.
Then, you will find a
forward kinematic chain
that is ideal to curve the
weapons and give them nice shape
whenever you are doing stylized animation.
And as usual, the yellow bones
will be our tweaker bones.
Moving them with allow you to
modify the shape of each joint
of the different weapons.
You can hide or unhide all
the tweaker controllers
and layers using the eye
icon on the top right corner.
Let's have a look to the rig property.
The head follow and neck follow sliders
allows you to enable or disable the fact
that the neck is following the orientation
of the chest or not.
It's the same principle
regarding the head and the neck.
If I disable the head follow
and I rotate the neck,
the head stay in the same orientation.
This is super useful for dance animations
or run cycles, for example.
And then we will find the same option
for the arm and the legs.
When enabling arm follow,
we can see that now
the arms are following the
rotation of the shoulders.
While when disabled, they will
keep their own orientation,
making it easier to
stabilize their orientation.
By default, the legs are
set to inverse kinematic.
This is perfect for any
contacting controller.
In this case, the legs
contacting with the ground.
But we can switch to forward kinematic
by switching this value to zero.
We can see the leg snapping
into another position
following the orientation
of the forward kinematic controller,
so it can be enabled in the layer system.
This can be useful to draw nice arcs
whenever your character
is making big jumps
or kicking something for example.
We will find exactly the same
mechanism for the other leg,
but also for the arms.
Setting the values to zero,
will switch to forward kinematic.
To one, will switch to inverse kinematic.
By default the arm are using
forward kinematic mechanism,
but you can switch to inverse kinematic.
Again, this is super useful
whenever your character
is contacting with something.
When doing push ups, for example,
or interacting with another character.
You will find the parent option
for the legs and the arms.
By default the leg inverse
kinematic controller
are parented to the
root, so they don't move
whenever the torso is moved.
And the pose target is independent.
When switching the parenting value to one,
the pole will be parented
to the foot controller.
Meaning that rotating the foot
will also rotate the knee.
This is the method I generally use.
Switching the value to two
will also parent the foot
to the torso controller,
but not to the hips.
That can be useful whenever
you make your character jump for example.
You will find the same option regarding
the inverse kinematic arms controller,
but only when one value
that allow you to parent
the inverse kinematic
controllers to the torso root.
Again, they won't follow the chest,
but they will follow the torso root.
I've heard the same kind of
mechanism for the weapons.
Allowing you to whether
snap them to the left hand,
right hand or not snap them at all
so that they can move freely in space.
This can be useful
whenever you want to throw
the weapon for example.
The weapon emit option
will allow you to play
with the strength of the
emission shader on the weapons.
If you press play, you can see
that the shader is currently animated.
Bringing a magical touch to those weapons.
On top of this, you will
find a weapon spawn option
that will allow you to make the weapons
progressively disappear or appear
with a nice dissolve effect.
As for the squirrel character,
you will find visibility properties
that allows you do hide
different part of the character,
making its silhouette easier to read
or allowing you to focus on
specific part when animating.
Last but not least you
will find a snap utilities.
This will allow you to change
from inverse kinematic
to forward kinematic
and also align the controllers together.
Allowing a seamless switch
between the two mechanisms.
A disclaimer here. Due to the complexity
of the rig mechanism and
the rubber limbs system,
it can be sometimes not 100% accurate
but the pose can be fixed in one second.
And this is way faster
than trying to align
the controller by hand.
I'm not used to have this in production
so this is really a bonus.