- [Narrator] Welcome to chapter five.
This is the first chapter
where we are going to animate
a humanoid character.
We will use some of the
techniques you've learned
in the previous chapter
to make a first run cycle.
You may think it's weird
to start with a run cycle,
while we haven't learned to walk,
but runs are easier to
animate than a walk cycle.
In this chapter, I will also introduce you
to a new character rig we are going to use
until the end of this animation course.
Even if you want to jump
into the further chapter,
I advise you to at least watch this video.
We will go over some reference analysis,
as well as some zero
recall video about rotation
and how they work in (indistinct).
Welcome to this new chapter
and let's get started.