- [Instructor] I'd like
to finish this chapter
with a little tip video.
We have seen in the previous chapters
that we can use the NLA editor
to layer different animations
and modify the current one.
To create an ad term, for example,
or to transition between
two different animations.
But what you can do to
rapidly modify your run cycle
and create iterations is to
simply offset different curves
on your main controllers.
For example, here, I've offset
the X quaternion rotation
of the torso.
Now, I'm doing the same
with the neck controller.
I will do the same with
the hips, with the chest,
and this is very easy to push those curves
to get a totally new
attitude for our character.
On a locomotion cycle,
you will generally favorize the rotation
around the x-axis of the
different torso controller.
But you can also move the Y
location of the torso root,
and get a more cartoony,
afraid-like run cycle.
Or in the other end,
push everything forward
so that you get a way more
accelerated, dynamical run cycle.
This is a very good and fast technique
to explore different
versions of your cycle.
And that can be very useful
in a studio environment
to explore different
moods for your run cycle.
You can play with all the
different controllers.
You can offset the Y location
of the foot, for example,
so that they will be
offset forward or backward
during the run cycle.
You may want to fix the neck orientation
using the secondary controllers.
In one word, have fun with your animation!
And make additional
use of the work you did
on this run cycle.
It will sure need a pass of polish
once you've totally changed
the pose of your character,
but it's a very fast and painless
way to explore new poses,
new attitude, and bring
life to your character.