- So this is the final
stage of this animation,
where we will polish the
forearms and the hands.
As we did before with the arm,
I advise you to use the
wrist tweaker controller
to track the arcs.
If we have a look to the final
version of this run cycle,
we can see that the
forearm eats it's extreme
at frame three when moving back.
This is the moment where
the elbow is the most open.
Then when we're studying the reference,
we have seen that as the
elbow is reaching its extreme
on frame eight,
the four arm is bending
inward to compensate.
After frame eight, the elbow
or arm start to rotate forward
and the forearm is still
closing until frame 11
and from frame 12 to frame 15,
the forearm is slightly
open before closing again,
while it reaches its highest point.
So as we watch the references,
we understand that it's
a little more complex
than a simple follow-through animation.
Forearm polished, we can
now jump to the hands.
Only play with the rotation
channels of the hands.
There is not that much to
track regarding the hands.
We could track one of the knuckle joints,
if we do want to track the
arcs of the tip of the hands.
In my case, I jumped back to the reference
and I'm really focusing
on using both hands.
You can see how it dives
inward as if he was swimming.
So my goal is not to have
this level of exaggeration,
in this kind of swimming motion,
where he's really trying
to pull himself forward.
Again, it does show us that the hand
is not only dragging
back during the motion.
So instead of showing you all,
I've pushed each controller
in the rough editor.
We'll have a look to the
final results on the right.
When the hand is moving forward,
as it reaches the passing pose,
it's relaxed as it is dragging a bit.
This is the time where the
Z value is at its maximum.
Then as the arm reaches
its extreme pose forward,
the hand curves toward the head
and as the arm comes down,
the hand drags a bit.
So on frame zero 24,
the hand is reaching its opposite extreme
where the thumb is getting
closer to the forearm
by rotating the wrist.
Then the Z curve makes a
quick bump on frame three.
This is where the hand is
trying to reach backward
to get this kind of swimming pose,
as if the character was trying
to pull himself forward.
The wrist and forearm are almost aligned.
And then as the arm reaches
its extreme on the back,
the hand is curving forward
as if it was compensating the movement
of the elbow and get
ready to dive forward.
So from the side view,
mostly working on the Z turn and rotation,
we can see that it's a little more complex
than a simple drag again.
If we now have a close look
to the Y and X rotation curves,
we can see they have a sinusoidal shape
because they will mainly
influence the twisting
of the wrist and its left to right motion.
So they are mainly used to
keep a nice shape of the wrist
that doesn't look too broken.
The hand is slightly more
rotated inward around frame 14
during the passing as if it was pointing
toward the place it wants to be.
So, that's not super complicated
when it comes to work
from the front view, just try
not to have two broken wrists.
And if you have something to
remember about this polishing
it's that the hand is
not necessarily dragging
during the run cycle animation,
which is a common mistake.
From there, we will be
able to mirror the motion
of the left arm onto the right arm.
So I've pressed Alt + H
to unhide all the curves.
And then I will select all the
controllers of the left arm,
the shoulder, arm, forearm,
and the hand controller we have polished.
In the graph editor press eight,
to select all the curves,
press Control + C to copy the curves.
And then I will jump onto the other arm,
select the shoulder, arm,
forearm, and hand controller.
Select all the keys but
the one on frame zero
and delete them and then select
all the keys on frame zero
and press Control + Shift + V
to paste the mirrored animation.
Then, as we did for the previous cycles,
I will duplicate over the
curve by pressing Shift + D,
X and 24
to offset them by 24 frames on the x-axis.
Then I will press eight
to select everything,
press G X minus 12,
to offset them back by 12 frames.
This way we have a 12 frames offset
between the right arm and the left arm.
Finally, I will move the
play head on frame zero.
Press I to insert the key
frame on all controllers,
then select all the keys I
just returned on frame zero.
Press V and set the angles to three.
I will then select them again,
press Shift + D and 24
to duplicate them on frame 24.
And now I can get rid of any key frames
before and after frame zero and frame 24
and our run cycle is finally done.
In the next video I will just
share with you a few tips
on how you can change a bit
your run cycle with ease.
As always when it comes to art,
you will have to make multiple run cycles
until you get them right.