- Let's start the blocking
of our walk cycle.
I will start where I've
left in the last chapter
and I will create a new action.
So, I will go into Pose mode,
select my character,
and press this icon to
duplicate the run cycle.
From there, I can rename it
and click the shield icon
to make sure I won't lose this data
whenever I restart Blender.
Now I will select all the key frames
but the one on frame zero
and I will press X to delete them.
Now we need to make sure
that we have clean channels.
Since we have worked in the
graph editor on many curves,
I need to make sure that
I reset those curves.
In my action editor,
I will press Control+Tab to
switch to the graph editor,
and enable "show hidden."
I will then press Alt+H to make sure
that I reveal all the curves.
And from there, I will
press A to select them all,
press the T key and switch
everything to Bezier.
Then I will press the V key
and switch everything to Autoclamp.
Now, everything is reset.
If you have a look to the key frames,
we can see that they have a round shape,
meaning that they are
all set to Autoclamp.
If I switched to Vector, for example,
they become square.
If I switch to Align,
they will have this kind of diamond shape.
Now, we need to reset
the pose of our character
before we start working.
So, I will make sure
that I have all my controllers available.
And as you can see
here, my UI didn't load,
So what I will do is open the text editor
and with trident rig script selected,
I will press the play button.
Now to make sure that
it automatically play
whenever I reload the file,
I will go to Text, and enable Registered.
From there, in the rig UI,
I will enable all the layers
and press A in the 3D view
to select all my controllers.
And I will press Alt+R, Alt+G and Alt+S
to reset the rotation scale and location
of all the controllers.
Once I'm done with that,
I can hide the controller
we won't be using.
So we can hide the root,
the torso tweak from the time being,
all the face controller,
keep the leg I-case,
keep the arm eighth-case.
While we will be using
them, we can hide the hands.
And we will hide every
weapons controllers.
I will just rotate a bit
the arm of the characters so that he looks
a bit more relaxed and we can get started.
The first pose we are going
to build is the contact pose.
Let's have a quick look to the references
to spot the key features of this pose.
This is the moment where both
feet are contacting the ground
and are further away, one from the other.
Both are on the extreme.
One on the heel, one on the toes.
The hips are slightly tilted up
from the back leg that is pushing.
The chest is slightly tilting the same way
as it is transitioning into the next pose
where we will have the contrapposto.
But it's twisted the opposite way
compared to the hips toward the front arm.
Toward the front arm,
the center of gravity is almost centered,
but it's a bit favorizing the back foot.
Note that the reference on
the right is showing someone
with an athletic walk,
so the arm swing motion is a bit extreme.
We will keep our walk cycle
a little more relaxed,
with less amplitude.
We will start our first
pose by posing the feet.
You may choose to push
whether the left or right foot forward
and the other one backward.
Then we can use the role controller
to raise the toes for the front leg
and raise the heel for the back leg.
I will lower a bit the center of gravity
to make sure that the
legs are not stretching.
Don't forget to pose the
toes on the front foot
as they are dragging a bit
before they contact the ground.
On this walk cycle animation,
I will try not to rotate on the side
or twist the torso root controller.
I will slightly rotate it forward
to give a more dynamic
pose to our character.
But we will mainly use
this root torso controller
for the up-and-down and
side-to-side motion.
I have twisted the hips
toward the front foot
and I'm twisting the chest
toward the front arm.
Remember to pose the arms
the opposite way as the foot.
When the left foot is forward,
the right arm is forward.
Also remember that your
elbow is supposed to rotate
only on its local Z axis.
You can't rotate your
elbow around multiple axes.
So when it comes to posing the arm,
I mainly use the arm controller
to orientate the arm.
Another thing to double check so that
we don't get the same problem
as during the run cycle
is to make sure that
both the neck and head
have their rotation fully disabled.
As usual, I'm showing the final pose
we are supposed to reach.
Don't forget to slightly shift
the weight of the character
on its back leg by selecting
the torso root controller
and slightly move it on the X axis.
Left to right motion
will be more pronounced
on the walk cycle than on the run cycle.
Here you can see me
fighting a bit with the pose
of the hips and the chest
because I wasn't looking at the reference.
So I was trying to set a contrapposto
while the chest should
be almost horizontal.
The only contrapposto that occur
is the twisting.
I'm tweaking the pose
to make sure that my
character look balanced.
Take the time to properly
refine this pose,
because this is the
one we are going to use
to build the other ones.
And it will communicate a
lot about your character.
From there, I will
re-enable the hand layer
and I will slightly pose the hands.
So I will build a default
pose on one of the hand,
by slightly curving the palm
controller and each finger
to make the hand pose a bit more relaxed.
Then I will select all
the left hand controllers.
Press Control+C to copy the pose
and Control+Shift+V to paste it,
mirrored on the other side.
So as I explained before,
after watching my references
I've decided to slightly
realign the chest,
to have my shoulders more into
an horizontal line as on the reference.
Don't forget to double
check the arm position,
the hands position, using the reference,
as this is the extreme pose for both arms.
Then you can push a little bit
the feet toward the inside.
It will look a little more
natural and less robotic.
The more you push the
feet toward the inside
on a central line, the more feminine.
So if you were to animate
a stereotyped sexy woman,
you would push the feet
toward a central line.
This is the kind of pose you
will see in a fashion show.
But it doesn't really fit our character
so let's cancel this and
jump into the next video.