- Start polishing the
torso of our character.
As usual, I will start with
the torso route controller.
This is something we have been doing
on all the previous lessons,
whether it was the robot
or the squirrel character
or the run cycle on this character.
What I want to point out here
is that the motion of the
torso root is one of
the most important parts
of your character.
Define the center of gravity
motion of your character.
Hence it will define the weight and rhythm
of your walk cycle,
which is the most important
notion in body mechanic.
Start with the up and down
motion, or Z location curve,
which is the most important
on the walk cycle.
Right now, the curve
looks very (indistinct)
and very smooth
but it seems that the extreme are
pretty well positioned in time.
Goal will be to bring contrast
to the motion by holding
a bit the down pose and the up pose.
We will have a slight plateau
on the highest and the lowest
values of the curve.
On the extreme up,
I'm trying to have the
leg almost fully extended.
Here I'm comparing the
previous pose with the new one.
During the pushing or up pose,
I'm trying to get an almost straight leg.
This give a better shape to the leg
and a better line of action to it.
We will talk about line
or action in detail
in the next chapter.
To make it simple here,
it makes the silhouette
of our character more readable.
As the straight leg supports
the idea of verticality,
of pushing up.
So I've polished the
first half of the motion,
I will first duplicate the
extreme down on frame four
and move it by 16 frame of
the length of the cycle,
get rid of all the key
frame after frame 20.
And they will duplicate the
polished portion of the curve
from frame four to frame 20
and move it by 16 frames.
There I can select the key on frame 32,
if you don't have one and you
can insert a key frame there
and move it on frame zero.
You treat of any keys that
goes beyond our 32 frame rail.
If needed, don't forget to rotate
to beat the keys on frame
zero and 32 to align the curve
from one cycle to the other.
Where you are polishing a
specific feature or area
of your character,
don't hesitate to hide the other part.
So I will add that to the
visibility properties panel
and I will hide arms
and hide the arms
(indistinct) controllers.
I do so I remove visual noise
and I feel like the up and down motion
while it's properly timed
is a bit too strong.
To make sure I'm using the bounding box
as a pivot point so that I
can scale the whole curve
on an average.
I will simply scale the
whole curve on the Y axis
by pressing S and then Y.
You can also move the whole
curve along the Y axis
in the (indistinct) to
either raise or lower
the center of gravity of your character.
I want my character to
almost have a straight leg
whenever he is pushing so
that it feels lightweight.
With the up and down motion now polished,
I will jump to the side to side motion,
working on the explication.
We'll add the Z location and
display the X location curve.
It currently looks a bit messy.
We are going to fix it pretty quickly.
First thing we need to do
is identify the extremes.
Weight mainly shift
between the contact pose
and the passing pose.
Then the body is to decide
during the pushing pose,
before the body starts
falling on the other side
and accelerate,
shifting the weight onto the other leg.
To the polished curve,
when zero we have the contact pose,
and we are almost reached the extreme
on frame six in the curve
is until frame 11,
where we start pushing.
Frame 11 to frame 15,
we slowly shift the
weight onto the other side
until the contact pose where we will have
a fast change in direction.
So you really want to shift
the weight from side to side
during the fall,
whenever the leg is about
to contact the ground
and contact the ground.
And as the character recover
with this contacting leg
and start pushing on it,
it will first absorb the momentum
and then start pushing on the other side.
As usual, you can refer to the
current curve on this plane,
but if you want to properly learn,
mostly focus on what we've just explained
first motion during the fall,
and then easing from the transition.
I was getting close to a convincing result
I want to be able to properly
symmetrize the motion.
Note that this is not mandatory.
If you have a difference between
the left to right motion,
it can be interesting
as a real life walk
cycle is never perfect,
but I just want to show you how
to mirror the curve over time.
I will get rid of any
curves that goes beyond
half of the cycle.
After frame 16, we select
all the other keys,
duplicate them and move them
by 16 frame on the X axis.
Now, my side to side motion
repeat over 16 frame,
but always go onto the same side.
You need to symmetrize the
value of our curve along
the Y axis and around the value zero,
we can easily do this
by using the 2D cursor.
It is defined by the play at position
for the X value
and this horizontal blue
line for the Y value.
Since we want to symmetrize our
curve around the value zero,
we need to reposition our 2D cursor
horizontal value to zero.
Precisely set this value
by adding to the view tab
where we can see the play at position
named cursor X value and the Y value.
So I would replace the
current Y value by zero.
Now, I just have to
make sure that I'm using
the 2D cursor as a pivot point,
scale on the Y axis by minus one,
the keys from frame 16 to frame 32.
This way, we make sure that
our cycle is currently cycling.
And then I will clean a bit the curve,
removing the keys that talk
too close one to the other,
and doesn't bring any information.
From there, we can work
on the Y location axis
of our torso.
Polishing the Y curve is
going to be pretty simple
because it has a very subtle
influence onto our walk cycle.
If you don't want to play with this curve,
that's fine,
but you should always
input a bit of motion.
By that is that since we
are animating our walk cycle
on the spot,
the torso route forward and backward wise
should it be on the spot too.
There is always a bit
of variation of our time
while your whole body is
moving in a linear fashion,
the are variation for every single point
in the body of your character.
Thing to know is that as the
character is falling forward,
just before the contact pose,
the body is accelerating forward.
And as soon as the foot
is hitting the ground,
the body will slow down and move backward.
Double check the values of my curve.
You can see that the range of
motion is very, very subtle.
It just brings some extra
texture to the motion.
Our torso root is now polished.
And in the next video,
we are going to polish the
other features of the torso.