- [Instructor] This video, we are going
to finish our walk cycle
animation, polishing the arms.
If you want to track your arcs on the arm,
I suggest you track the tweaker controller
of the elbow.
Then we can select our arm controller
and we can isolate the rotation channels.
For the whole chain down to the fingers,
we will only be playing
with rotation channels
from now on.
The most influential channel
for the rotation of the arm
in our swinging motion is
the z quaternion rotation.
Again, polishing this curve
is gonna be pretty straightforward.
It is mostly about cleaning the curve
than really reworking the animation
or the motion of the arm.
From view, I will press Alt + B
and frame half of my character
so that I won't be
distracted by the right arm
in the back when walking
from the side view.
The idea is to make sure
that we hold a bit the arm forward
and backward when it reaches its extreme.
While the arms were leading the animation
during the run cycle,
in the case of a walk cycle,
especially this relaxed walk cycle,
the arm are swinging in
reaction to the fall.
So they will be delayed
compared to the motion
of the foot.
Just make sure that your
arms hit their extreme a bit
after the contact post.
In our case, we have our
contact pose on frame zero
and the extreme is on frame two.
Once you get a decent result
using the z-quaternion curve,
you should switch to
the y-quaternion curve.
My case, it add almost the same behavior
as the z-quaternion curve
and its motion was added
upon the z-quaternion curve.
Polishing this curve allows us
to refine the swing motion,
especially on the easing
toward both extreme.
That animation is not a linear workflow.
Based on your blocking, you
may not have the same result
as what I have on screen.
This is why it can be hard sometime
to follow an animation course
where you may not have exactly
the same behavior curve wise.
So your goal is not to focus on the curve
but on the motion itself.
In my case, when I reached the extreme,
especially when the arm was swinging back,
it feels like it was hitting a wall.
It was reaching its extreme back
and then kind of bouncing forward.
Polishing the y-curve did fix the problem.
This rotation curve allows
us to move the elbow away
from the chest of our character.
So basically, when the elbow
is passing by the chest,
you would move it away
and when it's in the back of the chest
or forward in both extreme,
we will move it a bit inward.
With the arm polished,
we can jump onto the forearm.
As advised before,
if you want to track
your arcs on the forearm,
I advise you to track the
arcs of the wrist controller.
The cool thing about the forearm
is that generally speaking,
it can only rotate around one axis.
So we will only have to polish one curve,
the z rotation curve.
That might not be the case
for a very stylized animation
where you want to break the
limbs or stuff like that
to create stylized motion.
Basically, we want the hand
to drag compared to the elbow.
So as the arm is swinging forward,
I will bend the forearm a big backward.
We will reach the extreme
as the arm is almost passing
on frame number eight.
As the elbow hits its forward position,
the hand will catch up
and the elbow will bend the other way.
The forearm will reach the
other extreme on frame 21
as the arm starts to swing backward.
It's pretty easy to polish this curve
and you should have something
quite similar to mine.
It might be offset in time,
depending on the timing of your walk cycle
and also depending on
the amount of rotation
you are inputting,
the amount of dragging
you're inputting to.
The more the hand is dragging,
the more the forearm will look loose
and the more your walk
cycle will feel relaxed.
From there, we can jump
into polishing the hand.
It's gonna be exactly the same process
but this time on multiple axis.
Polishing the hand rotation
won't be a difficult task.
I'm first trying to figure out
which channel does what
and I will start by
polishing the z channel.
Orientate the hand forward or backward.
So from our side view,
this is the first most
influential channel.
The goal is to make the hand rotate
with a bit of delay
compared to the forearm.
One major mistake you should avoid
is to bend the hand too much backward.
Try it yourself and rotate
your own hand along this axis.
You will see that when it comes
to rotating the hand backward,
you are pretty limited in the range
of rotation you can reach.
And it's even worth the other way.
So don't overdo this backward
and forward rotation.
Regarding the x-quaternion rotation,
the inward and outward rotation
or orientation of the hand,
the motion range is not really a problem.
From the front view, whenever
the arm is swinging outward,
I make sure to make the hand drag a bit
by rotating it inward
and as the arm swing inward,
I make sure to rotate
the hand a bit backward
toward the outside.
Note that I have a bit
of clipping on my model.
During the passing pose,
the sum is crossing the
psi and cut the mesh.
So I will have to slightly open the arms
during the passing pose
by pushing the x curve.
So while the motion may feel good,
I need to fix a bit this kind of problem.
So I will increase the
x rotation amplitude
of the arms so that it
move a bit more away
from the thigh and I will also
slightly offset my x curve
for the hand so that I
also move the hand away
from the side.
Don't forget to check your
animation from every angle.
So animate from the side view,
front view and back view
and often turn around your character.
You should also check your
animation in perspective mode.
Not only in autographic mode.
After that, I worked a bit
on the y-rotation curve,
which makes the hand twist.
There is not much twisting
in this walk animation
but still, it's important to polish it
so that we have a smooth movement.
I've also worked on the
W-quaternion rotation curve.
The idea is not that it will
influence that much the pose
of our character or the motion of the hand
but I just want to make sure
that it flows perfectly
and that it blends from
one cycle to the other.
So the idea is mostly to clean the curve
than to improve the current
motion or modify it.
I often don't work on the
w-quaternion rotation,
especially for such subtle motion
but especially on cycles,
it can sometime input some glitches
if you don't have a good flow
between your very first
and very last keys.
As soon as I add the
satisfying hand motion,
so basically our whole
arm moving in space,
I decided to mirror the motion
onto the other arm to
have a better overview
of our current walk cycle.
I won't show you again how to copy
and paste mirrored a curve
or several curves onto the other side
of your character
since we've been doing
this several time already.
And both the arms in action
makes the walk cycle looks really cool.
The final touch will be to work a bit
on the palm deformation and the fingers.
We can input a bit more details
into our motion by
slightly animating the palm
and the fingers.
Regarding the palm,
I will only be playing
with the z rotation,
compressing a bit the bones
and simply inputting a bit of delay
in the rotation of this
pastor palm controller.
So I'm only using the z Euler rotation.
Whenever the hand is swinging forward,
I will slightly open the palm.
Whenever the hand is swinging backward,
I will slightly close the palm.
Then I will just make sure
that my curve cycle properly
and I'm done.
To add on with the palm
bone can be interesting
to add a bit of rotation in the fingers
and in the thumb.
Again, it's just about making the thumb
and the fingers drag a bit.
So whenever the hand is moving forward,
I make the fingers rotate
backward and vice versa.
The only thing you have to check
and figure out is on which
axis your fingers can rotate.
And the best way to do it
is just to check your own hand.
Your thumb can rotate along every axis
but the y-axis, you can't
really twist your thumb.
You can easily curl your finger
but when it comes to twisting,
it's almost impossible
and they have a very small
range of side-to-side motion,
so you can input a bit
of side-to-side motion
into your finger as a dragging motion
but it has to be every subtle.
I will favorize the hand close/open motion
of the fingers.
Since there is not that much to explain
about animating the fingers
for this walk cycle,
I will let you with a bit of music
to finish this little time lapse
and have our whole walk cycle done.
See you in the next chapter
where we will learn
how to create appealing
and convincing poses.
(tranquil music)