- [Tutor] Welcome to chapter six.
In this chapter, we are
going to build another cycle
and it's going to be vanilla walk cycle.
As explained before, we
are doing this walk cycle
after the run cycle, because
it's a little bit harder,
since it's more subtle to
get an appealing result.
As usual, we'll go through
a reference analysis
and we'll try to identify
the main mechanism involved
into a good walk cycle.
Starting from scratch, we'll
build the main key poses
of the walk cycle, and then
we'll mix our post to pose
and layered approach to polish the walk.
I will guide you through the whole process
from polishing the feet to
the fingers of the character.
Let's get started.