- Welcome to Chapter Seven,
where we are going to learn
how to create good poses
for our character.
I will try to teach you
all the fundamental rules
to build poses from a reference.
We will talk about the
most common mistakes we do
whenever we're posing a character
and how to avoid them.
I will also try to explain you
how to study your references.
What do you have to
look for in first place?
And we will talk about the little details
that can improve your pose and some tips
to help you pose faster.
Once we are comfortable with basic posing,
we will see how we can improve our pose
by pushing them so that
they better communicate
the will of our character
and its personality.
So open Blender and let's get started.