- [Instructor] In this video,
we are going to talk about
one of my favorite part
on any character.
Hands are super important
and too often overlooked.
And you can often
identify a big inner work
just by watching the hand posing.
The first main issue is to keep
the rest pose of most rigs.
Most of the time for technical purpose,
most character rigs have flat hand
whenever they are in rest pose.
And to get such a flat hand
pose, you need tension,
meaning that you need to
straighten your fingers
so that you're not relaxed.
So the first thing I
would suggest you to do
whenever you are posing your character,
but whatever the rig you are using,
is to slightly curve the end
using the palm controller,
and then to slightly bend
the tip of the finger.
Here, you can see a reference
picture of a relaxed hand
and there is no flat shape.
Another thing that is very
interesting is finger grouping.
Most of the time, fingers
tend to group themself
by two or by three.
The current pose is the one I use the most
with the index and the
pinky being separated,
and the middle finger and the
ring finger being grouped.
If you watch some of my animation,
you can see that I use it a lot.
Whenever I'm posing hand,
this is my go to shape,
but you can group the middle,
ring, and pinky together
or you can not leave the pinky alone,
but you should avoid creating two groups,
one with the index and the middle finger,
the other with the ring
finger and the pinky.
While it may fit for a ninja turtle,
this is not a very natural hand pose.
Whenever you are building a fist pose,
don't just rotate the root of the fingers,
and then curve them inward.
If you do so, you will end
up with a very squared fist.
We have flat surface on top of the hand
on the front of the
hand, and on the inward.
This will look very low poly
like or old game fashioned.
While if you look to a
closed fist reference,
you can see that there
is a lot of curvaturing.
So a good practice whenever
you're posing a fist
is to do the same thing as
when you're posing a rest hand.
First of all, think of
using the palm controller
to slightly bend or curve the whole fist.
Then watch your own fist.
Watch the relationship between each finger
and the overall shape.
Don't hesitate to play with
the location of the bone.
It's very odd to get a convincing fist
with all the compression
by using only the rotation.
Again, remember that we are
currently sculpting the pose,
shaping our character.
This is not about getting logical,
about all the bones should behave
in the body of our character.
We are not manipulating bones,
we are manipulating controllers.
So again, watch reference,
use your own fist,
and try to match it.
Here is the result whenever
I'm using my own fist.
Note that the fist
position might vary a lot
from people to people
and that you will meet limitation
due to the current rig.
I personally believe that
hands are so expressive
that they can be considered
as being a separated character
within the character.
When you are posing a hand, just act it.
Why we have been focusing on motion,
line affection, and
all this kind of thing,
this course is about animation.
So bringing your character to life.
And I do believe that
even in an action pose
or an action animation,
hands can communicate a
lot about your character,
about his personality.
So whenever you are walking on hands,
treat yourself as a
child and play with them.
Just remember whatever you were doing
whenever you were mimicking a
monster when you were a child.
Hand poses are written
into our subconscious
because it's a strong point
of attraction on a character.
They can be very feminine for example
or they can show anger or the
envy of an evil character.
So whatever the tension, the
shape you build with the hands,
they will communicate something.
Finally, whenever you
are posing your hand,
you have to think about the limitation.
While we can break those boundaries
whenever we are playing with exaggeration,
it's always better to build your poses
on the current limitation of the body.
Remember that the side to
side motion of the wrist
is pretty limited, just a
few degrees of rotation.
Again, use your own hand to test it.
If you hold your arms straight forward,
you can almost twist
your hand by 180 degrees
with your palm pointing to the sky.
While if you twist your hand inward,
you will hardly get over 90 degrees.
Regarding the back and
forth tilting of the hand,
you should be able to
reach a 90 degrees angle
whether you are bending
your hand inward or outward.
So whenever you are building
those pose, try them yourself.
If it's become painful,
then you have to compensate
whether with the shoulder or the elbow.
Fingers also have their limitation.
While the thumb is pretty flexible,
you will reach a limitation
whenever you're trying to
spread it as far as possible
til it creates an L shape
with the index finger.
The index and the pinky
can process free rotation
with a lot of limitation.
So you can rotate a bit with them
to create a circular shape,
but they are mainly able to curl.
The middle finger and the
ring finger are more limited.
Finally, when it comes to the
next joint on your finger,
they can only curve and rotating
them along any other access
will look very weird.
Again, it doesn't mean you
can't rotate them this way.
And I do it a lot whenever
I'm building smears,
but if you hold a pose this way,
the finger will look broken.
Finally, depending on the people,
the finger might be more or less flexible
and you can totally bend
them backward a bit,
especially if they are
applying any pressure.
This will mark the end of this video,
but I do advise you to have a look
to the talk of Hjalti Hjalmarsson
at the Blender Conference.
It's one of the best talk about
hand posing I've ever seen
and it's really eye opening.
You will find the link in
the documentation as usual.