- [Instructor] In the
beginning of this chapter,
we've been talking about exaggeration
and line of action.
Exaggeration can be
used to amplify feeling.
If you want to communicate anger,
just make your character mad, for example.
But we have also seen that
we can use exaggeration
to give whether more impact
or more freely to the motion.
Look at all, the Trident
here is completely bent,
helping to read the arc of motion.
Next frame, all the limbs are reshaped
to exaggerate this pinning
motion of the character
or on this landing pose.
The character is stretched
toward the ground
clearly supporting the line of action
and the directionality of the jump.
And if you did your homework,
this should remind you,
this should remind you
something, right there.
Whenever we are stretching the ball,
we create some kind of smear
and we are exaggerating its motion
and the same occur
whenever we are squashing
the ball on the ground.
It's another exaggeration
that better sell the impact.
So how can we apply those
principles to our character?
When we are first in the
light the reference pose
output the different line
of action of the pose
using the red and orange line.
So now what if we push those lines?
What if we exaggerate them?
The goal is to build
our shape or silhouette
based on the motion of the character
as if he was pulled by the
inertia of the movement.
As our line of faction is
curving, just push the curve.
And as our character is twisting,
just support the twists,
creating a rotation motion
within the hum and the sword.
We can also build a strong
smear upon the sword
to simulate motion blur.
To do it, let's go back into pose mode.
I will duplicate the initial pose
and I will start by pushing
the center of gravity of
our character to the right,
in the direction of the motion
or in the direction of
the force is applying
to strike the ball or maybe
cut is opponent in half
to be able to shape the silhouette
of our character at will
we will need to enable the tweaker bones.
All the yellow controllers,
I'll use to reshape each part of the arms,
the legs, torso, or even the whip.
So as we need in the previous video,
I'm slightly pushing the pose.
And then I will start using
those tweaker controllers,
starting with the left leg.
My goal will be to shape the
whole left side of my character
as a single curve.
Note that I will mainly
build the shape to camera.
It's all down to create smears
that can read from all the angles
and focusing on the camera point of view
will alow you to push
the pose even further.
The bigger knee tweaker controller
allows you to push the knee with the thigh
and shin following.
While the smallest one will allow you
to shape each joint of
this thigh and the shin.
So, as we did so far,
just repeat the process several time.
Push should be the pose.
Shape the arm and the
leg into a curvy shape.
And whenever you reach a satisfying shape,
just try to push it by
repeating the process.
As you get more experience,
you will be able to reach your extreme
or exaggeration faster.
Another important thing
is not to over-focus
on one part of the character,
and this is why you
should often add a loop
to the silhouette of short character.
The first step to give a better shape
to the sword is to first bend it.
To do so, you can use the sword
master rotational controller
available on the root of the blade
by pressing R and D twice, I can rotate it
along its local Z axis.
Then you can use each
individual controllers
to whether tweak the rotation
or location or to scale them.
Here, I'm currently scaling
them along their local X axis.
Starting from the tip of the sword
And then going up until
the root of the sword.
Look, all, we already improve
the character's silhouette.
And we do feel like the
sword is currently swinging.
From this point, my goal would
only be to push the pose.
So I need to accentuate
the curvature of the body
on the left side so that
I have better continuity
between the left leg and the torso.
This will support the line
of action of our character.
I will also slightly tweak
the shape of the blade,
so that it is smoother.
I just need to re walk
a bit the X local scale
of the different tweaker bones
to avoid those jacket profiles.
So don't forget to test each controller.
I've also used the tweaker
bone within the torso
to give it a more curved shape.
Progressively push the pose,
and don't be afraid to fail.
If you can't nail a good pose at once
that's perfectly fine.
While I do believe I ended
up with a satisfying pose,
I am convinced it can be improved a lot
and a more experienced animator
will probably get a better
pose than mine faster.
As any other art form
becoming good at animation
is just a matter of practicing.
And someone practicing
every day for four hours
will be better than someone
practicing once a week
for one hour,
while it may sound abused,
this is something I'd like to remind you,
And I will probably remind you often
during this whole course.
And if you lack of confidence,
just stop telling yourself
that you lack of talent.
I personally don't believe in talent
and whenever you meet any
artist that is very good
as it's art and you make the effort
to dig a bit into his career.
You understand that they don't land there
because they were talented,
but just because they were working a lot.
So I will let you there.
Don't hesitate to experiment
with the body shape,
stretch the EDD to give it speed.
Just try to affirm. And don't
forget that it's okay to fail.
So if this pose doesn't look right to you
just restart from scratch.
(relaxing music)