- Since animation is a sequence of poses.
Creating good poses is a must have skill.
So let's study the different
features that make a oppose
a good pose.
In the previous video, we
have seen the line of action.
So clearly it's super important
that your line of action
are clearly defined on all your poses.
It will help to read your poses.
It will help to read the
flow of your animation.
So this is definitely the first
thing you have to look after
when building your pose.
Senior, or the evolution
of the line of action
clearly communicates
the flow of the motion
and the emotion.
Second thing you have
to look for, is balance.
Characters that look off
balance will look weird
even to a non-animator.
You as an animator should know how to fix
enough balance pose or
enough balance character
or a static pose.
A good technique is to draw a box
around the main feature of the body.
The ones that wait the more.
Since the main goal of
balance is to fight gravity,
draw a straight vertical line
in the middle of this box.
This line should basically come across
your center of gravity.
If you don't have at least one
contact point or better two
or three contact point under this line,
your character will look off balance.
In the case of three
contact point or more,
the center of gravity, just has to be bind
to the triangle shape formed
by those contact points.
When you have only two points
of contact with the ground,
the center of gravity
should come across the line
drawn by those two contact points.
Finally, when you have
only one contact point
with the ground, your center of gravity
must be vertically aligned
with this contact point.
Note that your center of
gravity is not always centered
around your hips.
You have to take in account
the weight of your legs,
of your arms whenever you're
trying to balance yourself
by spreading your arms on the side
or whatever piece of
equipment you are wearing.
The next important thing
whenever you are building
a strong pose is silhouette.
It's the main feature
that's gonna be identifiable
on your character pose.
While the inner shapes of your
character might need other
to notice or to identify like
the head of the character
on this pose.
Reading inner shapes will
greatly depend on the quality of
the character design and its contrast.
A good practice is to have a dedicated
window in blender with a 3D
view set to flat shading.
If you're animating to camera,
these should be the camera view.
This way you will always have a sneak peek
to the silhouette of your character.
Now that we know how to
display our silhouette,
what makes a good silhouette?
The most important thing is readability.
The trident is currently a good example,
showing the three teeth or
three points of the tridents,
make it clear on the silhouette view.
While if I rotate it by a few
degrees and show its profile,
it doesn't read well anymore.
We no longer identify a
trident, but simple spear.
If we scrub through the animation,
most of the poses are clear
on this one, the legs,
the arms and the sword
are clearly identifiable.
The same will apply to this pose
where we can clearly
see that the character
is handling this weapon with two hands
or even this pose where through camera,
I slightly offset the
position of the sword
so that it appear in the
back of the character.
While I did the mistake
on the specific pose
to not have a clear silhouette.
And I received this as a
critique a lot of time.
And that's a bummer because
this is one of the strongest
moment in the animation.
This could have been
improved by slightly rotating
the whole character so
that we can see more
of a profile of the character
distinguishing both feet
and a bit of the arms.
Another principle that will help you build
a solid silhouette is
simplicity versus complexity.
If we have a look to
those different poses,
we can clearly see that
one side of the character
has almost a straight
line or a smooth curve.
While the opposite side of the character
is generally more detailed.
This will improve the
appeal of your poses.
It will also improve their readability
by giving them an orientation
or at least giving them contrast.
We did talk a lot about
contrast in our motion
whenever we have an odd
and a fast transition
That's the same regarding posing,
simplicity versus
complexity brings contrast.
And so it brings more
interest into the pose.
Another important point
regarding silhouette
is negative space.
Negative spaces are the
holes in the silhouette
of the character.
When you have overlapping
features like the arm crossing
the body of the character in this case,
make sure that you use those
negative space to show the
different features that will
help the viewer to identify the
different parts of the character.
Like the same here of the
silhouette of the biceps
that allow us to clearly identify the hand
or the arm of the character.
You should also try to avoid tangent
on your character or on your silhouette.
On this specific pose, the leg get tangent
with the end of the spear
and why it's not the end of the world
that could be improved if
the character was moved a bit
to one side or the other
so that we have no tangent
between the leg and the spear
and we can clearly identify both features.
There is another pose that look decent,
but that will read better
and it will be more appealing
if we were to separate a bit
the silhouette of the legs
and break the tangent in the
arms by showing the wrist
or an elbow, for example.
Avoid twinning in your poses.
Twinning occurs whenever you
have two features of the body,
like the hands or the
feet that have exactly
the same pose.
While it can be something
you voluntarily create
to bring strengths to a pose
or to bring control into a pose
like on the beginning of this jump,
where everything about
the body of our character
is symmetrical.
This is something you should live out.
For example on this pose,
both feet have a slight different of pose.
If I make them having the same pose,
it won't look as appealing
as the previous one.
Twinning will bring a lot of stability
and so it will kind of break the momentum
or the contrast in the pose.
Twinning can also occur in timing.
For example here, my character is catching
both sword at the same time,
and this is a personal choice
because I want to show that
he's perfectly knowing what he's doing
and mastering his art.
So twinning both in timing
and in the pose can show
strength and stability.
But in the case of this jump for example,
if I was to make both feet
arrive at the same time,
that will make the animation
a bit less appealing
and interesting.
In the end twinning bring
a sense of perfection.
And whenever you're achieving art,
what you want to avoid is perfection.
There is a lot of randomness in life,
and she's what we want to represent.
We want to make it alive, not
to make something perfect,
something CG.
Another thing you should
avoid are perpendicular lines.
If I take these pose that is decent
and I now make the arm
perpendicular to the spear
by straightening the elbow,
making this pure vertical,
that will look super stiff.
And if I even exaggerate
despite straightening
the whole torso, the neck, the head,
or even the other arm
that will look really bad.
And my last advice,
try not to hide any
part of your character.
There will be many times where
it's gonna be impossible,
but when you have the
choice like on this pose,
make sure that we see
a bit of the fingers.
Don't hide them into the silhouette.
Or on this other pose,
the pose looks great.
But if I twist a little more the hand,
I won't be seeing the thumb anymore.
So the end will be harder to identify.
That's a little detail, but
it will make the difference.
So whenever you are
pausing your character,
make sure you hit all
the notes in this video.
Watch full line of action
that we have explained
in the previous video.
Watch for balance, make
sure that your character
is not falling, especially
if he's turning.
Be very aware of the
importance of the silhouette.
Watch for readability of the silhouette.
Watch for simplicity versus
complexity in your silhouette.
Use negative space, avoid the tangent.
Break twinning by angling
a bit your character.
Break perpendicular lines,
avoid hiding part of your character.
In the next video, we will
start building our first poses.