- Now that we have our base pose,
it's time for us to push this pose
to make it more dynamic and appealing.
We have learned before the fundamentals
by identifying the line of action
and studying the basics of
creating a nice silhouette.
Now it's time to apply those fundamental
and exaggerate them.
The first thing I'm going to do
is duplicate our current
key frames onto frame two.
This way we can compare both poses
by hitting the up and down arrows.
The first thing we can do
is to push the directionality
of the line of action.
While on our basic pose
our line affection create a nice curve,
I will straighten the line of action
to give it more directionality.
The first thing to do is to lower
the center of gravity of our character
and push it to the side
on the supporting leg.
Then we need to increase the contrast
between the right leg and the left leg,
meaning that I will try
to make the right leg
as straight as possible.
First, with the different
controller in this case
I will slightly move the pole target
and I will also use the tweaker controller
to align the knee with
the ankle and the hips.
Then I will slightly open
the stance of our character,
pushing the left foot a bit backwards
so that it's not out of balance
and indirectly,
contrasting the open
stance of our character.
As usual, this is not a linear work,
so I may make the character
leaning forward too much,
then leaning backward,
then trying different poses
that looks more dynamical.
In the end, I've chosen to rotate
the center of gravity more forward
so that that it reduces a bit
the profile of the torso
and makes it more aligned
with the line of action.
Then we need to tweak
the position of the hips,
of the torso, of the head also,
tilting it a bit forward,
more into the pose.
And then we can start shaping the arms.
As for the line of action,
where I have a smooth curve.
I've decided to increase
the tension in the arms,
making the right arm straight
and supporting the line with the left arm
by opening it a bit.
But I was really hesitating
and still hesitating
to pose it more into an angled way.
I think this pose works too
and is also very strong.
I've straightened what was straight
and I've created another
angle where it was angled.
But they feel like there
is more readability
in the hand of my initial pose,
so we will stick to it.
So I will raise the shoulders,
I will open the hand,
I will slightly rotate it toward the sky
and make sure that the
palm is more open too,
more to the side.
To keep the directionality,
when we open the forearm,
we need to raise the arm
and raise the shoulder.
I will do the same with the left arm,
I will make sure that
it's in the continuity
of the current line of action
and I will slightly open the hand
so that we can clearly see the fingers
on the silhouette of the character
which wasn't the case previously.
While it might not look super natural,
I like to curl the fingers forwards.
It brings a lot of tension
as if our character was pushing the air.
During the whole process,
I will repeat the same
steps again and again.
Because it's very odd to push
a controller to its maximum
without comparing it to the other one.
Because the pose is to be read as a whole,
it's a relationship between the legs,
the torso, the arms, etc.
So whenever you're pushing the torso,
then you are rebalancing your
character by moving the feet
and it changes the pose.
But then maybe you want to
push this pose even further.
What I'm trying to explain here is that
you may need to repeat
the process several time
before you hit the right pose
or you hit the most extreme
pose or exaggerated pose
that still feels right.
As explained before in
the previous videos,
we are sculpting the pose.
And when you are sculpting,
you don't sculpt the details
of one hand or of the face
without looking at the whole
body of your character.
You generally already start looking
and then you refine each part one by one
and you refine them
depending on the other one.
You refine the proportion of
the head based on the chest
or the proportion of the
legs based on the arm, etc.
And don't fool yourself,
animation as an art form
is really comparable to
drawing or sculpting.
Because we are shaping
our whole character,
working on the relationship
between the shoulder,
the arms, the forearms,
the hands, the chest, the hips, etc.
So if you have fundamentals
into sculpting or drawing,
make sure you also apply them
whenever you are posing your
character for animation.
And if you don't have any fundamentals
in sculpting of drawing,
don't be afraid to study drawing
and sculpting techniques.
I'm not meaning that you
need to draw every day
or sculpt every day,
but at least read some
book about figure drawing
because you will see that
a lot of the vocabulary
we are using in this course,
or a lot of the fundamentals
we are using in this course
are applied in drawing and sculpting also.
So let's jump into the next
video and work on more poses.