- Before we jump into the next chapter,
there is a couple of more
poses I'd like to show you.
The first one is a katana pose
and we are going to use the
double-handed sword to do it.
The second pose is going
to be a flying knee.
For those two poses, I will go through
the analysis of the reference,
and then I will give you some
hints on how to improve them.
As usual, the first
thing you need to do is
to identify the line of
action in your character.
Since the character has
been swinging to his left,
there is big probabilities
that he was pushing
with his right leg.
We will also be able to
identify another line of action
going through the left leg.
It's interesting to
see all those two lines
form a triangular shape.
So this is something we
will have to try to match
in our pose.
From there as usual,
I'm drawing some lines on the character
to see the orientation of the face,
the orientation of the torso,
check the hips position
and outline some of
the interesting shapes.
Going to use anatomical
part as point of reference,
like the clavicles and the pecs
to figure out the chest orientation
or the eyes to figure
out the head orientation.
For this pose,
I advise you to switch
to inverse kinematics
for the arm controllers,
powering the weapon to the left hand.
From there, offset, a bit, the weapon
so that there is enough
room for the right hand
on the handle.
Then, as usual,
try to first match the right
position for the torso root.
In this case,
it is slightly twisted toward
the left arm of the character.
It is slightly leaning forward
and it is tilting toward the
right arm of the character.
Once your torso root is roughly posed,
you should pose the feet.
First, check out the
orientation of the feet,
and then double check that
your center of gravity is
currently aligned with those feet,
so that your character is balanced.
Finally, carefully watch
the knees orientation
and don't forget to use the pole targets
to rectify the leg's shape.
You will be able to see
the whole posing process
in a slow-paced time-lapse
in the next video.
When posing the arms,
double check the position of the elbows
and the position of the hands.
Watch for the angles made by the elbows
and carefully watch for hands orientation.
Then, use the shoulder
controller to reach those poses.
When working on the hands,
don't forget to use
the pan bone controller
and try to draw a nice
curling shape of the finger.
Make sure that your hand
doesn't look like a box.
Finally, don't forget that you can use
the sword controller to tweak
the sword orientation and position.
To push this pose,
you have to increase its directionality.
Since the center of gravity
is pushed to the right,
I will just push it even more.
And as the character is
slightly leaning to the left,
I will make him lean even more.
And since there is quite
a lot of spine twisting
engaged into this pose,
I will make the body twist even more.
The final touch was to fix some issues
regarding the initial pose.
On the initial pose,
the sword doesn't tread well
because it's overlapping with the body.
So while my first concern
was to make the character
look more dynamic,
I've also made sure that
the sword better reads
on the pushed pose.
For this new pose, as usual,
I'm looking for the line of action,
and since the character just jumped,
it's pretty easy to find it.
While the line of action is currently
supporting the motion of the character,
remember that we are here to translate
the motivation of the character.
And his purpose is currently
to hit his opponent
as hard as possible with his knee.
So when we are going to push this pose,
instead of focusing on the line of action,
I will focus on the
directionality of the knee
and make sure that the
whole pose of the character
supports this idea.
Once I was able to match
the reference pose,
I've pushed the pose of my character
so that we do feel the
directionality of the knee.
And it's to make your whole
character becoming a hero
pointing at the target.
I've shortened the angle of the left knee
so that it looks more pointy,
but I rotated the torso backward
so that it's more aligned
with the directionality of the knee.
And finally, I make sure that both arms
are supporting the current pose
and don't forget to support
the pose, even in the finger.
Make sure that the hands read
well and make the fingers
track toward their previous
position in the movement.
But you should also pose
the toes of the character.
Double check the orientation of the feet.
Basically check each
part of your character,
rotate around the pose and
make sure that each features of
the body are supporting the current pose
and make sure that the current pose
does translate or communicate
the will of the character.
This is the mindset you need to have
whenever you are creating a pose,
whether it's an action pose
like this one or an acting pose.
If your character is
feeling fear, for example,
how should his hand be
posed to translate the fear?
What kind of shape should his body make?
How do I pose the shoulder,
how do I pose the head?
What kind of shape do I do with the eyes?
So again,
whenever you are building
the pose, ask yourself
what it communicates
and if it does it well.
And if each part of the
character currently communicates
the same idea.
Use reference to get
a good quality of pose
and a good believability,
push the pose to better
communicate the idea
and connect with your audience,
whether it's for gameplay
animation or film animation.
This is the end of this video.
The next video will be the time-lapses
of the two different
poses we've just studied.
And I will see you in the next chapter.