- [Instructor] We are almost done
with our detailed blocking.
At this stage,
I am still searching for big changes
in the character pose momentum.
I check the poses I have
to see if they all communicate
the changes or forces or
momentum in the character body.
After the right cross,
there are two motions -
The one where the character
is pulling his right arm back,
and then where it is
anticipating the hook,
pulling his left arm back.
This is also the moment
where the character
is transferring his
weight onto the left leg.
As he does through those two poses,
the motion is pretty linear.
And every part of the chest
are moving at the same speed.
So the pose I'd like to add
is the entering V8 pose.
Where the chest will
drag compared to the hips
and the arms will drag too.
Toward the lower part of the body twisting
toward the left leg.
The upper part of the
body is dragging a bit
and so does the arms
before diving into the next pose.
So in the end, this is not
a very complicated pose.
We will favorize the next pose
with the root of the character
as the weight is shifting pretty
quickly onto the left leg,
but then you will rotate the
chest toward the previous pose.
And since the arms are dragging,
you will rotate them even
more toward the previous pose.
The trick is to track
the path of your elbows,
make sure that you twist
the chest a little backward
as it is dragging.
And from there, track the left arm joints
and make sure that they are dragging
into the hook anticipation.
As our character's recovering
from the hook and step back
before the switch kick,
there is no anticipation
between this settle pose
and the start of the jumping
into the switch kick.
Since it's a very fast
transition into the switch kick,
we just need a micro anticipation.
So it will be a down pose that will occur
over a couple of frames only
and that will have a very small amplitude.
It will just create an extra little motion
that will make the jumping to read better.
When you create an anticipation,
it's both for your
character to gather energy,
but also for your audience
to have the time to prepare
for the next move.
This is a pose that will be
relatively easy to create.
We just need to pull back a bit
to center of gravity, lower it,
and also move it a bit
toward the right leg.
And since the center of
gravity is moving down,
we will slightly raise the arms.
Raise the head.
Make every features of the body
that are further away
from the center of gravity
to drag a bit.
The almost last pose
we are going to create
is the smear pose during the hook.
As explained during the posing chapter,
this is an exaggeration pose
that will fake the motion blur
whenever we have a very fast motion.
The shape of the arms are here
to support the flow of the hook.
This is why from top view
it becomes an elliptic shape
so that it better communicates
the twisting of the body during the hook.
To pose the center of
gravity and the chest,
I'm using the breakdowner
and I am favorizing the next pose.
The Impact Pose.
Because the center of gravity in the chest
are currently leading the
motion compared to the arms.
They are pulling the shoulders
and pulling the arms.
So we need to favorize the
center of gravity in the chest
toward the next pose,
while the arms will be dragging.
So the method to create those mills
is to first create a natural pose,
the pose that your character
would have in real life
whenever he is throwing the punch.
And once you have the
right angle for the arm,
you can start pulling
the tweaker controller
to create a nice C
curve toward the target.
The most important
thing when you are doing
this kind of a smear pose
is to make sure that you foresee
the path of the elbow and the wrist,
and you make sure that you
align the arm along this path.
So it's very important to
rotate around your character
and jump between the
previous and next pose.
Once you've done the left arm,
work on the right arm and don't forget
that why we are creating
an exaggerated pose,
you should still pose the shoulders
to better position the arms
and also keep a believable pose,
a believable flow into your pose.
Finally, don't forget to
check the feet movement.
Whenever you are birding a strong pose
for a part of the body,
like the arms in this case,
we often forget to move the head,
move the feet, move the knees,
or move the hips.
So it's important not to over-focus
on one part on the character.
But since the kick is also a
very fast circular movement,
we will create a smear
for this motion too.
As for the hook,
I am first posing the center of gravity,
using the breakdowner, and
then tweaking its position.
The center of gravity and the
hips are leading the motion
and the foot is supposed to drag a lot.
Spacing-wise, when you're
making a striking motion,
you want to ease out of the anticipation.
So have a close spacing in
the beginning of the motion,
and then it accelerates before the impact.
The spacing between the impact
and the previous frame
should be the biggest.
I'm using the same principle
as for the previous pose.
I first bird a believable pose
or realistic pose, let's say.
Be extra careful
with the center of gravity,
hips, and chest position.
While during the first punch,
the momentum of our
character was out of balance
as he was punching forward.
In this case, he's spinning
around his right foot.
So your character must feel
balanced during this kick.
Plus, the hips and the chest
are leading the motion.
So if you don't get them right,
it will be harder then to get
the arms and the legs right.
Remember that this kind of pose
is made to support the flow of the motion.
So try to bird your arc
around the path
that the knee and the ankle
or the knee and the foot would take
to get to the target.
So make sure you refine your smear frame
so that you don't get any
weird angle on the leg.
Try to smooth it as possible
based on the rate possibilities.
Then since this part of
the animation is very fast,
I advise you to bird the previous pose.
The one where the foot is just taking off.
Use the breakdowner and align the foot
with the motion path
or the path you think it will take
to get to its target.
During this pose, the feet and the torso
are easing out from the previous pose.
Remember that you should
favorize the previous pose
as the feet is accelerating.
So it starts slow and
then go faster and faster
and travel more and more further away
from its starting point.
With all the poses we have created,
we should have enough
information to go into sparring.
But before, we should
fine tweak the timing
of our animation.
So we'll do this in the next video.