- [Instructor] Welcome to chapter eight.
In this chapter,
we will apply everything
we have learned so far
to create this 4 Hit Combo animation.
I will give you my best
advice to find good references
whenever you're starting
this animation process.
And I will also teach you some tricks
on how to use those reference
to plan your animation.
Then as we did in the previous chapter,
we'll go into the analysis
of the different poses
we are going to build.
From there, I will guide you
through the whole process
of creating this kind of animation
from the base blocking,
breakdown to creation,
and first pass of timing, blocking plus
adding even more poses
so that our animation is
perfectly readable in steady mode
to polishing our animation
and take it to the next level.
But this is a big chapter
and you should expect 10
to 20 hours of animation
to get to this result.
So stay strong, don't be afraid to fail
and let's get started.
(bag punching)