- [Instructor] So let's add
quick timing pass to our blocking.
so is that we convert all those poses
into something that will look
like an actual animation.
If you are doing the
same animation as I do,
here is a screen capture of my timing.
You may have noticed that
my key frame have colors.
In the dope sheet or the action editor
you can select keys and
press R to give them a color.
Those different colors
have a different label.
But those are just references.
They absolutely not affect
the way the keys will behave.
And they are just here to give you
a point of reference in your timeline.
I personally never use them,
but for the course it's
a good tool for you
to have a point in reference in time
whenever you are watching my content.
Regarding the timing pass in itself,
I advise you to work by chunks.
For example, I'm working on the timing
of the anticipation of the right cross,
the impact, and the overshoot.
And when this feels right,
I will try to time it
with the previous pose.
Remember that you can use the video
reference to time your blocking.
I want the first two punches
to flow pretty quickly.
Since I'm animating at
30 frame per second,
two to four frames between the
two punches should be enough.
This way I should get the
bam, bam I wanted initially.
With this first chunk done,
I can then work on the
second half of the animation.
But I want a pretty big
anticipation on the hook
to break the rhythm of the animation
and also give it more strength.
Though some poses are easier to time,
like the overshoot of the kick generally.
And overshoot is one or two frame
after the current hit
on the current extreme.
There, it's a lot of back and forth.
You have to play the animation a lot,
then move some of the keys and see
if the flow is getting better.
I would also recommend you to share
your work at this stage if you can.
It's always very valuable to
have fresh eyes upon your work,
even if it's not a professional animator.
When you're animating all day long,
you easily get over focused
and you have a hard time
spotting what's wrong or
right into your animation.
So as you can see, I played
the animation several time,
and then I decided to whether increase
or decrease the length of a pose.
Here for example, I will
make the anticipation
from the hook a little longer.
It will bring more power to the hook.
One last advice I'd like to remind you,
give yourself some space at
the end of the animation.
This way you will clearly identify
when the animation is finishing
and when it's restarting.
It will remove the visual
noise of your character
jumping from one position to the other.