- [Instructor] It's time
to prepare our Blender file.
First, let's get rid of
everything by pressing A
to select all the object
and X to delete them.
From there, we need to link our first rig.
So while you go to File,
Link, go into the folder
of chapter eight
and select the, "Punching Bag" file.
Choose the, "Collection" folder
and here you will find
only one collection.
Just double click it.
Click the arrow next
to the orange collection to unfold it
and right click on the sub-collection,
go to ID data,
and choose make library
override hierarchy.
Now both the punching bag object
and armature are available.
In the viewport changing option,
I will enable textures.
Now I will select the armature
and press control tab
to enter, "Poles Mode."
The main rotation
controller will allow you
to swing the punching bag.
The blue controllers are
a forward kinematic chain.
You are free to rotate,
scale or move them.
The yellow controller
on the tree curve bone.
They are perfect to
create the impact frames.
There is also a controller
to move the chains,
but I don't think we are
going to move this one.
Finally,
you will find a root controller
to move the whole rig in space.
We need to link our character
so we can go to file link.
I will go in the folder
of chapter five and click the,
"Trident Rig" final file.
From there going to collection
and choose, "Trident
Character Collection",
no click the arrow next
to, "Trident Character Collection"
and right cheek on the sub collection,
go to ID data and choose,
"Make library override hierarchy."
We now need to load
our rig script
to do so.
Open the text editor
instead of the timeline.
Then in the middle of the top bar
of the detail.
Click the folder to open
the punching bag rig UI.
Once the script is open,
go to text and click the register option.
From there,
you can press the play button
in the top bar of the text editor.
This will enable the
UI of the punching bag,
which is very busy with a few layers.
From there.
Repeat the process and go
to folder number five and search
for the Trident rig script.
Again, go to text register
and then press the play button.
From there.
Let's open the action detail
where we will be able
to access the king set
of our different rigs.
I will start with the character.
I will switch from dope
sheet to action editor,
and I will simply
duplicate decaying action,
but I will rename
the action combo blocking
on there in the field of view,
I will press control tab
to get back into, "Object Mode,"
select the rig off our punching bag
and do the same process.
Duplicate the current action
and rename it, "Combo blocking back."
Then I will go back onto the Trident rig
and in the rig properties,
I will disable the visibility
of all the weapons.
Then I will hide the controllers
of the weapons.
And in the head and neck properties
I will make sure
that the, "Head follow," is disabled
and the, "Neck follow," is enabled.
This animation we are going
to use arm forward kinematic
with the, "Arm follow," disabled
on both arms.
From there let's position,
the heavy bag or punching bag.
I will switch to object mode,
select it and press control tab
to switch to, "Post Mode."
Let's select the root bone
and set it's Z position to 0.2 meters
and Y position to minus 1.5 meters.
(swoosh)
Now I like to change the model preview,
so I will go to the
viewport shading option,
switch to flat and enable
cavity and shadows.
I think it offers a better readability
of the models.
A little tip here, select a both armature
in object mode, then press control tab,
and you will be in pause mode
on both amateur at the same time.
This way, no need to jump back and forth
into object mode to be able to select one
or the other armature.
As soon as you are selecting one
or the other armature,
the, "Action editor" will update.
As for our previous exercises,
I will open a new window on the right side
of the screen and create a new 3D view
to preview our poses from another angle.
One last thing I'd like to add
before we get started is a ground object.
This will help us
to define the contact pose of the feet.
So I will press control tab to go back
into, "Object Mode." Press shift A
and add the plane.
I will scale it up and press control A
to apply all the transformations.
From there, I will create a new material
for this ground object
that I will call, "The Ground."
I will give it a dark gray color,
and I will reduce the specularity to 0.1.
This way we won't have any visual noise.
Whenever we are previewing our render
with fancy reflections
and stuff like that.
From there, I will add up
to the viewport display option and set it
to a dark gray color
so that it's not too distract-ive
and not too aggressive to the eyes.
I will rename this flat object ground
and I will move it in the scene collection
in the, "Filter Menu,"
I will enable the selection restriction
and they will make the ground unselectable
so that we won't be
selecting it by accident.
Now, the final tip to be
able to pose our character
from the bottom view is
to head up to the shading option
and enable, "Back face culling,"
This way, whenever we
are facing the back face
of the plane, it becomes transparent.
From there, you can
reorganize your collection,
get treated of any useless collection
so that we just have our
character collection,
heavy bag collection
and our ground object.
And we can get started.