- [Instructor] If you've
watched the previous chapter,
it's no surprise for you that
the first thing we need to do
is search for references.
This video, I will show
you what I'm looking for
in my references and how I
use them to plan my animation.
I'm convinced that we are in
the golden era of learning,
or there is a bunch of stupid
things on the internet,
and you can waste your whole
life watching funny cats
and stuff like that.
Nowadays, you can find tutorials
for almost everything in life.
You won't necessarily get good
references from tutorials,
but you can learn a lot about
the purpose of a stance,
the purpose of a footwork,
how the body's supposed to be moved
to land an accurate
switch kick, for example.
Watching this kind of video
would bring your attention
to small details, whether they
are cultural or technical.
And those little details
will bring believability
and authenticity to your animation.
So it's always a good move
to mix your references
with watching tutorials.
And you should not limit you
references to real life videos.
You can use drawings,
you can use video games,
you can use movies.
One of the most important thing
is that you enjoy the
reference you've taken
because whatever is appealing
to you in this video,
it will stimulate you to put
them into your own animation.
Finally, when it comes
to real life references,
try to find the references
from the master on their art.
Since I want to do a Muay Thai combo,
I'm watching for references
featuring the masters
at this art, like Saenchai,
Jacquot, Liam Harrison,
or Jonathan Haggerty.
Then you need to plan your own animation.
If you are working in the movie industry,
you will probably have a
storyboard or an animatic.
If you're working for games,
you will probably have a list of moves
provided by the game designers.
And if you are working for yourself,
then you can choose whatever
kind of move you want to do.
But I advise you to do a
minimum of planning ahead
and then edit your references accordingly.
In my case, I want to
do a left jab, a cross,
followed by a powerful hook,
and then going into a switch kick.
It's a pretty common combo
in kickboxing and Muay Thai
and, animation wise, it's interesting
because the first two
punches are straight,
then the second draw a nice curve,
and the last move draw
an even bigger curve.
So we will have a nice contrast in shapes.
I've gathered multiple
references from different people
doing the same move.
And then using a video editing software,
you can use a Blender, for example,
I make sure I'm syncing
all the videos together.
And I use the extreme to do it.
In this case, the different hits
of the punches and the kick.
Finally, don't hesitate
to rework the timing
of your references until
you get a nice rhythm.
You can slow some parts,
accelerate other, or just cut in.
No, listen to the hits on the reference.
(men yell)
Now, what I will do is
that I will cut the sound
and only keep the impact.
(punches thwap)
(men yell)
And it goes like, pum-pum, pum, pum.
So while I was looking
for contrast in the motion
of the reference, there is
also contrast in the rhythm.
And if at some point you
have some linear reason
into your reference, use video editing
to get to a mock contrasted rhythm.
And the best way to do it
is to do it with your mouth.
Make the sound and the
rhythm with your mouth,
tum, tum, tum, tum,
and change it to ta-tum, tum, tum.
Once you find a good rhythm,
just edit your references
and go to the next step.
With my reference exported,
the first thing I do
is that I load it into
SimSketch or Keyframe Pro.
From there, I will
scrub through the video.
And I need to identify the
golden poses or the extreme.
I'm looking at the poses
where the character
are the most impactful.
So it's generally the moment
where they hit the bag
or just one frame after,
as the punch goes a bit through the bag.
For those first punches,
this is the moment where the
body is fully in extension.
And I will then do the same with the hook
and the kick.
Then I will try to spot
the contrasting poses.
In this case, the
anticipation for the hook
and the anticipation for the kicks.
Once I spot them, we
can analyze those poses.
So, as we did in the previous chapter,
the first thing I'm looking
at are the line of action.
On the idle stance,
the weight is generally
on the rear foot so that
they can block incoming kicks
with the front leg or the front shin.
Which means the line of
action will generally go
through the punching fist and
the real leg that is pushing.
On the hook, the energy generally come
from the front leg and the hips.
And finally, on the kick,
it's quite easier to identify
by just watching the
silhouette of the character.
One goes from the pushing foot
and the other on the swinging leg.
From there, I will be looking
at the secondary shape
exactly as we did during
the previous chapter.
They generally help to
define the silhouette
of the character once we have
defined the line of action.
From there, I will go more into detail
and I will try to define
the orientation of the chest
using the shoulder line,
the orientation of the hips,
and the orientation of
the head using the eyes.
I'm also drawing lines
on the tip of the feet
so is that I can remember
that I need to double check
the orientation of the feet.
It's super important.
It's super important to pay
extra attention to the feet
because they will directly
influence the hips' orientation.
And we need an extra attention
for this specific animation
because footwork in combat
sport is super important,
as it delivers power and balance
and so it will bring
believability to your animation.
So once you've done this
for your golden poses,
you will have to do it for
the breakdowns, et cetera.
So now that know my reference workflow,
let's jump into the next video where we
will start blocking our animation,
using the key poses we have defined here.