- [Instructor] The time has finally come
to start polishing our
animation and jump into spline.
To make the 3D space as clear as possible,
I will just hide the camera rig.
From there, we need to
switch our interpolation mode
from step to bezier.
So what I will do is that
in the action editor,
I will press Control + Tab to
switch to the graph editor.
Then I will make sure that
I display all the curves
by enabling the Show Hidden option.
And on top of this,
I will press Alt + H to make sure
that I have no curve or
transform channel hidden.
From there, we can press
Control + Tab again
and switch to the action editor.
Press A to select all
the keys, and then T,
and choose Bezier.
Then select the punching
bag and do the same.
Now if we play our animation,
it's no longer in step mode.
We have interpolation between the keys.
And since we've built a
very detailed blocking,
our animation already looks pretty good.
This is why I've been very insistent
whenever I was telling you not to jump
into spline too early on,
because now our work will
mostly to improve the animation,
rather than fix issues.
Before I jump into the graph editor,
I will rework a bit of the
timing of the animation
by moving some of the keys here and there.
Since we have the bag that is supposed
to be synchronized with the character,
it would be better to use the Dope Sheet
so that we can move all
the keys from the bag
and the character at the same time.
Again, I will make sure
that the Show Hidden option is enabled.
And as I want to make sure
I won't be moving the keys
from our camera rig,
I will lock all the channels.
And from there, I will make
some artistical choices.
So it's harder to justify
that pure mechanical choice,
but I felt like the impact of the hook
wasn't that impressive.
So maybe I should hold for a
couple of additional frames
the overshoot of the hook.
So from there what we can do
is select all the key
frames after frame 45,
and we can offset to beat those keys
whether toward the end of the animation
to hold the pose longer.
Or if you want to shorten it,
get it closer to the
beginning of your animation.
The other moment in the animation
I spot wasn't looking
that good at this stage,
so it's very rough, it's very floaty,
but still, you can feel the
animation, is the switch kick.
It's the moment where the character
stepped back into the switch.
I was hesitating whether
to make the character
jump as soon as he
reaches the extreme back,
or make him hold the beat down
before he make the jump
to the switch kick.
In the end, I've chosen to make him jump
into the switch kick as soon
as he hit the down pose.
So what I did is that I've
selected all the keys.
As you can see, I've made a test
where I've made his down pose longer,
but then I've moved it backward
so that he instantly jump into the switch.
It's now time to jump
into the graph editor.
So I've pressed Control + Tab
to switch to the graph editor.
And as always, I will start by polishing
the root of my character.
And I always start with its location.
You know it's like the bouncing ball,
we are not playing with squash and stretch
unless we have figured out the position
of the ball in space.
Now I will press Q to
access my quick favorite
and calculate the motion path
of the current torso controller.
And I will be only
calculating the motion path
from a frame of five to 30 or 25.
Because I will stop polishing
my animation by chunk,
I won't be polishing the
root on the whole animation.
That will be a nightmare to
handle and very odd to track.
So what I do is that I select
a part of the animation
that I feel is clearly defined,
in this case, the jab cross motion.
And I will work on this part
until I feel it's satisfying,
and then move to the next one.
It doesn't mean that I won't come back
to this part later on.
But at least I feel like
it's more satisfying
to polish a part, feel like it looks good,
and then jump to the other part,
than trying to polish the
whole animation at once.
Now let's talk about the curve.
What I want to do is to bring
as much contrast and impact
into this animation as possible.
I want it to be super snappy.
So the idea is to hold a bit longer
your character back when he's back.
And when he's moving forward,
move it in faster and
jump into the other shoot.
So if we have a look at the edited curve,
the Y channel is the
back and forth channel
of our character, so, basically,
the motion that helps him
to punch into the bag.
As you can see, that from four to eight,
the character is slowly moving forward
as he's taking his step forward.
And then, from eight to 12,
he's moving really faster
while he's punching,
while it was way more linear previously.
Then we have a plateau shape
between frame 12 and 16.
But this is the transition into the cross.
So the character is still moving forward,
but at a very slow speed.
And then there is a big drop forward
so that the character move
very fast from from 16 to 18
when he's punching with the right cross.
Regarding the Z curve,
I'm just wanting my character
to squat before he pushes.
So I further rised the first poses
and lowered the Z curve at the beginning.
Then as he push, he's raising a bit,
but he's not jumping,
he's pushing forward.
So don't create a too big overshoot.
Then he's diving into the right cross.
And as he punch, he's going straight.
There is a quick dive, then a plateau,
then he's recovering.
From there, I've been working
on the rotation of the root.
And I did approach the rotation a bit
as I did for the forward momentum,
meaning that I've tried to contrast it.
I'm starting with the X rotation curve,
which allow us to make our character
lean forward and backward.
So what I did is that I've just made him
slightly bend backward,
when he was dropping in the beginning,
as his torso is dragging.
And then, I will make
him lean into the punch.
So I haven't moved this curve that much,
because it wasn't needed from
the rocking we have done.
The curve I did put more work
on was the Z rotation curve,
because at this stage, it's
allows the character to twist
and the power of a punch
is all about twisting.
In the beginning when the
character is moving forward,
I've input the new information
we didn't have during the blocking,
is that I've slightly pushed up the curve
so that the torso of the
character is opening a bit,
and it creates a little anticipation
for the left jab that will
twist the opposite way
a couple of frames later.
Then to bring contrast to the animation,
what I did is that I
created a slight plot.
And then we are rapidly transitioning
into the opposite twisting
during the right cross
and there is a very slight overshoot.
Instead of our initial stimulus
with our curve we have here,
I have something that is more contrasted.
On there, I'm taking my
character from all angle
and I work on the other
curve just to eliminate
any pops or any weird
changing the direction.
For example, here, the X
location of the character
is going right, then left, then right.
So I'm just stabilizing the character
while he's punching with his right cross,
his weight is going over
the left leg, and that's it.
He's no longer bouncing right and left.
But once I'm done with my root,
I generally work on the feet.
That's because the contacting point
has a lot of influence
on the rest of the body,
so I like to time them
as soon as possible.
I want to make the foot
accelerating forward,
so easing forward,
by scaling the first pose.
And I want to get rid of
this straight leg pose
that doesn't look natural at all,
so I will offset the curve by one frame.
Then I've converted it to vector
because I want the foot
to plant on the ground
so it does a hard stop.
And from there, I will duplicate
a couple of key of the Z curve
and slightly push it up at the
time the foot is traveling.
This will create a subtle step,
instead of having the foot
sliding on the ground.
And we can quickly work
on the heel controller
using the X rotation.
As the character move forward,
his weight is more on to the left leg.
So we can lower a bit the heel,
slightly raise it mid-air,
and then set it to zero and to vector
and just half turn the foot
contact with the ground,
so that the heel will slam on the ground.
Now you can work on the bit
of overlapping motion for the toes.
Select the main toe controller.
Once the leg has left the ground,
rotate a bit the toes down
as they are dragging
toward the previous pose.
And as the leg touch the ground,
rotate them up a bit.
And then, one or two frame later,
flatten them on the ground.
From there we can work on the right foot.
And it doesn't feel natural at all
to have the right foot moving
at the same time as the front foot
as if our character was floating.
So we need to offset the
motion by at least one frame.
This will straighten a bit the back leg
so it feels way more
natural that the back leg
is getting pulled and no longer pushing.
It's pushing while throwing the left jab,
but then it's getting dragged by the body.
Since it's sliding on the ground,
we don't have to work
on the Z location curve.
But one thing that is bothering me
is the orientation of the knee.
It's a lot pointing on the outside.
So I will rework rapidly
the position of the knee
by changing the position
of the pole target
and offsetting it mainly
using the X location curve.
For this specific case,
don't focus on the graph editor.
Just focus on the shape of the leg
and remember that your
knee is more or less
aligned with your foot.
So having the knee pointing
to the outside is very weird.
I'm just fixing this.