- The next pose I'd like
to add to my animation
is the subtle,
just after the other
shoot of the cross punch.
To our right cross default pose,
we have created a pose where
everything is extended forward
so that it better
communicate impact and speed.
As a smear frame, this kind
of pose can't last too long,
or it will really looks weird.
So we need to burn a subtle pose,
where we get rid of all the exaggeration,
the chest we'll get back in place.
The hips will catch up and the right arm
will recover it's normal size.
Not that the left arm is doing
an overshoot and finishing
it's ark by getting a little straighter.
So building this pose is
going to be pretty straight
forward.
I will pull the beat to
the center of gravity back
and I will reset the location on all the
bones on the arm so that
it's not stretched anymore.
I will do the same with
the IEPs and the chest.
And then, I will reset or transform
on the tweaker bone, along the chain
of the spine.
We have used those bones to fix the shape
of the torso when it was extended,
but we don't need them anymore.
It's in the chest to the right.
And as the left arm was a
swinging back during the previous
frames,
I will spread a bit more
the whole arm chain as it is
finishing its motion back.
So compared to the previous pose
I have built during the blocking stage,
I've kept the character
way straighter this time.
I was initially planning to make him dive
into the anticipation for the hook,
but the character look way out of balance.
I prefer that he pulled back his right arm
so that the right leg can catch up
and then dive into the
anticipation for the hook.
So we do need to build the pose
where the right foot is catching up.
If we watch the previous pose,
we have built and the
next one in the animation
that we can see that as the right foot
is going forward, the
chest is going backwards
into a more neutral pose.
We are going to break the position between
where the right foot is still traveling,
and so our characters center of gravity
is more to while that the left leg.
He's still lightweight on his right foot
and pulling it.
This is why I raised the heel as the hips
are leading the animation because
they are dragging the character backward
the chest is dragging. So
does the right arm chain,
but they have already
started to move backward.
Particularly the lower
part of our character
is visualizing the next
pose, while the upper
part is visualizing the previous pose.
On this lead there is not that much
to say about the posing process
whenever I'm building
these specific in-between.
So I will jump to the next pose.
As usual, you will find a slow paced
time-lapse of the whole processes
that you can follow along.
(wind rushing)
The next area of our
animation is, that really
lacks information, is the step-
back after the kick.
We have already built the pose where
our character is pulling his left leg back
after the kick, then going
into the contact pose,
and then it's idle pose,
right leg goes back
and supports to weight of the character.
But we do need to create the poses where
our character will be
pulling his right leg.
Then when the right leg
is going to contact,
then you can even create a down pose.
Before you settle into the idle pose.
To start positioning the torso controller,
you can press shift E to
activate the break down there.
And then you can slightly offset
the torso controller to the
left, on top of the left leg that is going
to support the weight
of the character as the
left leg is supporting the weight
of the character, I'm
concealing the rotation
of the heels is that
it's in contact with the
ground and they've slightly pushed
the left foot into the ground,
to fake body pressure.
Then you can slightly lean your
character to the left as he's pulling
his right leg up.
Normally I will slightly clench or pose
the chest by twisting it to the right.
Since the hips are twisting the other way
to pull the right leg.
Finally, you can relax a bit the arms
by spreading them. In this case,
the right leg looks a little bit too
over extended, so I
will slightly raise the
foot as it starts traveling backwards.
We know of the pose where
the foot is taking off,
we need to create the post where the foot
is just contacting the ground.
As usual, you need to first think of the
position of the center of gravity.
The feet are traveling faster.
So the center of gravity will still
be more onto the left
foot, which is supporting
the weight, but also more forward.
It will catch up the right leg later on.
It's a common beginner mistake
to see the center of gravity
traveling as fast as
the feet. But generally
your center of gravity,
starting to move backward
The front foot is taking off, then it will
land, and then the center
of gravity will catch-up.
From there, since our
character is more relaxed
than during the punches,
I'm trying to make the
arm strike a bit. So if the body
is moving backward, I will slightly
rotate the arm forward.
If the body's going down,
I will slightly rotate the arm up
and I will do the same with the neck
and the head of the character.
You can track the chin of your character.
For example, if the body is going down,
or the center of gravity is going down,
slightly rotate the head backwards
so that the chin is raising it.
(wind rushing)
While our character is moving back.
You can take this opportunity to
pose the punching bag as
it lands on the ground.
So, instead of making each landing flat,
I will slightly raise the tip of the bag.
And then on the next pose, I will push it
further away so that it
seems to slide on the
ground. Just push it a
touch, don't move it too
far away or it will looks weird.
(wind rushing)
Another area of the
animation, where the feet
are changing location
and we haven't created
the contacting pose, is the jab.
As usual to get the right location for the
left foot I will go on to the jab pose.
I will press control C to copy the pose
of the left foot, go to a previous frame
and press control V. From there I can
tweak the foot rotation
and the heel rotation.
Remember what we have said before,
the feet move faster than
the center of gravity.
So using the break downer, I will create
the pose for the center of gravity,
favoring the previous pose.
So if we compare the pose of our
character on the previous frame
and on the jab frame, and now we
watch the transition
frame we are currently
building. Foot is moving faster
than the center of
gravity. As the character
is pushing with his right leg,
the center of gravity is likely
shifting toward the left foot.
Don't forget to also twist the
center of gravity towards the left foot,
increasing the range and
the strength of the punch.
Another detail regarding this pose
is that I've opened, a bit, the fingers
so that it feels like they are dragging
back as the character
is moving fast forward.
The finger of the right hand are relaxed,
are bending backward as
they are dragging back.
This is the kind of detail that
could have been added
during the polishing stage.
But if you think of something during the
looking stage, you should the block it
because you may forget it afterwards.