- [Instructor] In this video,
we are going to set up our camera.
Initial goal of this combo animation
is not to teach you how
to frame your character.
I think the camera now will
help us take some decision
during the position stage.
Since I don't have a clear direction
regarding the framing of this animation,
it wasn't planned ahead,
what I'm doing is that I'm
just positioning my 3D view
and see how I can frame my character.
Play a few frame of the
animation and see if it works.
By default Blender 3D view is set
to a 50 millimeter focal length.
So this is something we
have to take in account
whenever we are trying
to frame our character,
pretty freely for the time being.
On the initial pose when
I'm facing the character,
it looks pretty cool.
His base pose reads pretty
well and we do understand
that his objective is the punching bag.
But when I play the animation,
the punches don't look that powerful
and the character is
often hidden by the bag.
When we have build those first poses,
we have intentionally
created straight shapes
for our character.
So there are big chances that those shapes
will read well from side view.
In this regard, we will probably
favorize a side view for
those two initial punches.
Whether we are facing the
inside of the character
or the outside or back of the
character, when he's punching.
While I'm pretty convinced of the framing
for the beginning of the combo,
when the hook happened, I
don't feel like it reads well.
While if I rotate the 3D
view to face the character,
I better see the anticipation and I also
better see the arc built by the fists.
So I know that I will have to
transition from a side view
to a more frontal view of the character.
Also I think like it looks a little better
when we get closer to the
ground to frame the hook.
The characters look more impressive
and he's dominating the view.
Now regarding the kick,
the anticipation looks
very good from there
but the character get hidden by the bag
during the kicking pose.
And there is a lot of
verticality into the pose
so I feel like we lose a bit
the orientation of the kick.
While if we continue
rotating a bit the camera,
we get a very interesting framing
because we can see the
eyes of our character
in the negative space drawn
by the leg and the arm.
We still I've have a very strong
orientation of the kicking pose,
so it doesn't ruin all the
work we have done before.
One thing we can do to improve
those close range action shot
is to increase the angle of view
by reducing the focal
length of our 3D view.
I will switch from 50 to 30 millimeters
and while it doesn't really
improve the side view,
when it comes to spinning strikes,
like the hook or the kick,
it does look way better for sure.
The characters look stronger
and the arcs reads way better.
Finally, that will be cool if in the end,
the punching bag was still framed
and projected away from the camera.
Because it communicates the fact
that our character has extra human power
and he kicked so hard that he has
broken the chains of the punching bag.
So it does improve the
understanding of the current shot,
so it does improve staging.
Now regarding the camera initial position,
here is a cool trick I've
learned from Daniel Dettol
while I was working on
this specific animation.
He explained me that it's
better to set the camera
so that it rotates the
opposite way as the character.
Our character is pivoting
around this side of the bag.
So if we place the camera to the side
and we follow the motion of the character,
we will mostly be looking at his back.
Plus in the end, we will probably have to
revise the camera
position a little backward
to be sure that we properly
frame the kicking pose.
But why if we place the
camera on the other side?
We will have a continuous
rotation of the camera,
with an easing at the end into the kick,
and it will move the opposite
way of the character.
So it will increase the rotation feeling.
When you are following
a car on the highway,
you feel like the car is pretty static.
While when the car is running
the opposite direction as you're,
both speed are added on top of each other,
and it feels like it goes super fast.
So let's add our camera.
If it's not already the
case go to your preferences,
add on, and search for camera,
and activate the camera, add camera rigs.
This is the same add on we've been using
for our squirrel character scene.
From there make sure
you are in object mode,
press Shift, A, go to camera,
and add a dolly camera rig.
With the dolly camera rig object selected
press Control, Tab to switch to pose mode.
But we need to create an
action to control the camera.
So I will switch to the action editor,
create a new action,
give it a relevant name,
and click the shield icon
so that I'm sure I won't lose the section.
With all the camera controllers selected
I will press I to insert the
key frame on all transformed.
Or you can choose to use
only rotation and location
since there is no scaling
influencing the camera frame.
From there, I'm testing each controller
and see what range of
motion I can have with them.
For example, this one, I can just move it.
I can't rotate it nor scale it.
So I will just get rid of
all the transform channel
but the location transform channels.
The camera offset controller
can be moved and rotated, but not scaled.
So I will get rid of the
scaling transform channels.
I know that the aim controller
can only be moved in space,
it can't be rotated nor scaled,
and the root controller
can be moved and rotated,
but the scaling has no (indistinct)
so I can get rid of them.
You can basically key
frame any of the properties
of the camera but in the end the only one
we are going to use is the focal length.
So I'm going to add another key
frame onto the focal length.
From there I will switch
my secondary 3D view
to the camera view by pressing zero.
From there I will use the
main camera controller
to move the camera, and the aim controller
to target whatever I want to be framed.
I advise you to only use
those two controllers,
that's way enough.
And the less controller you will use,
the smoother will be your camera motion.
But my next advice is to push
the passepartout opacity to 100%.
This way you won't see what's out of frame
and it won't distract you.
And what you will have on screen
will be what will be outputted
whenever you are going
to render your animation.
From there, animate your camera
using the less key frame as possible.
First find the right
position for the first frame
while the camera stays still,
then find the position of the camera
whenever it's facing the
character for the hook motion.
From there reach the kicking pose
and set the camera and the aim target
so that you frame it as you have planned
And whenever you are moving the 3D view.
Then everything is about smoothing
the motion using the graph editor.
I must say that I'm not a
specialist of camera framing
or camera shooting as a gameplay animator
so I will keep it as simple as possible.
But if you're up to, watch
as much anime reference,
movie reference, whatever
style of animation you like,
and try to understand how the camera move.
This is the best way to learn.
Just watch other animation
and try to mimic their camera style.
So as explained before, I'm
just setting a key frame
on those two controllers
on the golden poses.
I'm slightly traveling toward
the bag until frame 25.
Then on frame 41, I'm lowering the camera,
I'm reducing the focal
length to 30 millimeters,
and then I make sure that
I'm facing the character.
Just focus on your current composition,
on the current pose, on the current frame.
Tweak the target and
tweak the camera position
until you are happy with
what you are framing
during the punch and
during the anticipation,
and then go directly to the kicking pose.
In my case, it's going to
be frame 74 and from there,
I don't care about the camera motion
or what it has been doing before.
I'm just focusing on framing the character
so that I check all the
details I wanted to have.
I want to read the
directionality of the kick.
But since my character is watching left,
I want to frame him on the
right third of my camera.
And finally, I want to make
sure that I read well his head
in the negative space
drawn by his leg and arm.
From there I will jump on the frame
where the bag hit the ground,
and I will make sure that
I'm framing everything.
From there, load the camera
in the beginning of your animation.
So duplicate the keys on frame zero
until frame five or seven.
What we don't want is
the camera to stop moving
as the character hasn't stopped moving.
Once you are done make
sure that you are easing
into the different camera position.
Think of the camera as a very heavy object
so you can move it fast,
but it won't settle into
the next pose very quickly.
As an example, let's take
the X location channel
off the camera controller.
There is a very fast motion
between frame 25 and frame 38,
but the camera reaches its
final position only on frame 48.
So it's easing until frame 48.
So basically your graph
editor will look like that.
You will have a pose,
then you will have a next extreme pose.
So it could be the motion between
the straight punch and the hook.
And what I do to make
the camera ease is that
I will duplicate the extreme movement
by 10 frame for example,
and then I will move
the value of the curve
where the camera was supposed to stop
towards the previous frame a little bit.
This way the camera
will continue on moving,
but it will slow down until
it reaches its final position.
This is pretty easy to use
illustrate with this cube.
When it does only two keys,
it slows until its final
pose pretty rapidly.
But if we modify its curve
as we did previously,
we do feel like the cube is slowing down
as if it was heavier so
it looks way more natural.
So now that you have your extreme poses
for your camera controller,
you should do this on each channels.
The thing is that once you have created
this easing on all your channel,
you can perfectly switch
back to the action editor
and offset the keys if you're not happy
with the timing of your motion.
But at least you have
created this natural feeling.
But now to add some extra
detail to your camera.
Spot the frame where your
character is hitting the bag,
then select the aim
controller of the camera
and select the Z location curve.
What we'll do is that on
each impact on the bag,
we will add a slight noise modifier
to create a camera shape.
To get access to the modifier stack,
make sure you have at
least one key active,
one key you have clicked.
From there in the modifiers panel,
click add modifier and choose noise.
Your whole curve will become a mess.
So we need to restrict the frame range
of the noise modifier by
clicking the checkbox.
From there start your
noise on that impact frame,
the frame 43, and end it
five or six frame later.
And then make sure that you blend
out of the noise over
five frame for example.
From there, make sure you reduce
the strength of the noise modifier
or the camera will shake as if
a T Rex was entering the stage.
The value of 0.1 should be enough.
And this is exactly the same
setup I've created off camera.
Then you can copy the current modifier
by clicking this icon.
Then you can paste it a couple of time,
clicking the icon next to it.
Put the next impact on the bag
and then set the second
noise modifier accordingly.
In this case, the kick occur on frame 74
and the noise stop on frame 80.
And I have increased the strength to 0.2
since the kick is a more powerful strike.
So it makes the camera
shake a little more.
And then for the third noise modifier,
I've set the range around the frame 95,
when it hits the ground.