- Let's go ahead with the next pose,
the right cross.
While I have chosen not to push
the pose too far for their job.
For this specific pose,
if you compare my current
pose to the reference,
I've pushed my character way further.
While the left jab is settle punch,
to get closer to the target
and mask the next punch.
This right cross is made
to destroy the target.
So to bury this pose, I'm
applying the principle
we've learned in the previous chapter.
I'm looking for the specific
features of this pose,
like the foot orientation,
the distance between them,
the orientation of the torso,
and the position of the center of gravity
based on the feet position.
On the right cross,
the center of gravity is
shifting towards the left leg.
So the front foot get
flattened on the ground,
while the right foot twist
towards the left foot
and its heel get traced.
The torso is twisting toward the left foot
and the shoulders are aligned
to create a straight line
toward the target.
But since we have already
identified the marker of this pose
I am already pushing the character.
I've built a wider stance with the feet.
I've lowered the center of gravity
and the line of action is pushed forward.
It's more oriented toward the impact,
but instead of keeping the
left elbow against the rib cage
I've raised it backward,
so that both arms from the profile view
creates a straight line.
This way even the back arm
or left arm is supporting the
directionality of the punch.
Once I'm done with this,
I will slightly twist
and tilt the neck toward
the right shoulder.
I'm exaggerating the
previous concept we have seen
where the character is protecting his face
and his chin using his shoulder.
One little detail I like to point out
is the way I slightly
twist the punching fist
so that the thumb is pointing down.
This is the way you have
to throw a straight punch,
whether it's across or a
jab to avoid overextension
of the elbow that can lead to injuries,
but it's also a way to get through
the guard of your opponent.
But once you're done
with your character pose
don't forget to also
pose the punching back.
So I've rotated the main controller
so that we can start swinging the bag.
And then I'm using the
tweaker bone to shape it
so that we feel like the
fist is getting through it.
Don't worry if you have
a hard time following
everything I'm doing here.
I will then provide a
slow paced time-lapse
showing the whole process so
that you can follow along.
Here I am trying to give you a guidance
to what you have to look
for and what is your goal
whenever you are creating
those different poses.
The next pose is the
anticipation of the hook.
Since the punching bag
just received a heavy blow
and is no longer in
contact with the character,
I've decided to pose it first.
I'm simply canceling
all the transformation,
and then I'm gonna rotate it
away using the main controller.
But one super important tip
whenever you are building
a new pose with your character,
is to cancel the rotation
of the chest, the hips, and
even the torso root controller.
First of all, it pushes
you to rethink about
the current pose instead of building it
based on the previous pose.
You will better watch your reference
and try to match it, so it
will improve your focus,
and secondly, it will avoid
you to source mistakes
from the previous pose.
Especially when it comes
to hips and chest twisting.
Now as usual, I've
repositioned the feet first,
and then I'm working on the torso.
Both the reference and the pushed pose
shows that the character
has both of his feet flat.
The character is gathering energy.
So he's twisting toward the left.
Since he will twist to
right to deliver the hook,
his weight and center
of gravity is shifted
toward the left foot.
Both arms are bent, the
right arm is bent in front
of the character to protect his face,
while the left arm is slightly
more open and slightly lower,
preparing to fire a big
punch into the next pose.
As usual, I work the
shoulder lines and the arms
so that I get a nice curve.
The arm and the shoulder
flow into an elliptic shape.
It supports the twisting of the character
and it communicates the
fact that our character
is going to swing the other way.
Once you are done, don't
hesitate to play the animation
even if there is no timing.
It's just a good way to see if the flow
between the different
poses is okay for you.
And you will get more
familiar with your animation.
When jumping into the next pose, again,
it's interesting to have a quick look
to the video reference.
As usual, my goal is to spot if the feet
are changing of location,
and the right feet
is currently moving forward.
I will work exactly as I
did for the previous pose.
I will first work on the
foot supporting the weight.
Rotating each a bit inward.
I will move the center of gravity
toward the supporting leg.
Move forward the right leg,
as we have seen on the video.
And then I will cancel
the rotation on the hips,
on the torso controller, and on the chest,
and build the whole
torso pose from scratch.
I decided to make the hook to the head,
because the previous punch is pretty low,
this way by changing the
level we are hitting,
we bring contrast to our animation
and so it will be more appealing.
From there make sure that
you're applying the rules
we have seen in the previous chapter.
Make sure you properly
define the line of action.
Make sure that the secondary
shape properly communicate
the wheel of your character.
In the punching pose for example,
make sure that the flow
of the arms really shows
what your character is
hitting, how he's hitting,
and as for the previous pose,
I make sure that the character lower is
at between his shoulders
to protect his chin,
because he's an experienced fighter.
A little reminder here,
whenever you are posing
the shoulder you can rotate them,
but I also encourage you
to change their location.
As for the finger, you will
have a hard time reaching
the right pose by only using rotation.
Avoid over-twisting the
chest and hips controller
and for the rise using the torso root,
the chest and hips can't
really twist that much.
Doesn't mean they can't, but
if you over rotate the hips
and rotate the chest the other way,
it will look a bit weird,
even for our stylized character.
Again, don't forget to
turn around your pose.
We are not animating to camera
because I want your poses
to work from any angle.
This is how you will
make the best progress.
Later on, we will add the camera
so that we can push the
appeal of our animation,
but for the time being,
let's create a nice animation
without a specific camera angle.
I spend a lot of time on each pose
to make sure that
everything flows properly,
that the character is
looking at what he's hitting,
that I don't have any broken joint,
unless this is a personal choice
to push the pose, for example.
And finally that my character is balanced.
The more time you spend
during the blocking stage,
the easier will be the position later on.
And as for the previous poses,
don't forget to pose the punching bag.