- [Narrator] So now let's polish the arms
and the little details for the first chunk
of this animation.
But one thing I'd done
before publishing the arm
is that I've input a bit of details
into the toes of the right foot.
So I'm not using the graph editor here,
I'm just directly posing to camera.
When the foot is moving forward,
I'm making the toes dragging a bit
as if they were sliding on the ground.
I will later in the video,
revise the rotation,
timing of the foot as it rotates toward
the pinch a bit too soon.
I will offset it by a couple of frames
at the very end of the video.
I will start by polishing the left arm
and I won't be showing you my curves
because it's not necessary.
What's important is the process.
First I've tracked the elbow
by calculating the motion
path of the elbow tweaker.
And now think of what's happening,
the character is dropping down,
so I want the shoulder to drag a bit.
I want the shoulder to raise a bit
when the character is fully.
So I'm just spotting
which channel I can use,
which is the extradition channel,
and I just raise a bit the curve,
so that it raise a bit the shoulder.
Then I will do the same with the arm.
I want the elbow to raise a bit
while the character is going down.
And then for the next two frames,
I will fix the pose of the arm
so that it doesn't cover
that much the face anymore.
I will push a bit the forearm forward
and check out my camera view
to make sure that I see
the eyes of the character.
So while we may rely a
lot on the graph editor,
for the root motion of the character,
because it's super
important and it reads well,
whenever I'm polishing the arms
or the knees or stuff like that,
I'm just tracking the arcs on screen.
The graph editor does make sense to me,
but you don't need to
perfectly understand everything about it,
to be clever about your choices.
So now that I've fixed
the few initial pose,
I will track the rest of my character,
and it feels like it's popping too much.
To double check that I will
simply select the wrist tweaker
and calculate its motion path.
So what I will do by working
on the different controllers of the arm
and not really caring
about the graph editor,
is to reduce the gap
between those two frame,
especially the ups and down
because it's breaking
the flow of the punch.
So if we focus on the
shoulder of the character
between frame 12 and frame 13,
there is a big gap of shape.
On frame 12 the arm is overextended,
and so does the shoulder
while it's compressing on frame 13.
So I can find some kind of
in-between shape on frame 13
by moving a bit the shoulder,
moving a bit the arm,
moving a bit the forearm
and try to flatten a bit
the motion path of the fist.
Again, I'm not relying on
the graph editor to do so.
I tweak the pose through graph editor,
but also directly in the 3D view.
Next, if we follow along
the tracking of the wrist,
we can see that there is a arch angle here
and the fist of the character
disappear on the next frame.
All of these from the camera view,
not in our space.
So what we can do to fix this
is that we can make the elbow
diving little more down.
So I will slightly twist the arm
so that I get more of
an angle with the hand.
This way, I will be able later on
to create a smear into a
C-shape from the camera view.
Now in the next pose,
I will try to show as
much elbow as possible
so that the arms read well,
and it will also extend the
current pose of the character.
I'm sure checking my
character from all angle,
I'm tweaking the pose,
but as you can see,
I don't work that much
directing to the graph editor.
I work a lot directly on my character
a little later on in the animation,
same issue, same solution.
Here you can see from
frame 19 to frame 22,
I have a flat motion path.
So it will be better if we add a nice arc.
So the point here is not to know
what all the curves are
doing into this motion,
but choose the right curves
that will help me to fix this issue.
And if I take the arm controller
and then just check each rotation channel,
I will find one of the curve
that I'll need to raise a bit the arm.
They found the couple of curve
that will all meet to rotate the arm
the way I want from the camera view,
I can tweak them to create the arcs.
I will just regularly
update the motion path
and you can see in a few seconds,
I have fixed my issue,
and this is why having
a super detailed booking
before we switch to
spline was really helpful
because now we can focus
on improving the animation
in putting detail and
fixing the little arcs.
(sound whooshing)
As I fix the arcs,
I have now a motion path
I can full to bard my smears.
I will enable the tweaker bone in the UI,
and then they will jump
to the action editor.
And I will make sure
that I have a key frame
on all those controller on
the previous and next frame.
Around the current frame,
I want to build my
smear frame on this way,
those tweaker bone won't interpolate,
since they are locked before
and after the current frame.
Again, here, there is no magical trick,
I'm just shaping the pose.
So I am pushing, pulling
the different controllers
until it creates a nice arc with the arm.
I'm also breaking the wrist and rotating
the hand so that it's pointing
toward its previous position.
Try to keep the current arch in the arm
as smooth as possible
and focus on what will be
seen from the camera view.
On the next frame,
I will also try to cheat
and show a part of the
left hand of the character
in the camera view.
Even if it's only on one frame,
the fact that we don't
lose track of the hand
will help reading the animation.
Again here, there is no
graph editor involved.
From there even if I don't
see it from the camera view,
I am bulging the smear on the left arm.
Maybe I will have to present
this specific animation
from many angles.
Maybe I will have to tweak
the position of the camera,
both learning wise,
and to prevent any rework later on,
you should do this also.
(sound whooshing)
I will speed up a bit the
video for the right arm,
because in the beginning I'm
doing exactly the same thing.
As the character drop,
I'm raising the shoulder,
then from the camera view,
I will be tracking first
the elbow of the character,
and I will try to create a nice arc.
Also from camera view,
I will try to show as much
of the right arm as possible.
So I'm slightly offsetting the elbow
so that it shows it's
not cut or overlapping
with the chest of the character.
From there, I will calculate
the motion path of the hand,
and I feel like it's jiggling a bit here.
You can see that the path is not clean.
I have both a problem of spacing,
and my arc is not clearly defined.
I will manipulate the shoulder,
the arm and the forearm
controller until I get it right.
And at some point I will also recalculate
the arcs of the elbow.
Since I'm modifying the
position of the arm,
I may mess with the position of the elbow,
the arc of the elbow,
the spacing of the elbow.
Once I was done,
you can see that I have a clean arc,
that is easing into frame 15
before he's throw the punch.
From there, I was able to
work on the current spline.
so when we have switched to spline,
the right opened a lot around frame 16,
because of the forward kinematic mechanism
and both pose wise animation
wise and boxing wise,
this is not super efficient.
And there, instead of using
the interpolation of the curve,
I've decided to revert the current pose
and I've boxing wise exaggerated it
using the tweaker bone.
They're used to create
like a narrow with the arm
that will bench into the bag.
From there, I reworked
each frames of the punch,
working on all the controllers of the arm
to make sure that the
motion path of the punch
was as straight as possible,
and that the whole shape of the arm
was following this motion path.
So even the small orientation of the wrist
is important at this time.
And then when the character
is pulling back his arm,
the fist is currently falling down
and it feels like the arm
is heavy for our character.
While he's supposed to
be super bad bad-ass
so it doesn't fit.
Instead of having the
wrist falling down forward,
I reworked the shape of the arm,
so that the elbow is leading.
So I've made the elbow pointing down,
So is that I can raise the wrist
as if it was following through
or overlapping instead
of leading the arm down.
Those little details
will make the difference
because they communicate a different idea.
The initial pose of our
character make him lose control.
He feels weak and I don't like that.
We don't want that.
He's a bad-ass character,
so everything he does,
he does it with control.
Why the previous animation
might be mechanically correct,
communication wise it's wrong,
because it doesn't communicate
what our character is about.
And asking yourself this kind of question
is not a matter of skill level.
You might be struggling
with your mechanism
or body mechanism,
but you should beginner or not
always ask yourself those questions.
Your animation might not be perfect,
but if he does communicate
the right information to your audience,
then you're doing a better work
than having a bad-ass motion,
but nothing to say about your character.
As explained in the
beginning of the video,
the right foot was
rotating a bit too early,
so I just offset its rotation
by a couple of frames.
But once I was happy with the result,
I've made a final pass of details
onto this chunk of the animation.
(sound whooshing)
I did a little pass on the fingers.
I was originally planning
to have my character with open hands
most of the time during this animation,
because in Muay Thai,
it's more natural to have the hands open,
to be able to catch our upend.
But I've chosen to close the fists
because it will take forever
to spline in polish those fingers.
But while the educational
content would be super imitated,
the fingers are some hold
the limbs of the hand.
So they need to move with pupils.
They will help you to define
the shape of the hand,
and they can also communicate
something about your character
as seen in the posing hand chapter.
What I've done here is that
as the hand is going down,
I will the finger drug by
bending them a bit backward.
And just before the fist closed,
I have made the ultimate joint
to bend backwards so that it feels
like the fingers are snapping into a punch
more than they are crawling into a punch.
It will make the punching even snap here
to have the opposite hand
to also have a snappy motion.