- [Instructor] Before we
start detailing our blocking,
I'd like to introduce a new tool
that will help us
accelerating the process.
It's the Breakdowner tool.
To show it to you,
I've created this simple action
with the bouncing ball rig,
with the main controller only animated
on the Z location access.
The Breakdowner tool is accessible
in the tool panel on the left
whenever you are in Pose Mode.
You can also access the Breakdowner option
going into the editor,
Pose, In-Betweens,
and the different Breakdowner option
will be available here.
If I now go on frame two,
where the ball stopped to raised the air
and I will select the
Breakdowner tool on the left.
If I now left click and
drag in the 3D view port,
You will see the ball going up and down,
whether going toward the
pose on frame number five
or the pose on frame zero.
And as I'm doing it, you can see that
we have a percentage of breakdown
shown in the top left corner.
Currently 40%, this percentage correspond
to whether we are favorizing frame zero
or frame five.
If I create a breakdown this way,
we have a value of zero,
it will be exactly in the
same pose as pose zero.
With a value of 100%,
exactly the same pose as frame five.
If I use a value of 50% for the breakdown,
the pose that will be created
using the breakdown now
will be exactly in the middle
between the pose on frame five
and the pose on frame zero.
As most Blender tool,
we can isolate the channel we want
whenever we are using the Breakdowner.
Here I input a rotation pose on frame five
so the ball is interpolating both
its location and its rotation
from frame zero to frame five.
I now go to the Breakdowner menu,
choose the Breakdowner.
Or, you can use the shortcut
shift+E to activate it.
If I then press R, it will only work
with the rotation of the ball.
If I press shift+E and then G,
it will only work with
the location of the ball.
And you can absolutely combine those
with the X, Y, and Z key.
If I go on frame two, press shift+E
to activate the Breakdowner,
then G, then X,
the ball will only slide along the X axis.
It behaves exactly the same way
as any transform tool.
Two other tools are available to us.
The Relax tool, that we
can access with alt+E,
and the Push tool that we
can access with ctrl+E.
If my player is on the frame with a key,
and then I press alt+E to
Relax the current pose,
the resulting pose will
be closer to pose zero
as I get to 100%.
If instead, I press ctrl+E,
it will Push the current pose.
So basically, it will
check the interpolation
between frame zero and five.
The ball is raising, and
it will Push it higher.
The Relax pose tools that
you can call using alt+E
will create an intermediate key pose,
or breakdown of arranging the pose,
between the previous key
frame and the next key frame.
So using alt+E and Push it over 100%
is exactly the same that using shift+E
the classic Breakdowner,
and set it to 50%.
So this tool is very useful
when you start to detailing your blocking.
For example, here I have two poses
that are pretty extreme,
meaning that there is a big contrast
between those two poses.
With the torso root controller selected,
I can press shift+E, and Blender will
start interpolating
between those two keys.
From there, I can choose
to lower this controller
to create a better arc instead of
having a straight line.
And then, I can choose
to use the Breakdowner
on the chest controller,
and whether keep a low percentage
so that I'm favorizing the previous pose,
or I can go beyond 50%
if I want to rotate more the chest
as if it was leading the animation.
So it's a very cool tool to
quickly block your breakdowns.
But I do advise you to use it
very cautiously and as less as possible.
I generally use it only for
the root of my character,
and sometime to position the feet.
It's a fantastic tool to
keep track of your arcs,
but certainly not a good
tool to pose your character.
To summarize, we have seen that
the breakdowners allow us to create
a key between the two poses
by choosing the level
of interpolation we want
between those two keys.
As any transform channels,
we can enter the value we want
the interpolation to be processed with.
We can isolate the
location, rotation, or scale
of the transformed channels,
and we can choose the axis
we want to use the tool on.
There is also a Push
tool and the Relax tool,
but I don't think they are very useful
since we can achieve the same result
with the Relax tool using the Breakdowner.
And I don't advise you to Push your poses
using a tool like that.
I would do this by hand to
get a more accurate result.
The Breakdowner is a super cool tool
to keep track of your arcs,
and get a base for your
pose and break downs,
but I would never use it
to create the final pose
of one of my character.