- [Teacher] In this video,
we will start to blocking our animation
using the extreme poses.
We have a spot and
define on the reference.
As we did when we were animating
the squirrel character,
I will create those key
poses every five frames.
So for the time being, we
don't care about timing at all.
And to make sure that I
have no sliding controllers,
I will insert the key
frame on all controllers
for both the character
and the punching bag.
Since our character will
be doing a lot of footwork,
and that generally the
knees align with the foot
in the rig properties,
I will make sure that the
leg parent is set to one.
Meaning that the pole target
is now following the foot.
And as we rotate the feet,
the knee will follow.
So let's now build our first pose;
the idle pose.
The right leg or back leg
is open to the outside,
meaning that the foot
is rotated to the right.
The weight of the character is supporting
mostly by this leg.
So I'm pushing the center
of gravity backward
and onto the right leg.
If we watch the reference and
look at the line affection,
we can see that the whole body
is slightly leaning forward,
creating a nice C curve forward
from the supporting foot to the head.
Generally the front leg or left leg
is not supporting that much weight.
and the character is supposed to be
on the tip of his toes.
You will often see muay Thai fighter
making slight bounce with the front leg.
It's a way to input rhythm into the fight
and they keep their front leg ready
to block any kick using their left shin.
When posing the arms,
don't forget that you
can't rotate your elbow
in any other axis then the Z-axis
and that the arm bone can't rotate upward
than the line made by the shoulders.
So it's super important to
currently pose the shoulders.
I see too many beginners
not playing with the shoulder controller
while they are very important
and critically influence the
silhouette of your character.
Now ask yourself, why on the reference,
the character have the shoulders so high?
We are not here to only
answers mechanical properties
of the body, but also
the purpose of the pose.
Again, as explained in
the previous chapter,
if you give a clear goal
to the current pose,
it will communicate the
will of the character.
And as soon as you do that,
you're giving life to your character.
In muay Thai and in boxing in general,
shoulder are raised a
lot to protect the head
of the character, especially the chin,
because a shot in the chin
can knock you out instantly.
If you were to animate
some beginner in boxing,
maybe you should drop the shoulders
so that you communicate a
big mistake boxing wise.
Here I want my character to show mastery
in the art of boxing.
So I will try to mimic the reference pose
and even push it more;
pushing the head deep into the shoulders.
As usual, the step between
a good pose and a great pose
is pretty long and it's
about a lot of tweaking.
But why it might be more
natural to have open hands
whenever you're not wearing gloves?
Especially in muay Thai,
where you can catch your opponent
and go into the clinch,
I've decided to close the left hand
because both my hand were
posed a bit the same way,
and I had some twinning in the post
and it didn't look that interesting.
So I will close the fist
and I will slide the scale,
the palm fingers on the local X axis
to make them slightly larger
as if the fist was a bit squashed
by the pressure of the closing hand.
Don't forget that you can
refer back to the video
about posing the hands.
Don't forget to pose
the neck and the head,
but don't over-rotate those controllers.
And as a final touch, you
can use the face controller
to shape a bit the eyes.
Now our character is
ready to kick some ass.
So don't forget to rotate
a lot around your character
to check if the center of gravity
is properly aligned and
your character, balanced.
And don't forget to check
the overall silhouette
of the character of from different angles.
Again, remember that you can refer to the
previous chapter to
double-check the method
to get a good pose.
Before you start posing the jab pose,
double check the video reference.
You can see that both
feet are moving forward
during this punch.
Beyond rotating the feet, don't forget
to change their rotation
while posing the jab.
So the first thing I will do
is to move the feet forward.
Now, as we watch carefully the reference,
we can see that the weight is
shifting onto the front feet
and the whole chest is
twisting to the right.
And so does the feet.
So, since we have weight
on the front foot,
I will flatten it a bit,
and then I will raise the back foot
using the heel controller.
And then we would rotate
both feet to the right.
But when you punch left,
your feet turns to the right.
When you punch with the right,
your feet turn to the left.
But I haven't pushed this pose too much
because the next punch will also be
a straight punch forward.
And if we go too much forward
and too much into a horizontal pose
for this initial punch,
we will lose the contrast
with the next one.
And so our pose may look good,
but the animation won't because
it will lack of contrast
between the first pose
and the second pose.
Another thing I'm doing though,
is that I'm slightly spreading
the arms of the character.
While it might not be a super good idea
whenever you are boxing,
because you are exposing your chin,
this improve a bit, the
readability of the pose
and it slightly extend
the overall silhouette
of the character when
we follow the shoulders.
Finally, don't forget
that you also have to pose
the punching bag.
Don't push it too far and
don't use that much controller.
Moving all the controllers
won't necessarily
give you better result.
While we do agree that
everything is connected
so everything should be
moving; keep it simple.
Your audience will mainly
focus on the character.
So you want to avoid any glitches
on the bag by moving too much controller
at the same time.
Once done, don't forget to
key all your controllers
and don't forget to add subtle
rotation details to the feet.
When we watch the reference,
we can see that there is a
subtle tilting during the punch.
Don't forget to add it
during the blocking state.