- With our golden poses done,
it's time to add some breakdowns.
The goal of those
additional poses is to have
a better grasp on the
flow of the animation.
We will build the first step into the jab,
which is the anticipation of the jab.
Then the transition into the right cross
and the right cross overshoot
really help to communicate
the power into dispatch.
Then we will add a couple
of poses after the hook
to show the steps taken by the character
to get back into idle before
performing the switch kick.
We'll create the transition jump
into the anticipation of the switch kick
that is already blocked.
After the kicking pose
we will add an overshoot of the leg
that will sell the power of the kick.
And finally, we will add a transition pose
before the two steps we have
already blocked back into idle.
Before building those poses,
I've watched the reference and
I've spot the frame that
were interesting to me.
Like this pose in between
the idle and the first jab
character is lowering
his center of gravity
and also pushing forward.
So it will be a great anticipation.
I've also noticed that the
character is slightly dropping
his hands during this anticipation.
As a person pose for a walk cycle,
I'm trying to find a good break down
and the time where the character
is pulling his left hand
and pushing with the right hand
seems to be pretty nice.
Also adding notes as a reminder,
that the torso is twisting
a lot on this pose,
Then I will spot the overshoot.
If your reference doesn't
show the next move,
just put note on top of this and make sure
that you look for new reference later on.
So this is something I've
been doing for every poses
I wanted to add into the blocking stage.
As in the previous videos our goal
is not necessarily to copy
100% the exact same poses.
But to check the body
mechanisms that are involved
and then push them to make our animation
more exaggerated and more appealing.
So let's work the step
forward into the jab.
As usual, I will try to
define the line of action.
The simple C shape the front
foot is currently raising
while the back foot is pushing.
So as before I generally scrub
around the current frame to
check out the motion of the
different parts of the body,
the hands, the head, the feet,
so that I don't forget to put them.
And also I could choose whether
I favorite the front foot
to move further away or to be closer,
to drop more the feet, to lean
more the character forward,
make any choice to
exaggerate the current pose.
Now in blender I will insert a key frame
for all the controllers
of both the character
and the bag on the frame seven.
Again, at this stage, we
don't care about timing.
We can do it on frame seven
or eight doesn't matter.
Then I want to get rid of the rest pose
we have on frame zero.
So I will duplicate
frame five on frame zero.
When working on an animation,
if it's not a gameplay animation,
I you advise you to keep five
frames also in the beginning
in the still pose so
that you can get prepared
to what is coming next.
If you start your
animation from frame zero,
sometime it's a bit hard to read.
The difference between this new pose
and the previous one won't be that big.
First I want to lower
the center of gravity
as our character is gathering
energy to throw the punch.
Then I pushed the center
of gravity forward.
As our character is
already moving forward.
The left foot is raised a little bit and
slightly rotated towards the inside
because it's going to leave
the ground on the next frame.
And so the center of gravity
will shift a bit to the left.
The character is pushing
toward his left foot
with his right foot.
So you have to move the
cog a bit to the left.
Then I do a few adjustment with the arm,
making them dragging it.
So I raised the shoulder
as the center of gravity
is getting lower.
I open the hand as the
whole body's moving forward
as if there was wind blowing
into the palm of the character
and I do the same with
the neck and the head.
As it drop into the step
I slightly raise his chin.
(swishing noise)
When we watch the reference
for the next pose,
we can see that the character
is currently pulling
the left arm and bring it close
to his chin to protect it.
In the meantime, the
right arm is traveling
towards the target.
The hips are twisting a lot.
The center of gravity too
and the chest is twisting,
but dragging a little bit.
Finally, the right foot is rotating a lot.
So those are the main point
we are going to address
into our breakdown pose.
As for the previous pose
I will add a key frame
on all the controllers of the bag
and the character on frame 12.
Again, at this stage, we
don't care about timing.
Since the location of
the feet doesn't change
between the previous and the next pose
we can directly work on
the center of gravity
of the character.
As the character is twisting to his left,
his center of gravity is also
shifting to the left foot.
So we need to twist the center of gravity
but we also need to move it to the left.
Just imagine that the character is diving
into the next punch
with his left shoulder.
As seen in the reference the
right foot is rotating a lot.
So I rotate it even more and
I will raise it with the heel.
Don't forget to adjust the
position of the hips accordingly.
Now we can twist a bit the chest,
but don't forget that
the hips are leading.
So the chest may not
twist as much as the hips
for the time being.
Once the punch is thrown,
the chest will catch up with the hips.
And as the weight is getting
on the front left foot,
I'm slightly tilting it to the left
and I'm slightly pushing it down.
This will mimic the compression
of the foot on the ground.
For this breakdown I decided to not go
too into the orthodox boxing pose with
the left fist very close to the chin.
I've kept the left arm
slightly more opened.
This way we have a nice circular
flow between the two arms.
As I explained before,
remember to move the arms with
the anatomical constraint,
rotating the elbow on neuron one axis,
and don't forget to pose the bag.
That's not the most important thing,
but it will help you read your animation.
To do so I reset all the
controller of the bag,
and then I slightly rotated it backward
just after the little jab
as if the jab has pushed it a
bit and the bag is swinging.