- [Instructor] We still
have a couple of breakdowns
to add to our current animation,
but before we do so
I'd like to give myself
some space on the action editor.
As explained before, for the time being,
I'm not working on the timing
of my animation, only the poses.
So I want to move all
the poses of my character
and the punching bag every five frames.
So instead of working on
the action of the character
and the action of the bag separately,
I will switch to the dope sheet.
The dope sheet will expose me
all the keys frame available
in the actual blender scene.
If I collapse the action
details in the dope sheet,
we can see that both the Trident
and punching bag armature
are listed in the dope sheet,
along with their own actions.
And since we were posing
those two in sync,
their key frame are aligned.
So by clicking the summary key,
I can select all the
keys for both the action
and offset them in time.
From there, back onto
my current animation,
I will select the summary keys
and position them every five frames.
This is a good moment to
review the different poses
and see how they flow one with the other.
And this is generally the time
where I find tweak some of the poses.
I may push them a little more.
You may spot weird poses of the shoulder
or the shape of the arms or the position
of the center of gravity compared
to the previous or next pose.
Since it's a creative process,
it's sometimes hard to
clearly explain what I'm doing
because it's a lot about feeling.
And when you scrub through
your different poses,
you may feel that something
is wrong or that something
could be improving the flow of your poses,
and the blocking stage
is the moment to do it.
The next breakdown I'm
going to do is the jump
during the switch for the switch kick.
I'm going to do a pose where
are both feet are in the air.
Depending on the reference and watching
distance might be more or less opened.
Liam Narissan on the left
side has a crazy open stance
because he's going to
throw a very powerful kick.
There a very quick and subtle
moment during the switch
where the body is making a C
shape toward the left shoulder.
And then as a spring, the
body bent the opposite way,
and this is what I want to
achieve with this breakdown pose.
I'm not sure if it's super accurate,
but it does seem to work.
And if it doesn't work in the end,
I can change it to later on.
One super important detail
that I want you to spot
before posing your character
is the position of the right foot.
Look, how much it is open to the outside
whenever it hits the ground.
With this position, as
soon as the left foot
will leave the ground, the
hips will naturally twist
towards the right foot,
increasing the power of the kick.
So when I'm posing the
right foot I make sure that,
even in the air, it starts to open a bit.
The foot doesn't rotate
when it hits the ground,
but just before, when it is in the air.
Keeping the right foot pretty flat
while the left foot will land on its tip.
So I make sure that the
tip of the left foot
is pointing toward its landing zone.
The left arm is raising,
the right arm is dropping.
So I make a bit the forearm dragging,
meaning that the left arm
will be slightly straighter
while the right arm will be slightly bent.
Finally, I've exaggerated
the C shape of the torso,
maybe a bit too much.
I will see that later on.
For the next pose.
I wanted to create the overshoot
just after the leg hit the bag.
At this point, the leg is almost straight
as the kicker is trying
to get through the bag
or through the pose.
What's interesting is
that at this very stage,
the hips already start to twist backwards
and then the shoulders will follow.
And if you watch the right heel,
it seems it's hitting a wall.
This is also a moment
where I am going to build
a little smear on the left leg.
Using the tweaker bone, I
slightly the break the joint
to bend it into a knock that
is the opposite direction
a leg normally bend.
While the body of our character
is not supposed to move that much,
this recreate a nice contrast
in the shapes of the leg
and will better communicate
the strength of the impact.
As it is an overshoot,
I want to push for one beat
and then we need to twist it
back a little bit in reaction
to the impact with the bag.
We need to do the same with the hips
and the chest controller.
This is the time where the right foot
hit its extreme toward the target,
so I rotate it a bit to the left.
Since the left arm was swinging back,
I will rotate it a bit backward.
And since the right arm
was rotating forward,
I will rotate eat a little more forward.
Regarding the left leg, I
want to exaggerate its pose,
so I will push the left foot controller
further away from the hips.
I've also repositioned the pull target
to make sure that the knee's not flipping.
It's totally fine to have
some stretching in the leg,
because whenever we are
building a smear frame,
it won't last more than one or two frames.
If you were supposed to feel
this beyond, not see it.
You want to the knock that will
wrap around the punching bag,
so I'm even rotating the
toes in this direction.
I've enabled the trochlear
of the leg in the read UI.
And from there, I will
move them one by one
to shape the leg into a knock.
Start with the new controller,
as it allows you to bend the knee backward
and then use the smaller tweaker bone
to create a the arc with
the sheen of the character.
As I was building the pose and rotating
a lot around my character,
I've noticed that the
punching bag was not reacting
in the right direction.
Eventually, I fixed this by reworking
all the pose after the kick.
Slowly but surely, and even
without working on the timing,
our animation flow is
getting better and better.
The very last pose I've created
for this breakdown stage
is the transition into idle.
It's the moment where
the left leg is dropping,
almost straight, into a nice arc.
All the weight is on the right foot
and counter balancing the left leg.
So the body is creating a
nice C shape to the right.
This is not a very difficult pose to build
since it's really flowing between
the kicking pose and the next pose.
Don't forget to also rework the bag
and move some of these poses.
It doesn't matter if you have
a hard time with the bag.
The most important pose
are the contact pose
with the character.
If at this stage, you have
a hard time figuring out
all the poses of the bag,
that's not a problem.
For the time being, keep
the poses of the bag
and the character synchronized.
When we will on the
timing of the character,
it will be easier to figure
out the timing for the bag too.
Regarding the current pose, to be honest,
I don't really know what to say
since it's a pretty simple pose.
You have the reference,
just try your best to
fit what you are seeing.
In the next video we are going to give
a first pass to the
timing of our blocking.