- [Narrator] Here we go again.
Let's add even more
details to our blocking.
On the video reference, there
is the killer- (cut off)
Whenever Liam Arison is throwing his hook,
I'm kind of shaking in his left shoulder
in his chest, and in his head.
it looks like the recoil of a shotgun
or something like that.
To build this effect
I will need two poses,
one overshoot of the whole torso
we have the left arm will stay still
and then a second pose
where the whole body
will be pushed backward by
the force applied to the bag by
the left arm.
So basically what we need to do
is create an overshoot
for the whole torso,
push it further forward
twist model chest
controller, rotate the head
and the neck to the
right open the right arm,
and then contrapose the left shoulder
and hold left arm controller
as if there were some kind of recoil.
And try to keep the fist
in the same position
World-space-wise as the previous pose.
Even if it's hidden by the bag,
you can squash a bit the fist too.
Maybe we will be able to try
some little tricks to better
sell the impact during
the polishing stage.
From there when I'm looking at the motion
of the bag, it seems that
its trajectory is not really good.
And since this is an impact frame,
I will give it some love and
spend a bit of time to reshape
the bag and better align it
with the punch. As usual,
after we have reviewed all the poses,
I will provide you a slow paced
timelapse so that you can
follow along all the manipulation
I'm doing. Just to note,
don't forget to slightly
change the position of the feet.
The next pose we are going to build
is the actual recoil after the punch.
As seen on the reference
in the beginning of this video,
just after the impact, the chest,
the center of gravity and the hips
are twisting to the left.
It's a pretty subtle change compared
to the previous pose.
All the location and rotation
of the torso is going the
opposite way compared with
the previous pose. So,
it's very important to add another pose,
like the bounce in your bouncing ball
while the location of
the ball doesn't change,
its shape and the momentum of the ball
is completely changing.
So you need to block this. If you will
whenever the momentum or the energy
of the current motion
is brutally changing direction,
you should always block those poses.
Getting this pose right
is a lot about the amount
of twisting you input
into the chest and the center of gravity.
Then you can find tweaks,
the shoulders position,
the angle made by the arms,
et cetera. I've decided to keep the armor
pretty angular into a closed stance
So that it really sells the fact that
our character is fully contracted.
If our character was more relaxed,
I will loosen a bit the arms
and I will open them a bit more.
Since this pose occurs after the hit,
don't hesitate to push the heavy bag away
from the character.
The further it is, the more powerful
will the hook feel.
If you can bend, a bit, the bag
towards the point it came from.
This will bring a bit
of overlapping motions
that will make it look a little more
organic.
(wind wooshing)
I previously explain you
that you should always lock the poses
when the feet are getting
in contact with the
ground. Well, I also advise you
to block the poses
whenever the feet are leaving the ground.
For the switch of the switch kick,
we have the previous pose
with both feet on the ground,
and then we have the
pose where both feet have
left the ground.
So we currently need to block the pose
where the character is
pushing into the jump
and still has one foot
on the ground.
As we watch the reference,
we can see it's a pretty quick jump.
And the right foot is the
last to leave the ground.
The goal of this jump is not to
get as high as possible
or to cover distance.
It's all about repositioning
the feet so that the kicking
leg is in the back and
have more range to move
towards the targets.
So don't push the center
of gravity too high.
You can push it a bit to the front
and a bit to the left
since the whole weight
was on top of the right foot
and now the right foot is
pushing. So the center of gravity
will slightly shift towards the front,
but also so toward the left.
Then as the character is rising,
you can drop a bit the arms.
(wind wooshing)
Same concept comes for the next pose.
After the jump,
our character doesn't contact the ground
with both feet at the same time.
So we do need to build the pose
where the first feet is
contacting the ground.
And as I double check the reference,
we can see that the left
foot is the first to land.
So this is what I'm going to build.
But pose wise and motion wise,
I feel like the kick and the switch from
Liam Arison on the left look way more
badass.
As he lands almost into
his anticipation position
and throw the kick right away.
I may not be super objective since I love
his style.
To get the left foot in
the correct position,
I will simply select it.
Then go to the pose where it's in contact
with the ground, copy
the pose and paste it
on the previous frame.
Since this is the contact pose,
I will raise the toes so
that on the next frame,
they will slap on the ground
creating a nice overlapping motion.
To find the pose of the torso
controller, I will use the breakdowner
so I will press shift-E
and I will use a value around 60%
and I will repeat the
process with the foot,
the hips, and the chest.
The value of the breakdowner is
not the important point.
- Plus this will change
depending on the timing
of animation, if you have
the same pose as I have,
or not, and from one
controller to the other,
the timing won't be the same.
So the use of the
breakdowner and the value
of the breakdowner will change.
- Your job is to watch the reference
and understand which part
of the body is arriving
first in the next pose
and use the breakdowner accordingly,
the transition between the landing pose
and the kick and the moment
the kick is being released is very short.
So I've dealt with the next pose exactly
as I will do with a
bouncing ball. As I am finishing
to build the pose before the anticipation
of the kick,
I will consider the next frame
as the contact pose with
both feet contacting the ground.
Then we can consider the next pose
as the ball squashing on
the ground before jumping back.
So I will squash the body of my character
by slightly lowering
its' center of gravity,
before he rise again into the kick.
The difference between the two pose
will be very subtle.
My goal here is to create some kind of
moving hold as we did
for the anticipation of the hook.
But this time the transition
will be very short,
like one or two frames!
So I won't be building a moving hold
with a lot of amplitudes.
I will simply slightly
lower the center of gravity
slightly twist the character,
maybe push a bit the arms inward
before the release.
A bit, as if I was creating an overshoot
of the previous pose.
The goal is not truly to guide my posing,
but mostly to lock my timing.
And when I will switch to spline,
there won't be any surprises regarding
the timing of this part of the animation,
since I'm animating "on ones".
So I have a key frame on
every single frame here,
but it doesn't mean that I won't have to
rework those poses
during the polishing stage
with the graph editor.