- [Instructor] Here is
the final timing pass
for our blocking of the animation.
As explained before, there is no motion
between frame zero and frame five.
Those first frames are just
here so that we can have a look
through the whole scene,
see our character in the fighting stance,
and start to think of
what's going to happen.
From there, our character is
easing into the first bench.
So, we first have three frames
later, the anticipation,
with this moving forward
and a bit downward.
A couple of frames later,
we have our contact pose and
a couple of frames later,
the current jab, with
another extended left arm
and a frame later, the same pose,
but with the arm back into position.
This little trick creates
a more snappy impact.
Then we have a fast transition
into the right cross.
On only two frames,
our character starts to
swing it's right arm.
Two frames later,
we have the impact with the bag.
And one frame later, we get the overshoot.
So this time we create the
overextension of the arm,
a frame after the impact.
so that there is more
the sense of penetration
than just little snappy punch.
And it takes three more frames
for our character to recover
its normal body shape, let's say.
Then over five frames,
the right food is catching up
and then pushing, in a way,
the left foot over two frames.
From there, our character is ready to go
into the anticipation of the hook.
So he will ease out into the anticipation.
So it will take five frames
to get into the anticipation
and five additional frames of moving
all the weaving overshoot.
Or an exaggerated anticipation
so that the hook will look
even more powerful.
From there over a couple of frames,
we have the fast swing,
one from later, the impact,
two frame later the overshoot,
and on frame forty seven, the recoil.
On frame fifty,
we have the down pose after the hook,
then it takes six frame
for the right foot to reach
its contact pose.
And from there five
additional frames to get
into the down pose that will
serve as the anticipation
before the switch kick.
From our micro-anticipation
on frame sixty one,
our character will be pushing
on two frames and will be
airborne on frame sixty six.
On there we are animating on once
the contacting of the left
foot, then the right foot,
then a slight down pose.
From there, I want to build
a strong easing of the foot.
So we have two frames for
the foot to leave the ground.
And then it's animating on once
until the impact on the bag.
The impact is put over all four frames,
so that our character is holding the pose
for a long time and need
to look more impactful.
from there, the left foot is easing
into a drop to what it's contact pose
ten frames later on frame eight eight.
Six frame later on the right foot,
is contacting back,
before easing five frames
later into the new idol pose.