- [Instructor] With our center of gravity
and our feet polished,
it's gonna be way he's
yours to now polish the hips
of the character.
To get rid of any visual noise,
I will ID arms of the
character using the rig UI.
So let's expose the hips rotation curve.
And keep in mind that the
hips can either be pushed
by the supporting leg or
lead the leg, pulling it.
For example, on the
section of the animation,
as the weight is totally
shifting toward the right leg,
the hips will raise toward the right leg,
because they are pushed by the right leg.
And our goal is not to
know which curve to use,
but to figure it out based
on the character motion.
The weight is on the right leg,
so I need to slightly raise
the hips toward the right.
I'm testing different curve.
The Y rotation curve seems to be the one
that will do what I need.
And I tweak this curve rig-wise.
Most of the motion of the
torso of our character
is generated by the torso
root or center of gravity.
So most of the time,
once the center of gravity is polished,
polishing the hips is mostly
smoothing out the curve,
so that we don't get harsh
angles or distorted torso shape.
And then I tend to rotate a little more
to chest controller
than the hips controller
As you can see, I'm pushing and pulling
along the way of the curve,
so that I get smoother transition
from one extreme to the other.
On frame 47, I will push down a bit
the Z quaternion curve,
because it will make the hips
to twist a little further
into the punch.
Since the hips are leading the punch,
it's where the energy come from.
We do need just after the impact them
to slightly overshoot.
And then I'm realigning the
hips with the rest of the body,
so that I don't get a too distorted trunk.
This little push on frame 47
will create a slight overshoot,
and that will better sell the impact,
because we will have a slight
glitch into the hips rotation
just after he hit the bag.
And since the hips are pulling the leg,
I will propagate a bit
the slight overshoot
into the left knee, by
playing with the pull target.
We can see the pull target
shifting after frame 47
to the left, but I will
just pull a bit the curve
on frame 50 and 52 to
create a slight overshoot
toward the inside.
As the hips rotate, the
knee is pulled inside,
overshoot a bit, and then
get back into its position
on frame 58.
(air whooshes)
Polishing the chest will be
mostly about making it drag.
A lot of the force in boxing
comes from way you deal
with your center of gravity,
so basically how you move
your feet and your hips.
Having a strong upper body
is really a secondary factor
to the power of your punch.
This is why we can make it drag it,
because this is not the primary force
into the punching motion.
The twisting of our character chest is led
by the Z quaternion curve.
So that our character
torso root is twisting
toward the left, I will
make the chest drag
by inputting a bit of delay
into the Z quaternion curve,
meaning that I will
offset any extreme pose,
and I will push the curve
toward its previous value.
This is a very easy
method that you can use
whenever you're trying to
achieve a dragging motion,
whether it's the finger,
a pony tail, or whatever.
You just delay the keys of the controller
based on their position in the chain.
The closer they get to
the tip of the chain,
the further you will offset the keys,
and I will apply this
concept to different degrees
for the chest.
The more strength the character
will put into his punch,
meaning that he will contract
all the muscle of his torso,
the tighter will be the dragging.
So I may not offset by your
key, every pose of the chest,
but rather have a rise to
previous pose, and then overshoot.
For example, here, I will
push up the Z quaternion curve
on frame 44 and 45,
but then I will push it down
to create the overshoot.
Pushing up the curve create
the drags into the twist.
Pushing it down create the overshoot
and sell more power to the hook.
Now you have to be careful
not to smooth out the motion too much.
A good way to input a bit of
texture and impact to the hook
is to use the location of the chest.
As the character is moving up very fast,
I will pull the chest down.
I will squash it onto the hips,
but then as the character hit the bag,
I will slightly pull the chest the back.
So I will make it drag a bit.
And just after the impact,
I will push it forward.
So basically you move the
chest opposite to the punch,
and then you move it toward the punch.
It will feels like the chest
of the character is bouncing
due to the impact of the hook.
Don't hesitate to push
this pose further away,
pushing forward over one frame,
and recovering over two or three frames.
(air whooshes)
From there, polishing the neck
and the head is pretty straightforward.
I'm using the tweaker bone
at the base of the head
to calculate the motion path.
And from there, I will walk as we did
in the previous segment of this animation.
We are going to make the
neck dragging compound
to the chest.
Since the neck is following the rotation
of the chest controller-wise,
the element of work to polish those curve
won't be that big, but just for our eyes,
it will beat the previous pose
by pushing the value of the curve
toward its previous value
or offsetting in in time
by one frame.
Then track your arcs.
You can see here, I have a very clean arc
made by the pace of the head.
And since the head comes from the left,
I'm tweaking the value of the curve,
so that the head move
a bit more to the left
during this transition move.
And then as it hits the next pose,
I will make it overshoot
a bit, one or two frame,
after it hits the extreme pose.
Technically, I don't have that much tricks
to teach you here,
but to watch the motion path
and make sure you create
as smooth arc as possible.
It's exactly the same
method as what we did before
for the arms.
We were tracking the elbows,
and then playing with the
rotation curve of the upper arm.
We were modifying the
shape of the motion path.
At no point was I focusing
on the graph (indistinct),
but mostly on the arcs made by the elbow.
At this stage, it's tweaking
each pose frame by frame,
whether you're doing these
for the rough editorial
or directly in the 3D
view port doesn't matter,
but your arcs must be super clean.
For example, here, as
the torso is rotating
toward the right, I will
rotate the neck to the left,
so that it is dragging.
And then after the impact,
I've pushed the neck to the right,
so that I get a nice overshoot
and we feel like the head has
a lot of weight and momentum.
And as I feel up here
with the result here,
I will do exactly the
same thing with the head.
Instead of tracking the base of the neck,
I may track with the top of the
head or the tip of the nose.
From there, you will see
that it's very, very straightforward.
When the head is raising,
I will lower the chin a bit.
When the head is getting down,
I will raise the chin a bit.
When the head is turning to the right,
I will make the nose drag to the left.
So we are repeating the
same method over and over
along the whole animation.
There is just a moment with
the specific controller
where we are going to
break the rules in the way
to create more impact.
If you remember, when we
were watching the reference
of Liam Harrison throwing a big hook,
there is a lot of rotation in
his head during the impact,
and this is what I want to reproduce here.
And they want to get that
into my animation too.
But instead of having
a recoil in the head,
I want to hold during the drag,
and then move it away as fast as possible.
To do so, I will create a little plateau
with the Z quaternion rotation.
This way the head is looking
at the punch, so it dragging.
And on the next frame, I
will push the curve way down,
so that it rotate the opposite way.
And it creates a very
impactful rotation of the head
just after the punch.
From there, I will smooth the curve,
so that the character is out of this pose.
From there, it was all about
adding some extra detail
to the animation of the torso.
First I've checked the pose of the head
from the camera angle.
And then using its location,
so moving the head in space,
I've exaggerated a bit the impact.
Then I've used the tweaker controller
to add a very slight
stretching to the head
whenever it's moving super fast in screen
on this specific frame,.
As for the arm, this will
fake the motion blur.
Then I will play with the
tweaker controller of the torso.
I will select them all,
and they will insert a key
frame on every single frame
during the hook
This way, I'm sure that those controller
won't interpolate from
one frame to the other.
And from there, I will
use those controller
for two main reason.
First, I want to slightly
reshape my character,
so that there is not that
much breaks in his silhouette,
and this way, I offer better
support to his line of action,
but I will also use them to create a bit
of a shaking his body
whenever he hit with the hook.
On frame 48, I will
select the tweaker bone
in the middle of the spine
between the hips and the chest,
and I will push it forward.
This is subtle details that
will bring a little more impact
to the current animation
as if the body of the character
was projected forward,
because of the momentum of the strike.