- [Instructor] As usual, once I'm done
with polishing the torso
or the center of gravity,
I work on the contact
points of the character.
So I will work on the feet as always.
I will start with the right leg
as it's going to be pretty fast.
First of all, I want to make sure
that the leg gets fully extended
before the foot leave the ground.
So I will simply delay by a couple
of frame the moment the
foot leave the ground.
From there, I will make sure that the foot
is drawing a nice arc in space,
and then I will slightly
push the z location curve
to create the up pose of the
foot right in the middle.
I will then switch the handles to vector
for the starting point and ending point
of the z location and x location.
This way I make sure that the foot
is accelerating when leaving the ground
and when it's about to contact the ground.
Then I can revise the heel orientation
or heel rotation using
the heel controller,
raising the heel just before
the foot leave the ground
and flattening the foot a couple
of frame after the contact pose.
Then I'm also working on
the toes of the character.
So as usual, I will make them drag,
meaning that they will be pointing
toward their previous position.
On the contact pose,
I will raise the toes
and then I will slap them on
the ground one frame later.
And I will convert the contacting key
of the toes to vector
so that I'm sure that
they are accelerating
before they hit the ground,
even if it's over only one frame.
Then I will work on the jumping motion.
So I will make sure
that the foot leave the ground late enough
so that I get an extended leg.
And as I move the foot,
I will also work on
its quaternion rotation
to make it drag.
So the ball of the foot will be pointing
toward its previous position,
and then while in the air,
I will make it transition
toward its next position,
toward the contacting pose.
I will slightly open the
foot just before the impact
so that the character land
on the edge of the foot,
and it slightly pivot while the weight
is shifting onto the foot.
Then I will work on the kicking motion
of this current foot,
the foot that is contacting the ground.
It has a specific rotation,
as we have see in the reference.
It twist to follow the hips
and then just after the impact,
it twist backward very fast.
So we have this very fast
back and forth motion
of the heel toward the target.
In this case, it's driven
by the W quaternion rotation
for my foot, and I'm creating this V shape
with the curve
where when it's going down,
it rotates toward the target,
and after frame 81, it rotates back.
To make this motion less linear,
I will hold the pose
for a couple of frames
by adding a new key on frame 80 and 81.
And then I will make the
foot ease into its rest pose,
just before the left foot enter contact
with the ground.
Once I'm done with this,
I will work on the last step backward
with the same checkpoint
in mind as before.
I want to make sure that
the leg extend a bit
before the foot leave the ground.
And that the foot contact the ground
before the weight of the
character starts to shift
toward the current foot.
So as usual, I'm often delaying the moment
where the foot is leaving the ground.
In this case, by two frames.
And then I switch the
contacting pose to vector
so that I get a hard contact.
And I input a bit of up pose in between
using the z location to make
the foot raise in space.
From there, as usual,
I will refine a bit the heel controller
to make sure that the heel is raising
whenever the foot is getting pulled,
and that it's at it highest point
just before the contact frame.
Then I will switch to the foot rotation
and see if I can make
it drag a little bit.
And as I did before,
I want the foot to rotate
a bit after the contact
as the weight of the character
is shifting upon this foot.
And also, contact first
with the inner edge
of the foot, and then the foot will tilt
to become flat.
This create a slight roll on the ground
of the foot that looks more natural
than the foot getting flattened
directly on the ground
as it contacts.
As the final detail, as usual,
I will work on the toes.
Whenever the foot is leaving the ground,
I will make the toes drag
and eventually, when
it contacts the ground,
I will raise them a bit
so that they slap the
frame after the contact.
Another detail I wanted
to add is the friction
of the toes on the ground
when the character is
twisting to throw the kick.
If you flatten your hand on the table
and you push on the hand
and try to twist it,
you will see your fingers dragging
in the opposite direction as the twist
because of the friction and the resistance
on the ground, or on the table.
So this is what I'm doing here
using the z Euler rotation.
I rotate them toward
their previous position.
It's the same principle
as when we lift the foot
but in this case, the
motion is side to side
instead of being up and down.
From there, I've worked on the left foot.
At this point, the
workflow is pretty linear.
I hope you understand what
I've been doing before
and if not, you should rewatch the videos.
I know how confusing it can be
to read the graph editor,
especially for beginners
where you are not comfortable
with the tools.
So talking about poses, rhythm and spacing
might not translate for
you watching those curve.
If it's the case, jump back
to the squirrel chapter
and make sure that you
practice with this character.
During the switch,
I'm mainly reworking the up pose
so that it's smallest in
the middle of the motion
of the foot toward its new position.
And as you can see, I deal
with the z curve a bit
like with the bouncing ball
with vector handles when the
foot is leaving the ground
and hitting the ground
and a scale key in between.
Now, as you have guessed,
most of the work was during the kicking,
first, make sure that you
calculate your motion path.
The first choice I did
was to make the foot to stay on the ground
as long as possible.
This way we do get the feeling
that the hips is pulling the leg
as strong as possible.
But also, it will all
need to get less frames
to throw the kick
so that it will be very fast,
and very snappy.
So as the foot is leaving the ground,
I make sure that it's very close
to its initial pose
so that I will have a big spacing
between the starting frame
and the contacting frame.
We will have a big acceleration,
so for the in between,
I'm favorizing the first position,
so that the spacing get bigger and bigger
and we do feel the acceleration
of the foot before the contact pose.
Once I feel good with this,
I will make sure that my arcs are clean,
especially on the impact frame.
I will slightly tweak
the position of the foot
from the camera view
so that it perfectly wrap
around the punching bag,
creating a nice arc.
Since the punching bag is an accessory,
I will pose the bag later on,
paste on the foot motion.
But it's not hard for
me to create a nice arc
from the camera view,
considering that the punching bag
will be more or less there
since we have blocked everything before.
Then when the leg is pulled back,
I will make sure that
I get a very clean arc
and that the foot is
accelerating toward the ground.
Beyond being bound to your graph editor,
you should be more watching
and analyzing your motion path.
This is the tool that perfectly
translate to you the arcs
and the spacing of your animation.
Then with experience, you will be able
to read this also into your graph editor.
As usual, from there, I will
work on the heel controller.
That's pretty straightforward.
As the foot is leaving the ground,
I'm raising the heel.
The only tricky thing
is that our character just jumped
into the anticipation for the kick.
So the heel is going down
and then he's pushing to throw the kick.
So the heel is raising.
There is this slight
plateau at some point.
From there it's all about
building the smear frames.
Don't hesitate to work
with all the controllers,
like the toe controller, for example,
to make the foot longer
as it's getting pulled from the ground.
The trajectory of the knee
will also be crucial,
so it's very important to track the arc
of the knee and from there,
build the shape of the leg.
Just think of the leg as a whip.
You want to create a nice curly shape
with the whole leg
that is going toward the kicking position.
Make sure that the foot orientation,
make it drags toward
its previous position.
And take advantage again
of all the controllers.
There are tweaker on the top of the toes,
so do not hesitate to
make those toes dragging.
At this stage, it's not about animating
but really sculpting your pose.
There are only three
frames of your character.
They must be perfect.
One tip to get this muscle shape
is to hide the heel of the character
from the camera point of view.
You can easily do this by
using the ankle tweaker
instead of trying to rotate the foot.
I'm trying my best to get
a smooth shape for the leg.
There are limitation due to
the anatomy of the character
but also the resolution of his mesh
and the number of controllers in the rig.
On the frame, just after
the contact with the bag,
I will scale on one axis the sheen
and the foot so that it feels
like they are squashing on the bag.
It's like creating an explosion.
You start with a thin shape
and then you make it very big.
And this visual pop will bring more impact
to your animation.
And this is exactly what
we want for the kick.
When it's done over one frame like that,
it's barely viewable or noticeable
but it will feel for sure.
For this kind of shape,
I don't really have any rules to tell you
or to explain you.
What I do advise you is
to search for references,
like in anime, for example,
where they do deform a lot the character
to get crazy perspective
or crazy impactful shapes like that.
You will also find this
kind of crazy shape
in kids cartoon.
I think that's a very,
very interesting source
of inspiration whenever it
comes to stylized animation
because I guess that
as the target are kids,
we consider that they are more fantasy
or more imagination than adults.
And so they would react
positively to crazy shapes.
But in the end, if you
input it in your animation
and it's subtle enough,
it will work for any
public or any audience.
For the last step of this
polishing stage on the left leg,
there is nothing we haven't seen already
or we haven't talked about
while working on the other foot.
So now we need to polish the hips,
the chest, neck, head and then the arms
of the character.