- [Instructor] As in the previous videos,
after I polished the torso
on the center of gravity
of my character, I like
to work on the feet.
This will help us to figure
out how to polish the hips
and, later on, the upper chest.
As our character is pulling his right leg,
I want to slightly raise
the foot from the ground.
So I will duplicate one
of the keys of the Z curve
and then slightly push it up.
From there, I will move
the newly created keys
around frame 21 when the foot
gets pulled from the ground.
Then I will convert the contacting frame.
The key to vectors is
that we have a hard hit
of the foot on the ground.
This is generally my go-to when it comes
to the Z location curve of the
foot when it hits the ground.
This will ensure that
the food is accelerating
before it touch the ground.
I'm not saying that you should do this
every time your foot is going down,
but most of the time, this is true
so I generally just switch to vector
and then if I have to
revise, I revise later on.
From there, I will revise a
bit the rotation of the foot
so that the ankle gets
more aligned with the knee
and the foot does drag a
bit while it is pulled.
Basically, I want the foot
to lean toward its next pose.
From there, I will just
slightly tweak the heel motion
so that it hits the ground a little harder
when the character is shifting his weight
on top of the right foot.
I will raise it, touch
the heel before the hit,
and on the hit frame, I will
convert the curve to vector.
Finally, as an extra detail,
I will work a bit on the
toes of the right foot.
I will simply make them
drag by rotating them down
while the foot is getting up
and rotating them a bit up
while the foot is getting down.
And then I will slap them on the ground
a couple of frames later
by switching the handle to vector.
From there, remember what I've said
during the blocking stage that the feet
are always moving while on the ground?
As the leg is pulling onto the right foot,
I will slightly rotate it toward the hips.
As I'm reviewing the leg motion,
I can see that there is a little
glitch or pop on the knee.
Since the leg doesn't get fully extended,
this is not a problem due to the rig
or to the inverse kinematic mechanisms.
So I will just double check my pull target
as there must be a very
quick change in its position.
And this is the case.
I have a couple of keys
close one to the other,
with different position
for the pull target.
To fix the issue, I will simply get rid
of the in-between keys so that Brendan
will automatically interpolate
from frame 32 to frame 36.
And this will smooth the
knee motion for free.
During the hook, the right foot get pulled
but it feels like it's hitting the wall
whenever it's getting to its final pose.
Has a hard stop and I'd
like to smooth this a bit
so that I get a bit of
feeling as if the foot
was sliding on the ground.
To do so, I will simply offset the keys
from frame 45 to 47 and
then I will push the values
of the keys on frame 44.
This way, the value of the
curves on frame 44 and 47
are almost the same, but not the same.
This way it will a feel
like the foot is stopping,
but it will still move a little bit
as if it was sliding a bit on the ground.
Then I revised the rotation curve
to make the food drag toward
its previous position.
So basically I'm rotating the foot
toward its previous
position based on the speed.
The faster it moves forward,
the more it's rotating backwards.
And as the leg is pulling the foot,
I'm slightly raising the hip.
As explained when we were
polishing the torso root
of our character, we need his weight
to be supporting on one leg to be able
to easily raise the other leg.
And on frame 26, it feels like
the weight of the character
is centered between the two feet.
So I will offset the
movement of the left foot
by one frame so that the foot
start leaving its current position
once the weight is more on the right foot.
Then I want the foot to
move fast in the beginning
and then ease into its final position,
so I will scale the curve.
And then, as we did for the right foot,
I will input a new Q frame
in between the two position
and push a bit the Z location up,
so that it feels like the foot is raising
before it hits the ground.
Then, using the heel controller
and the foot rotation controller,
I will make sure that the foot opens
toward the next position,
meaning that I will make it slide
onto its inner edge.
And after it hits its contact pose,
I will make it tilt to the outside
so that it flatten on the ground.
From there, as we did for the right foot,
I will work a bit on the
toes to make them drag
so whenever the character is
moving his leg to his left,
the toes will slightly drag to the right.
If you are beginning in animation,
and this is the first time
you do this kind of exercise,
note that those details
are not that important.
They will sure bring some
interesting information
to your animation, but
you should always focus
on the broad motion on
the center of gravity,
the chest, the position of the foot,
the position of the hands.
Works on those little details
only at the very last moment.
Basically always work from
the root of the motion,
in this case, the center
gravity, to the tip of the chain,
the tip of the feet, the tip of the hands.