- [Instructor] We are
hitting the final part
of our polishing stage,
where we are going to polish the kick.
At this stage, you should
already have guessed that
we are going to start with
the torso route controller
of our character.
The first thing that might
be a bit disturbing is that
since our character has rotated
in space during the hook,
the side to side motion
of his center of gravity
is no longer driven by the X location,
but the Y location curve.
This is because our torso controller
is aligned with world space.
So as our character is rotated
by more or less 90 degrees,
its local left to right
motion is now aligned with
the world space forward
and backward motion.
As usual, you don't need
to think about all of this.
The important thing is
just to test the curve,
see how your character
behave and start from there.
As we did before,
I'm moving the center of
gravity of the character
based on the steps it's taking.
I'm pushing the center of
gravity on the left leg,
whenever the character
is freeing his right foot
to be able to pull it back.
And then we have this
micro anticipation before
the jump into the switch.
The weight of the character is
shifting upon the right leg.
And we are holding don't
pose for a couple of frames.
Then as our character is jumping,
the value of the Z curve
is raising pretty fast.
And since our character has no
more contact with the ground,
I'm making the Y curve almost linear
because our character is not able
to apply any forces to accelerate
on its X or Y axis while in the air.
When your character is airborn,
The only axis that gets a lot
of variation is the Z axis,
the up and down.
As the lens, the reason
micro anticipation,
so a little down pose over fret 74.
From there, I will give a quick polish to
the X location curve of our character.
Remember that the feet travels faster
than the center of gravity.
So when the character is stepping back,
I will hold his center of
gravity upon the left foot until
the right foot reaches its contact pose.
And then the center of gravity travels
toward the right foot
and as I did before with
the Y location curve,
during the jump, I will
make the curve more linear
by simply removing the unnecessary keys.
Once I got the satisfying arc
for the jump of the character,
I will try to push him back
and down as far as possible
to contrast with the position
whenever it's kicking.
From there, I didn't have that much work
regarding the kick itself
because it was already polished a lot
during the blocking stage, since
we have animate it on once.
So from there,
I will be mainly working on
the step back of the character.
And as usual,
I will make sure that the center
of gravity of my character
is aligned with the contacting foot
and that the weight shifts
upon the new contacting foot
as soon as the current
foot contact the ground.
So first the foot contact the ground
then the center of gravity
shift toward the foot
and to be able to move the
food, the character need
to raise his center of gravity.
So the center of gravity
will both shift to what the
supporting leg and raise
while the opposite foot
is moving to its next contact pose.
And as it reaches its next contact pose,
the center of gravity start to get down
and toward this new contact pose.
Very common mistake is to move
the center of gravity
in sync with the foot.
As explained before, the
center of gravity and
the feet don't move at the same speed
because at some point
the center of gravity
needs to be supported by the foot
and at some point the center of gravity
needs to free the foot
so that it can move.
So just try to keep this in mind,
this mechanism where the
center of gravity will shift
towards the available foot,
the ones that doesn't move anymore.
When it comes to rotation,
as soon as the character is pulling back,
I am making the torso drag in a bit
so that I will rotate it
toward its previous position.
When the character is moving back,
I will make him slightly leaning forward.
Compared to what has been outputted
from the detailed blocking,
I'm not touching the curve that much.
It's mostly about revising a bit,
the timing of the
rotation of the character,
then reworking his current poses.
And you can notice that I
generally have a very smooth curve
with some plateau whenever the
character is moving his foot.
And then the little acceleration of twist
as soon as the foot has reached
its contact pose as for the
X and Y location, whenever
the character is jumping,
he will have a hard time to
create any variation in its
rotation speed while airborn.
To be able to accelerate or
decelerate, you need to apply forces.
And if your body is not
in contact with a surface,
you can't push to create this force.
This is why my curves get small linear
on during the jump.
From there, I will walk on the rotation
as I did on the location.
I will try to push the
extreme of the anticipation
as far as possible so that
I get a very strong contrast
compared to the kick release.
So I'm leaning the character back
and twisting toward its left leg
and then I will twist the
body toward the right leg
and lean the character into the kick.
Then when the character
is coming back into idle,
I'm mainly tweaking and
smoothing the existing curve,
making sure that the body is dragging
as the foot reaches its contact pose,
and then the body catch up.
Exactly as we did for the location.
As usual, I will provide
you a slow paced time-lapse
so that you can watch it almost real time.
Note that entire of the
animation, I've given me like
five or six additional frame,
just to ease into the idle,
instead of having art stop,
I will deal with almost all
the controller this way,
creating some kind of moving
old until the last frame.
He will be easing into his final post
and that should look right.