- [Instructor] Time to move on to the arms
to finish the polishing
of the hook portion
of this animation.
As explained in the previous video,
when it comes to the arm,
I don't rely that much
on the graph editor,
but more on the motion
path drawn by the elbow
and the wrist of the character.
But I will repeat myself here,
when it come to the torso
routes or the torso in general,
using the graph editor is super important
because the position
curved for the torso route
or even defeat absence.
But when it comes to the
quaternion rotation of the arm,
it becomes a little more abstract.
I'm not saying here that
it doesn't make sense,
but since we are mixing orientation
and no longer rotation
as when using eulers,
quaternions behavior is not linear
and might change depending on the space
you are animating your character.
For example, in our case,
the arms are not following
the rotation of the torso
based on the orientation of
the character and ward space,
the behavior of the quaternion
curves of the arm may change.
Again, we don't need to know
all the technical details
of all quaternion behaves.
The curve will make sense
on portion of your animation
and your goal is to get
nice arc and nice spacing,
so just focus on this.
In time I started polishing
the right shoulder.
Everything here is about tweaking the X
and Z rotation curves,
avoiding to touch the Y
rotation curve that much,
even if you can touch it.
And make sure that the
shoulder are droppings,
so whenever the torso is twisting back,
the shoulder will be delayed forward.
When the torso is going down,
the shoulder will raise a bit.
And when the torso is going up,
the shoulder will lower a bit.
Here, I'm working on
the rotation of the arm
from the camera point of view.
Before I do so, I've
calculated the motion paths
of the wrist.
And as you can see, it
makes a jagged stroke
instead of having a nice C shape curve.
I will mix the use of the graph editor,
but also directly posing
the arm in the 3D view,
until I get the smooth arc in the 3D view.
I'm mixing the rotation
of the arm controller
with the forearm controller
whenever I need to open a
little more the forearm.
Regarding the forearm, since
it's using euler rotation,
the graph editor does
make a little more sense.
So whenever the elbow is going back,
I will bend the arm inward.
And as the elbow stop and go
back, I will open the arm.
The idea is to make the hand
drag compared to the elbow.
And after a few additional tweak,
even if I don't get a perfect result,
I get a way better arc,
and it will drastically
improve my animation.
Another thing that I have taken care of
and we might not see in this recalled,
is that the right arm is
no longer crossing the eyes
of the character when getting
back in front of the head.
It's still crossing the head,
but they've kept the arm
from being awkwardly did
by the right arm.
Regarding the arm tweaking,
you can see that here,
I'm executing exactly
the same thing as before.
I'm polishing the arc so that
it looks a little better.
So I'm tweaking the position of the arm
until I get a smoother arc.
From there, I will switch
back to the camera view
and work a bit on the forearm
during the stroke of the hook.
The idea is to make sure
that the current pose
is blending as well as
possible with the next pose.
So, I need to lead a bit
the motion of the arm
with the elbow by raising it.
And from there, I will start
to use the tweaker bone
of the arms to slightly curve
the arm into the next shape.
It's like I'm starting
to blurred the smear,
but just to touch.
The arm is starting to work,
but it's still have some
kind of natural shape.
From there, I've been
tweaking all the controllers
one by one to create the
recoil of the right arm
just after the hook hit the bag.
Just after the hook hits the back,
the right shoulder is projected back.
And then, when we've one frame
of delay, so does the elbow.
All these secondary movement
will happen upon four
to five frame.
To keep it as clean as
possible, I will do as usual.
I will start with the base of the chain
and then go further along.
So, I will start with the
shoulder and a couple of frame
after the punch contact with the bag,
I will push the shoulder backward.
And then two or three frames later,
the shoulder will get back to
some kind of normal position.
From there, I can work on
the right arm controller.
And to other point of reference,
I will track the right elbow.
For the time being, the right
elbow draws a pretty nice arc,
but what I want to try to do,
is to reduce the spacing between
those different key frames.
If from the camera view I'm able to group
those different point in
space into a single point
or making them very
close one to the other,
it will feel like the
elbow is pin in place.
And it will increase the
sensation of popping of the elbow.
This is typically the kind
of thing we want to avoid
whenever we are animating,
to a have bunch of keys gather
one on top of the other,
but in this case, I want
to have this pop on screen
so that it brings more impact.
Another little detail we can't see here,
is that both arm are
overlapping one on the other,
so it will make the
silhouette of the character
a little odder to rip.
So upon the one frame, I will
just spread a bit the arms,
so that they separate better.
At least on one frame.
It's now time to work on the left arm,
and on the first frame until the hook,
I didn't do that much.
I did find two examples, is I
did move a bit the curve here
and there are to try different timing,
but in the end, I stick
to what I add already
from the broken stage.
So, let's jump a little
further to the current hook.
To be able to track the
alchemy by the shoulder,
I've used the tweaker
bones that is attached
on the route of the arm.
Note that the camera shake
can be a bit disturbing
to be able to properly follow
the arc of the shoulder.
A little reminder, you can
temporarily disable a modifier
by simply selecting the
bones at all the modifier,
and click on the little wrench icon.
This will mute all the modifier assign
to the current transformed channel,
and make the current frame
a little easier to read.
Click the wrench icon again to
re-enable all the modifiers.
So back into my 3D scene,
I will select the tweaker
bone and calculate its arc.
So, I really want it to push the shoulder
as fast possible just
after the fist hit the bag.
And I'm working the pose from camera view.
This is some things that
will really need to be read
from the camera angle.
Then you can turn around
your character to make sure
that it doesn't goes too crazy.
And right after this overshoot,
I'm pulling the shoulder
back so that we do feel
that the bag is resisting.
This will create super odd
angle in the motion path,
just up to a frame 47,
then it will bounce back on frame 49
before recovering on frame 52.
So, I have an overshoot over one frame,
then a bounce over two frame,
and then a recover over three frames.
This will create a nice shoulder bounce
that will better sell the
impact again of the hook.
From there, we can start
working on the arm controller.
So as usual, we need to track the elbow
and see if we get clean arcs.
One thing that struck me
here is that the elbow
is traveling faster than the
shoulder on this specific part
of the animation.
So, I do need to make the
elbow or the arm controller
to drag.
In the graph editor, it means
that I will push my curve
toward the previous value.
And if I feel like I can't
reach the pose I want
using the curve, I can
simply pose by hand.
From there, I will be
tracking the hand controller.
You can also track the
elbow as same before.
And here, what I want to
do is try to avoid the hand
to overlap on the eyes of my character.
This is something to consider exclusively
from the camera view,
since this is what your
audience is going to see.
Once I fixed this little issue,
everything will be
about getting a nice arc
and respecting the hierarchy.
So in this case, making
the hand drag a bit
compared to the elbow.
At some point, creating
this dragging effect
became pretty subtle.
It's just about rotating a bit the hand
toward its previous position.
Then I'm checking the
arcs made around frame 40.
The keys are grouping a
bit in the camera view
and that's okay,
but I will see if I can
refine a bit the arc
using the forearm controller.
That's okay to have grouped
points here in space,
but if you can make a smoother arc,
that's always a little
improvement of your animation.
The keys here are bunched up
because we are into moving hold
and we don't want the forearm to overshoot
because our character is
getting very contracted.
So it's controlling its arm.
Its arm is not lose, be very
cautious we've overshoot.
When I was a younger animator,
I tend to put them everywhere.
So it looks fun and cool,
but at some point it doesn't
really translate everything
in your animation correctly.
In certain case, you want
hard stop in your emotion
or sharp angled arcs as we did
for the shoulder overshoot,
just after the impact.
Here, on this mirror
frame, I'm scaling a bit
the tweaker bones to get a
better silhouette of the arm.
On the next frame, I will
elongate a bit the forearm
using the tweaker bones.
I will also stretch the hand.
This has a couple of benefits.
First, we better see the
left eye of the character.
Second, it increased speed feeling.
So, I'm stretching the fast
moving part exactly as we did
with the bouncing ball in
the very first chapters.
Now, from there, let's get to be creative.
Instead of simply punching the bag,
we will squash the arm against the bag.
And I want to create some
kind of shockwave effect
within the forearm.
If you watch carefully
these frame by frame,
you can see the elbow getting bigger.
And then this big shape
traveling through the forearm
until it reaches the fist.
A bit as in the old school cartoon,
when a character was swallowing something,
or when someone was
shooting with a big cannon.
Again, here, there is no magical trick.
I'm just sculpting the arm of
the character frame by frame.
There is no magical
graph editor shenanigans
to get to this kind of result.
So as we did before, I will
select all the tweaker bone
and I will insert the key
frame on all the frame
of the specific section of the animation.
This way we are sure that there
won't be any interpolation
of those controller if we forget to reset
their transformed channels.
From there, frame by frame,
I will start by scaling
the elbow area,
then the middle of the forearm.
And finally, the fist.
Another thing I will do during this stage,
is to make sure that the
wrist doesn't move that much
in space, as if the
fist was hitting a wall.
And we will be able to see
this on the motion path
of the wrist controller.
As keys will be bunched
toward the area of the punch.
In this section, the camera
shake is a bit distracting.
So what I will do is that
I will exit pose mode
with our character.
I will end eyed to dolly camera rig,
I will select the aim controller
that hold the noise modifier,
and I will click the wrench
icon to disable the modifier.
This way it's a little more comfortable
to double check my animation
from the camera view.
From there, I can use
the wrist tweaker bone
and stabilize the position of the fist
in the camera view space.
If needed, we can also tweak
a bit the position of the arm.
The idea is to influence
the tip of the chain,
which is our fist, actually.
From there, I spent most of the
time trying to clean the arm
and fist trajectory so that I
have no glitches into my arcs
or into the motion path.
Especially when the character
was pulling his fist back
because we have been sculpting the poses
during the punch frame by
frame so there is no surprise.
But we haven't checked the
next step in this animation,
which is when the character
is pulling his arm back.
So here, I'm making sure
that the elbow leads
the motion backwards.
So the elbow drops first
and then the fist follow.
I will recalculate the motion paths
from the wrist tweaker controller.
And here, I want to get rid of the zigzag
in the motion path.
It will create a little
visual glitch while the fist
of our character is slowing
down as he's pulling it.
It's not a fast action.
So as explain before, when
we have a very fast action,
it's okay to have harsh
angles into our arcs,
but here, it doesn't look really good.
Exit, I will be manipulating
both the forearm controller
and the arm controller to
make sure that I don't mess
with the elbow.
I have calculated the
motion path of the elbow,
but also of the wrist.
And look at the arcs, all
I'm slowly smoothing them.
As soon as I will be done
with polishing those arcs,
I will be able to jump
in the very last segment
of the animation, which is
the switch and the kick.
For the time being,
I will let you with a
time-lapse of the full process
for the hook polishing.
And I will see you in the next video.