- We will now start to polish the hook.
And, as usual, I will
start with the center
of gravity of my character
using the torso root controller.
Our goal during the punching stage
is to better sell or communicate
what we have blocked out before.
We need to bring as much
impact into the hook
as possible and make sure
that all our body mechanics are correct.
As our character is recovering
from the right cross,
there is a weight transfer
onto the right foot.
I need to move the center
of gravity of the character
toward the right leg.
His weight will be supported
onto the right foot,
and he will be able to move the left foot
toward the next step.
So I've lowered the value
of the X location curve
until frame 31 as the character
is making a step with the left foot.
And once the left foot is in contact,
I can transfer the weight
onto the left foot.
Now, working with the Z curve,
my goal is to create a
nice arch that will go down
as the weight shifts toward the left leg.
And then the character will raise a bit.
When we watch the curve,
we can clearly see the weight shifting
toward the right foot
between frame 28 and 13,
and then transitioning onto
the left foot until frame 38.
While the character is
traveling to the left,
the value of the X location is raising,
he's lowering his center of gravity,
so the value of the Z curve is going down
and stabilize just before
this little drop here.
This drop in the Z curve over two frames
is micro-anticipation.
On the timing, my character is easing
into the anticipation on frame 42.
And then, from frame 42 to
frame 45, is releasing the hook.
Using this kind of moving hold
from frame 32 to frame 42,
we have created a long and slow
anticipation into the hook.
To break this anticipation
and bring even more contrast to the hook,
I will insert a key frame on frame 40,
and then I will push the
anticipation pause on frame 42,
meaning that I will lower
the center of gravity.
And I will also rework a
bit the Y location curve
so that the character is
pushing a bit backward.
Basically, I am pushing the
curves the opposite direction
than during the hook motion.
This little extra anticipation
over one or two frame
is called a micro-anticipation
and it's used a lot
in cartoonish animation or game animation.
From there, I will be working
on the Y location curve
of the center of gravity.
Here, I'm slightly
pushing the character back
so that the left foot is not
supporting too much weight
and can be raised and pushed
forward into the next step.
Once it hits its contact point,
I can shift the weight
onto this current foot.
Then I will ease backwards
for the moving hold
of the anticipation until frame 40.
And from frame 40 to 42, I will
push the character backward
a little faster so that we do
create the micro-anticipation
we were talking about just before.
During the hook motion,
I will tweak the curves
frame by frame.
Whenever we have a very fast motion,
we have a lot of changes into
the pose of the character.
That's pretty common to animate on ones,
meaning that you will add a key frame
or insert a key frame, every
frame, every one frame.
In this case, I'm just
watching the arcs made
by the motion path of the center
of gravity of my character
and I'm just pushing the different curve
so that it creates a nicer arc.
I have the pretty squared angle.
Here, I'm just curving it into a C shape.
From there, I will slightly
rework the X location curve
so that the character
transition into the other shoot
a little faster between
frame 46 and frame 48.
Since we are the very detailed blocking
of this parts of the animation,
the polishing stage in this case
is really about refining the arcs
and the speed of the motion
over a couple of frames.
I will repeat myself again,
but the more detailed
is your blocking, the easier and faster
will be your splining and polishing stage.
As usual, once I'm done
with the location curve,
I switch to the rotation curves.
My goal as usual is to
bring contrast to the motion
so, generally, when
you switch to splining,
your curve will be smoothed
out, which is normal.
Your job from there is to favorize
whether the previous pose or the next one.
Prior to the hook, I
will make the body drag.
So when the character is going down,
I will raise the upper part of the body
by pushing the X rotation curve down.
And then as you dive into the
anticipation for the hook,
I will push the curve up.
So, basically, I've created a drag
and then a slight over shoot,
and they will do the same
with the twisting motion.
As he goes toward the anticipation,
I will make the upper
body dragging by pushing
the Z quaternion curve down.
And then, as his weight is
shifting upon his left foot
and easing through
anticipation for the hook,
I will push the Z quaternion curve up
and they will do the same
with the Y quaternion curve.
Again, your job is not to know by heart
which curve does what, but
what the body should do.
In this case, I want to drag
while I'm switching stance.
And once I've reached the new stance,
I want to push the anticipation.
So I need to figure out
which curve does what
by just clicking them and
watching my character.
When I moved the Z quaternion curve,
I can see that the torso of
my character is twisting,
so I will work on that curve
for this specific part on the animation.
And since I want to put the
micro-anticipation as before,
between frame 14 and 42,
I will slightly erase
the Z quaternion curve,
which make the character
twisting his body.
Then we have this huge
drop into the curves
that generate the twist
the opposite direction
to perform the hook.
What I will do from there is
create a slight over shoot
by rotating the Z
quaternion curve angle down.
This way, the torso will
continue rotating a bit
just after the character hit the bag.
This will bring more weight to the motion,
while if we were to rotate
the body the opposite way,
just after the hit, it
will make a bounce motion
that will be perfect for a
light punch or a bouncing ball.
Again, since we had a
very detailed blocking,
pushing those curve is pretty easy
and I'm not really modifying their shape,
but just choosing
whether to push them down
or push them up a bit
to favorize the previews our next pose.
For example, on the X rotation curve here,
I'm pushing it down a
bit so I'm favorizing
the previous pose where the character
is leaning into the punch.
And then, as he will be walking backward,
I will push the curve a little up
so that the body is dragging forward.