- [Instructor] But once the
bag rotation master controller
and the route were done,
I've locked their transform channel
so that I was sure I would
not edit them by mistake.
From there, I will select
all the other controller
and get rid of all the keys
but the very first one.
Since the bag deformations are very fast,
it's easier for me
to rework them from scratch
than trying to work from
what we have locked before.
Whenever I want to create a pose,
I will make sure that
the previous keyframe
is currently keyed.
This way I'm sure to avoid
any undesired interpolations.
On frame 12, I will kind of sculpt the bag
as it receive the first jab
by pushing the tweaker controller,
and then a couple of frames later,
I will just console all the transforms
so that the bag recovers its shape.
Then a frame later, I will
pull a bit the controller
that was hit by the punch
so that we get a very
subtle shake feeling.
Then I will repeat the
process for the next punch.
I will kill the controller on frame 16,
the frame prior to the hit or impact.
Then on frame 17, I will sculpt the bag
by pushing the tweaker bone
but also scaling them on one axis
and then scaling them
down on the opposite axis.
I'm trying to preserve
the volume of the bag.
From there, four frames later,
I will console all the transform.
And then I will refine the shape
of the bag frame by frame.
Since the hitting frame operate is short,
it's a very fast process.
Rebuilding the whole animation
for the whole bag took
me about half an hour.
And then I've started over again
with the hook, sculpting
the pose from scratch,
using the tweaker bones.
And as soon as I was done
with the hook, guess what.
I did exactly the same
thing with the kick.
I've exclusively started working
on those deformation frames,
using the tweaker bones,
and that's pretty important
because they are very easy to use
and to sculpt those specific impacts.
Then I start working using
the blue controllers.
Those are the forward
kinematic controllers
that will allow us to
slightly bend the bag.
We could spend hours in
the graph editor polishing
those controllers but instead,
I've kept the process
as simple as possible,
keying as less frame as possible,
and letting Blender interpolate
between those frames.
So I'm selecting all the controllers
from the one just upon the impact frame
toward the tip of the bag.
Then make sure that you
are using individual origin
so that we will be able to bend
all the controller at once.
And just bend the bag
toward its previous position
as if it was dragging as less as possible.
If you bend it too much,
it won't look realistic
because it will look too smooth.
And from there, if you don't
jump into the graph editor,
that's gonna be hard to make it look good.
And as soon as I reach
the next impact frame,
I'm keying the frame before the impact
and then I'm slightly
increasing the curvature
of the bag on the impact.
Then when the hook is about to happen,
this is the time where the
bag is traveling the fastest.
So I will slightly bend it
toward again its previous position.
And this is how you create
this subtle dragging,
almost for free.
The trick is to make sure that
you manipulate all the bone
in the chain at the same time.
Since they have a parent
and child relationship,
you rotate the parent that
makes the child rotating too,
and then you apply on top
of this a bit of rotation
on the child, et cetera, et cetera.
And it generates a slight bend in the bag
that looks very natural.
The only moment where I had
to be a little more creative
was on the kick
where I've posed the bones frame by frame.
On the frame prior to the kick,
I've just made the whole bag dragging
and then on the impact,
I first made the top part of the bag
to rotate to the right behind
the leg of the character,
while the lower part of
the bag will be dragging.
So I will invert its rotation
and rotate it a big backward.
Since the bag is arriving very fast
and we're kicking it
the opposite direction,
there is a lot of deformation in the bag.
Then as it is projected by the kick,
I will slightly bend it backward
toward its previous position
to make it drag a bit.
And finally, as it hits the ground,
I bend it toward its previous direction
so that it is dragging again,
and then I'll console the
rotation a couple of frame after,
and convert all the landing keys
and the keys after to vector
so that I have a hard slap on the ground.
One final touch I've added
is that I've used the tweaker controller
to squash the bag on the ground.
In the end, it's barely noticeable
because I've kept it very subtle.
I selected all the tweaker bone,
inserted a keyframe on the key prior
to squash the back
so that I don't get any
weird interpolation.
Then I've scaled them up
a bit on the x and y-axis
and flatten it, scaling
it down on the z-axis.
And then two or three frame later,
I've consoled any scale
by pressing Alt + S.
One final detail I have revised
but I'm not sure I've captured it
is the rotation of the bag
just after the right cross.
I've slightly lowered
the level of rotation
of the bag so that it stays on screen
while we are rotating
around the character.
This is typically the kind of detail
I wouldn't have taken care
of a year ago, for example.
But it's very important
because it does improve the readability
of your animation.
But this is typically the kind of detail
that will bring you to
professional level of animation
because it shows that you
care for your audience
and make sure that they
will get everything
about your animation.