- Once the bag rotation master controller
and the root were done,
I've locked their transformed channels
so that I was sure I would
not edit them by mistake.
From there, I will select
all the other controller
and get rid of all the keys
but the very first one.
Since the bag deformations are very fast,
it's easier for me to
rework them from scratch
then trying to work from
what we have blocked before.
Whenever I want to create a
pose, I will make sure that
the previous key frame is currently keyed.
This way, I'm sure to avoid
any undesired interpolations,
On frame 12, I will kind of sculpt the bag
as it receive the first jab
by pushing the tweaker controller.
And then a couple of frames later,
I will just console all the transforms
so that the bag recovers its shape.
Then a frame later, I will pull a bit
the controller that was hit by the punch
so that we get a very
subtle shake feeling.
Then I will repeat the
process for the next punch.
I will key the controller on frame 16,
the frame prior to the hit or impact.
Then on frame 17, I will sculpt the bag
by pushing the tweaker bone,
but also scaling them on one axis
and then scaling them down
on the opposite taxis.
I'm trying to preserve
the volume of the bag.
From there, four frames later,
I will console all the transform, and then
I will refine the shape
of the bag frame-by-frame.
Since the the hitting
frames are pretty short,
it's a very fast process.
Rebuilding the whole
animation for the whole bag
took me about half an hour.
Then, I started over again with the hook,
Sculpting the pose from scratch
using the tweaker bones.
As soon as I was done with the hook,
guess what I did.
Exactly the same thing with the kick.
I've exclusively started working
on those deformation frames
using the tweaker bones.
That's pretty important because
they are very easy to use,
and to sculpt those specific impacts.
Then I start working using
the blue controllers.
Those are the forward kinematic controls
that will also us to
slightly bend the bag.
We could spend hours in the graffiti tool
polishing those controllers,
but instead I've kept the process
as simple as possible,
keying as less frames as possible
and letting blender interpolate
between those frames.
So I'm selecting all the
controllers from the one,
just upon the impact frame,
toward the tip of the bag.
Then make sure that you are
using individual origin,
so is that we will be able to bend
all the controller at once.
And just bend the bag toward
its previous position,
as if it was dragging as less as possible.
If you bend it too much,
it won't look realistic
because it will look too smooth.
From there, if you don't
jump into the graffiti tool,
that's gonna be hard to make it look good.
As soon as I reached
the next impact frame,
I'm keying the frame before the impact,
and then I'm slightly increasing
the curvature of the bag on the impact.
Then, when the hook is about to happen,
this is the time where the
bag is traveling the fastest,
so I will slightly bend it toward, again,
it's previous position.
And this is all you create
this subtle dragging, almost for free.
The trick is to make sure
that you manipulate all the bone
in the chain at the same time.
Since they have a parent
and child relationship,
you rotate the parent,
that makes the child rotating too,
and then you apply on top of this
a bit of rotation on the
child, et cetera, et cetera.
It generates a slight bend in the bags
that looks very natural.
The only moment where I had to be
a little more creative was on the kick,
where I posed the bones frame by frame.
On the frame prior to the kick,
I've just made the whole bag dragging.
And then, on the impact,
I first made the top part of the bag
to rotate the right, behind
the leg of the character
while the lower part of
the bag will be dragging.
So I will invert it's rotation
and rotate it a bit backwards.
Since the bag is arriving very fast
and we kicking it the opposite direction,
there is a lot of deformation in the bag.
Then, as it is projected by the kick,
I will slightly bend it backward
toward its previous position
to make it drag a bit.
Finally, as as it hits the ground,
I bend it toward its previous direction
so is that it is dragging again.
And then I will console the rotation
a couple of frame after
and convert all the landing keys
and the keys after to vectors
so that I have a hard slap on the ground.
One final touch I've added is that
I've used the tweaker control root
to squash the bag on the ground.
In the end, it's barely noticeable,
because I've kept it very subtle.
I selected all the tweaker bone,
inserted a key frame on the key prior
to squash the bag so that I don't get any
weird interpolation,
then I've scaled them up a bit
on the X and Y axis, and flatten it,
scaling it down on the Z axis.
Then two or three frame later,
I've consoled any scale by pressing alt+S.
One final detail I have revised,
but I'm not sure I've captured it,
is the rotation of the bag
just after the right cross.
I've slightly lowered
the level of rotation
of the bag so that it stays on screen
while we are rotating
around the character.
This is typically the kind of detail
I wouldn't have taken care of a year ago,
for example, but it's
very important because
it does improve the
readability of your animation.
This is typically the kind of detail
that will bring you to a
professional level of animation,
because it shows that you
care for your audience,
and make sure that they will get
everything about your animation.