- [Instructor] Now that the
torso root of our character
and the feet are polished,
we can start polishing the
whole chain of the torso,
the hips, the chest, neck and head.
As usual, I will start
with the hips rotation.
And as explained in the
previous animation chunk,
I'm mainly following
the motion of the feet
to figure out the rotation of the hips.
Also since we add a
very detailed blocking,
generally the stage is pretty fast
as we mostly have to smooth
out the motion of the hips
based on what is already blocked.
For example, here I'm slightly reducing
the tilting of the hips
so that they are more facing the character
and facing the orientation
of the center of gravity,
because this is the transition motion
and our character is
settling just after the hook.
Then I'm reworking the step back.
So I make sure that the character
hips don't tilt too much
and it looks too feminine.
I'm also making sure that the hips twist
follow the right leg.
But remember that the
hips are pulling the legs
that are not in contact with the ground
while the supporting leg
are pushing on the hips.
This should gives you a broad idea
on how to tilt the hips.
The character is pushing for the jump,
I make sure that the bit
is oriented backward.
The hips are oriented
forward towards the groin
during the anticipation
and oriented backward toward the bit
during the pushing pose.
Then I will fix the overall
orientation of the hips
during the jump as they look delayed here.
Whenever I'm working on the hips,
it's often a matter of feeling
whether the pose looks right or not,
that's pretty hard to explain.
Hopefully when you're watching this video,
you can see the improvement
whenever I'm moving a key
over the different rotation axis.
One part that definitely
needed some refinement
is the kicking part.
As I have initially blocked
a very odd recoil of the hips
and it generates a very odd visual glitch.
You can see the difference of rotation
between frame 79 and frame 80.
There is a big jump in the
value of the Z quaternion curve.
And so what I've decided
is to average the value
over frame 80 and switch on frame 81.
Having this big change of value
over two frames instead of one
really improved the animation in the end.
From there, here you can see the hips
are really twisted backward,
pulling the left leg.
And then it was just about
tweaking the existing curve
as we had no extreme motion,
making sure that the hips tilt
up upon the supporting leg,
making sure that the
twisting follows the foot
that was in error whenever the
character is stepping back.
The chest was a little more
interesting to work on.
Not that it is more
important than the hips,
but visually it creates more variation
in the shape of the character.
And during this polishing stage,
I will be able to push even more
the pose of the anticipation of the kick
and the kick itself.
On the initial part of this
chunk, just after the hook,
I'm tracking the axis
from the base of the neck,
and I will mainly make the chest drag
based on the center of gravity motion.
So whenever the center
of gravity is moving up,
I will slightly lean
the character forward.
Whenever the center of gravity
is twisting to the right,
I will slightly twist
the chest to the left
so that there is a bit of
delay in the chest motion
compared to the center of
gravity and the leading hips.
Even when the character
is initiating the jump,
we keep the same mechanism.
If the body is going up,
I will slightly lean
the character forward.
But then when the character
is airborne and about
to land just before throwing the kick,
the character starts to use
his chest for the anticipation
to load energy.
So I will make sure that it
twists as far as possible,
the opposite direction
than the kick release,
as if the shoulder were going
to pull the hips forward.
So from the camera view,
I just make sure that I
push the line of faction
as far as possible,
tilting the chest to the right
and bending the character
backward as far as possible.
Then the whole chest will
be moving toward the kick
as if the character was
trying to give a headbutt
to another bag that is side
to side with the current bag.
So in the end, if you
watch my current curve,
it's pretty noisy.
There is a lot of ups and downs.
And at the end of the polishing
stage of this very part,
you will see that I have
a way smoother curve.
And it does show in the arc
of the base of the neck,
which is pretty nice.
Then I will break a bit the smoothness
of the X rotation curve around frame 82
to create the recoil
effect after the kick.
But while the character was
really leaning into the kick
now that he has lost momentum,
he needed to get
straighter to find balance.
And once I've recovered this balance
during these short transitions
between frame 82 and 85,
it's just about making
the chest drag a bit
while the character is
taking a few step backwards.
Then to improve the animation,
what I did is that I've modified
the location of the chest
during the kick.
The idea was to create some chest shake
while the character was hitting the bag.
So I will be pushing the chest forward
just after the impact on frame 79
and a couple of frame later,
I will pull the chest backward
until it recovers around frame 85.
This will create a quick
back and forth motion
as if the torso was shaking
because of the impact of the kick.
This is pretty similar to
what we did to the shoulders
and the head of the character
during the hook motion.
(swooshing)
Once I'm done with the chest,
I always go further in the chain.
So I will be working on the neck
as we did for the
previous animation chunk.
As usual, I will be mostly
making the head drag.
Since the neck is a tride of the chest,
quaternion rotation behavior
is pretty close to
euler rotation behavior.
So from the side view,
I will be working on
the X rotation channel.
I will make sure to track my axis
using the base of the neck.
And then when the character is going down,
I will slightly raise the neck.
And when the character is pushing up,
I will make sure that
the neck is going down.
This is something we have already done
during the blocking stage.
So here I'm just revising
some of the poses
that may not be clean.
Like this little drop on the
y-axis that doesn't make sense
since the character is moving
pretty linearly to the side.
Polishing the neck is mostly about
the X and Y rotation curve
as they drive the tilting
and leaning of the head.
While my wheel is to make the head drag,
the polishing stage is
also the opportunity
to fix some of the poses.
And my go-to for this
is to watch my character
and make sure that the head
doesn't feel too uncomfortable.
I'm just watching the relationship
between the chest and the neck.
And whenever the pose feels
uncomfortable, I fix it.
(swooshing)
Regarding the head,
I haven't anything to add that
we haven't covered already.
For all the transition
between the punches,
the steps or any motion
that is not that fast,
I will make the head slightly
dragging as we did before.
I will jump directly
to the kicking moment.
And at this stage of the animation,
my goal is not to make
the head drag that much
because the character is
focusing on the target,
and it might not be as relaxed
as in between the different punches.
Your goal here is to make
sure that the character
is watching the target
from the camera angle,
or at least that we feel like
he's watching the target.
So, I'm orientating the head
so that it's looking at the same point
during the whole kick.
Once I'm done with the rotation,
I will play with the location of the head
to improve the impact of the kick.
First, I track the head
tweaker on the top of the head.
And my goal is to clean the
arc from the camera view,
for example, on frame 78,
you can see that the
arc is going a bit down
and then going up.
So I will raise the head so
that I get a cleaner arc,
and then after impact I
will push the head forward.
And after I've pushed the head forward,
because of the momentum of
the kicks that just stop
so the head is continuing
to travel forward.
I will try to bunch a bit
the different keys here,
this way just after the kick contact,
the head will stabilize a
bit from the camera view
and we will be able to see it clearly.
And it will improve the
recoil feeling of the kick.
Finally, I will add a bit
of stretching in the head
when it's moving down super fast
using the top head tweaker,
only working on the Z location
axis of the head tweaker.
And just after the stretch,
I will squash it a little bit
a couple of frames later
before it settles again two frames later.