- Hi, everyone.
In this video, I will
show you how to create
a real time animated
sword trail in blender.
Creating this effect is
a very simple process
that we will learn through two main steps.
First, the creation of
the texture and shader,
and then the rigging and
animation of the trail.
Only the sword motion needs to be animated
and we'll generate the trail affixed
based on this motion.
Let's get started.
Creating the trail mesh
will be super easy.
I already have my sword object,
and I will simply add a plane.
I will rotate it towards front
view and apply the rotation
and scale pressing control A.
I will then move it in object mode
so that it matches more
or less my sword shape.
Then in edit mode,
I will make it slightly taller
so that it covers the blade.
I advise you to make it
slightly taller than the blade
because a part of it will be masked.
The cool thing is that by default,
when you add the plane in
blender, it's already unwrapped.
So we are done creating our UVs.
In edit mode, I will press control R
to create two loop kits.
I think going above is a bit overkill,
so two loop cut is way
enough to get a small trail.
And the cool thing is
that the UVs are updated.
Then we need to create a new material,
and since I wanted to be transparent
in the material setting, I
will switch it to alpha blend.
I don't want it to emit any shadow,
so then I will switch
the shadow mode to none,
and we will keep the back
face cooling disabled,
because if you enable it,
then the shader will
show only on one side.
We can go to the next step
and create our first mask.
I'm working with blender 292,
but I guess 2.9 will walk the same.
In my 3D view port I've
pressed control tab,
and I will switch to texture paint mode.
In the texture slot I will
add a new base color texture
and set it to black.
I will keep it at 1 K resolution.
I will then go into the image
editor and switch to paint.
In the lowest part of
the painting tool panels,
I will open the tiling
option and enable X and Y.
Then I can open my texture library
and select the sword train based color.
With the tiling option,
I can now paint seamless textures.
You may have to experiment a bit,
but the method to paint
the flame is very simple.
I start by painting random,
broad shapes with the standard brush,
using pressure sensitivity
for both the radius
and the strength.
Don't try to paint any flame shape yet,
just paint slightly curved
or reasonable lines.
Then using the finger tool,
just push a bit the black
into the white and the
white into the black.
So the trick here to get a
good result is just to change
the size of your brush
often pressing the F key.
This is a pretty simple process,
but if you fail at first,
just restart again.
This is the first time
I'm using this method,
and it took me two trials
to get to a good result.
Keep it loose,
you don't need to add a lot of detail
because this is going to be moving
so we won't see it clearly.
I will save it sword trail mask zero one.
From there, let's open the shader editor.
We can get rid of the principle BSDF.
And with my texture selected,
I will press control T
to create a texture setup
using the node wrangler addon.
As explained in the beginning,
we will create a transparent material,
so we need a mixed shader
to mix a transparent shader
and an emission shader.
We will plug the transparent
shader in the first slot
and the emission shader
in the second slot.
Make sure you are using
the UV as coordinate,
and control shift to click the texture.
We can see our fire mask texture.
If you don't see it,
make sure you are in
loop dev shading mode.
Let's plug our texture into
the mixed shader as a factor
and control shift to
click the mixed shader.
Now, I like to add a bit of distortion
into my flame texture.
You can revise the tiling
and size of the pattern
using the scale input.
Don't choose the Z scale
because the UVs are two dimensional.
To create the distortion,
we will simply add a noise texture.
If we control shift to
clique the mapping node,
you will be able to
see the UV coordinates.
It's a simple gradient
mixing red and green color.
The green is the y-axis,
the red is the x-axis.
Since our plane is rotated,
they might not be aligned with word space,
but we don't care.
The only thing we have to
care is that our noise texture
is also made of color, so if
we mix those two together,
the red and green color of
our noise will influence
the coordinates of the flame.
So here, the distortion
is kind of overkill,
but as I reduced the factor,
I will get less distortion.
The scale of the noise
is also pretty important.
We want to have a broad noise,
so a scale of two is way enough.
And if we now play with the X
location of our flame texture,
it will kind of flow on the plane.
So you have the base principle on all.
We will create the effect.
I can now regroup my notes
and move on to the second texture.
And don't worry if you
don't get every single node
we are creating, at the end of the video,
I will show you the full node setup.
You can make a screenshot and
reproduce it at your site.
I will use the same process
to create the second mask.
In the 3D view, press control tab,
to switch to texture paint mode,
go into the texture slot,
press the plus icon,
and create a new texture,
same size as before and still
with a black background.
The idea is to mask
the edges of our plane.
We don't need to input as much
detail as on the first mask,
we just need a big, round
gradient that will influence
the opacity of our flame.
Just make sure that the
outer edges are pure black.
When you are done use a very large brush
with a very low strength to
paint the tip of the flame.
It will lower it's opacity
and we will have nice
and smooth gradients.
I will create exactly the same note setup
as for the first texture.
The only difference is that
I will keep the scale at one,
because we don't want this mask to tile.
Then I've used a couple of layout
to reroute items to make my
shader editor a little cleaner.
Then we can use a colored mix,
RGB node to mix both of our
mask and set the blend mode
to multiply.
I will push the mixing value to one,
and we don't care if you
plug the first texture
in the first slot or the second.
After that, we will add
a couple of new nodes,
the convertor color ramp
to be able to play with the
contrast of our texture.
We will use it to drive the
color of our emission shader,
and I will push the emission shader to 10,
then in the render option, I
will enable the bloom option.
Then I will add the convertor map range
before the color ramp,
this will allow us to fine
tweak our gradient if needed.
Then we can edit the
gradient of our color ramp
from black and white to
a cool looking fire tone.
So now instead of animating both location
of both mapping node, I
like to use only one value.
So I will use a converter combined XYZ,
and then I will add an input value node.
If I plugged this input value node
in the X value of the combined XYZ,
then it's like moving the X value directly
into the mapping node.
But then I can duplicate
this combined XYZ,
add math node in between, set
this math node to multiply
so that when I move my first value,
it will modify both X
location of both mapping node,
but not with the same rate,
this way we will have
a difference of speed
for both noises tiling,
and it will look a little
more random and natural
than if we add both noise
running at the same speed.
Now to animate our fire texture,
we just need to add a key
frame on our tiling value.
Hovering upon the value
I will press the I key.
With our key frame created
and our tiling node selected,
I will open the graph editor,
move the key frame created on
frame zero by pressing GNX,
and I will duplicate this
frame by pressing shift D
and move it on frame 10,
this way I have two key
frames for the tagging value.
I will switch the handle to
vector by pressing the V key,
and now I have a linear interpolation
between those two keys.
When I move the second key down,
I can see my tiling texture
moving the right way.
So I will push it down a bit,
then select both key and press shift E
and select linear extrapolation.
Now our curve will be extrapolated
and we can play our animation infinitely.
Our animated fire shader is now done.
In the UV editor, you
can push and pull a bit
the middle loop cuts from left to right,
to get a bit more
distortion or acceleration
and deceleration of the flames.
You can also improve
the distortion pattern,
switching the noise texture from 3D to 4D.
It will add a new input
to the noise texture node
called W which is an evolution over time.
So you can then use the
distortion value node
that we have animated.
Use the Mac node to change its
value and plug it in between.
Let's now create our rig.
It will be super simple.
I will snap the cursor to my sword,
I will press shift A and add an armature.
I will give everything a relevant name,
and then I will switch
the object to display,
to be wireframe so that it
will be easier to manipulate.
Then they will go back into
object mode, select our plane,
select the first vertex
and snap the cursor to it.
I will go back into
edit mode on my armature
and add a new bone.
I will scale it up just
for visual purpose,
it doesn't matter if you scale the bone,
you don't need to scale it.
We will then duplicate this
bone free time and snap it
to each loop cut we have
created on the mesh,
so you can enable the snapping
mode and switch to vertices.
When I'm done as usual, I will
give each bone a proper name.
The first bone on the line
will be the trail route.
Back in object mode,
I've selected the sword,
then the armature,
I will switch to pause
mode and press control P
to parent the sword to the sword bone,
this way no need to do
any vertex painting,
the sword is parented to this bone,
then in edit mode on the armature,
I will parent the trailer
route to the sword bone.
Then I will switch back to object mode,
select my trailer mesh,
then the armature, press control P
and use with empty groups.
It does created a bone group
for each bone on our trail mesh
and going into edit mode,
we can assign each vertex
group row of each loop cut
to the corresponding bone.
Once done, each bone will be
moving one edge of our plane,
and you have just finished
the rig, so it's very simple.
Now to make it easier to read,
what I will do is that
I will reduce the size
of each bone.
Reducing the size of
each bone in edit mode
won't affect any of the
deformation we just created,
and it will make them easier to identify.
We can then add a subdivision
modifier to our mesh
and move it upon the armature modifier.
And instead of using the cat
wheel clock interpolation
for the subdivision modifier,
we will use the simple subdivision method
so that you can then apply
the subdivision modifier
and export your mesh if you
want to in any game engine.
By placing the subdivision modify first,
we will get a smooth deformation,
and if you want,
you can apply the subdivision modifier,
and your mesh is ready to be
exported to a game engine,
but I advise you to keep
the subdivision modifier
without applying it,
because there are option to
apply it during the export.
For the demonstration,
I will switch the bone display to be bone,
and that will scale them so
that it's easier to select them
and identify them.
Again, this has no
influence on the deformation
or on the rig functionalities.
So now we are done for
this step of the rigging,
we just need to animate the sword.
So I've hidden the trail
effects, I've hidden
all the bone but the sword bone,
and I've made a rapid
animation of the sword.
Time to see our little trick
that will generate the trail effect.
The process is super simple,
once you've finished your animation,
select the trail route bone,
then trade one,
press control shift to see
and add a copy transformation,
and do it for each bone.
It will collapse the trail
since every bone will be
one on top of each other,
so the vertices of our trail
will be one on top of each other.
So nothing will happen
when we play the animation.
But the trick is to bake the animation
and offset it in time.
So we'll select the free constraint bone,
press F3, search for bake
and choose bake action.
We will select only selected
visual king clear constraint
and overwrite current action.
Boom! All the bones have
lost their constraint,
but now we can move them.
But now I will select all
the key frames of the bone,
but the first key frame,
and I will offset them by one frame.
G ID is two offset trail one by one frame,
trail two by two frame and
trail three by three frame.
And we keep the first
frame to avoid any popping.
Now, each bone is playing
the same animation,
but with a bit of delay
compared to the blade motion.
And voila, we got our effect.
But when the blade is rotating backward,
we get a strange distortion.
To fix this issue, we just
need to select our trail mesh
and under the armature
modifier, use preserve volume.
Then if you want to fine
tweak the trail size,
you can switch from auto
snap to no auto snap
in the key frames snapping menu.
Now you can move your key
frame as smooth as you want,
or with the interval you want
and make the trail shorter,
bigger, whatever you want.
And if you need to create another effect,
just create a new animation,
create the copy transformed, constraint,
peg the animation, and
offset it, and you're done.
There other ways to create
this kind of effect in unity,
but this method is totally
relevant and reliable,
and you can preview it or
use it directly in blender.
So that's very cool to have
your preview in blender
and the same thing in your game engine.
This is the end of the video,
but before we wrap up,
a bit of self promotion.
This tutorial is sponsored by myself.
If you want to learn all
my rigging techniques,
or if you want to create
stylized character from scratch,
you will find all you
need on my Gameroad page.
Use the code p2design and
get 10% on whatever product
you want.
This is the end of this
video, I hope you've liked it.
Please like subscribe and share
if you want to support me,
and don't hesitate to ask
for tutorial specific topics
in the comments section,
I will try my best to answer your question
through new tutorials video.
See you.
(upbeat music)