(character grunting)
(bag banging)
- Hi, everyone. Pierrick from P2design.
In this video, I will show you
how you can use shape shape keys
to create stylized effect
on your animated character in Blender.
(logo whooshing)
(lively music)
This video is a free sample
of one of the 150 videos
that are going to be included
in my new course, Alive!
This Blender animation course
is gonna be available on next week,
the 13th of August.
Stay tuned and check the link
in the description below.
In this video, I will show you in detail
how to create shape keys
and how to apply them to
your animated character.
Let's get started.
Shape keys allows you to deform an object
into another shape.
They are also known as
morph target or Blendshapes
in Maya or ZBrush, for example.
Shape keys are often used
to create facial expression
for your character
that can be triggered later on.
It's great to create
advanced facial expression
or quick test for your character.
Then the rigger can create controllers
so that you can trigger
those shape keys at will
in your animation.
(screen whooshing)
Shape keys are a modification
or a transformation of the mesh.
So you will be able to
find the Shape Keys panel
into the mesh data of your object.
To create a shape key,
we simply need to click the plus icon
on the right of the panel.
The first shape key
to be created will be
automatically named basis.
It's some kind of snapshot
of the current position of each vertices
in your mesh.
Whenever we jump into edit mode
with a vertex selected,
in the properties panel,
we can see the current
location of this vertex.
The basis shape key
will record the position
of each vertex for our mesh.
And this specific basis shape key
is going to be the point of reference
for the next shape key.
It's a bit like the rest
pose for a character rig.
From there, we can
create another shape key
by clicking the plus button,
and now render is no longer
naming the shape key basis
but key number one.
Now, to be able to animate this shape key,
we need to create a first deformation.
You need to be in edit mode
and the most important thing
is to make sure that the
key is currently selected.
To select it, you just
need to left click it
and it will be highlighted.
From there, I can move one
of the vertices of my mesh.
You can move as many vertices as you want.
And as soon as I will press
Tab to exit edit mode,
my mesh will return to the shape it had
on the basis shape key.
From there, I can activate my shape key
by simply increasing the
value of key number one
from zero to one.
Blender will automatically
interpolate the shape key.
One being the shape key
we have currently built,
zero being the basis.
To understand how shape keys work,
I will create a new shape key.
Then I will enter edit mode
and I will rotate my whole character.
Note that you can rename your shape keys
as any other data in Blender
by simply double clicking its name.
As we have rotated our object in edit mode
by triggering the shape key,
I'm expecting it to rotate in space,
exactly as I'm doing here in object mode.
I'm going back onto my model,
and I will trigger the shape key.
What we learn here is that it seems
that my object is getting scaled
while I'm triggering the shape key.
But this is not the case.
This is currently how shape keys work.
And to better understand it,
I've tracked one of the vertices,
parenting a small sphere to this vertex.
If you carefully focus on this vertex,
you will see that it moves
in a straight line in space.
And this is because a vertex
only have location coordinates,
and Blender will simply move each vertices
in a straight line from
their original basis position
toward the keyframe position
over the keyframe value
that goes from zero to one.
So you can't perform a proper
rotation using shape key.
You can only perform translation
of individual vertices.
So even if the final output
looks a bit like a rotation,
this is not a rotation.
Each vertex is moving in a linear fashion
from its current basis position
to the shape key position.
Now, to better understand
shape keys extrapolation
and their behavior,
I have created this arrow shape
and I will create the basis shape key,
and a first key.
From there, I will jump into edit mode,
and with my shape key number one selected,
I will move by one Blender
unit the top vertices
of the arrow.
Now, when I trigger my shape key,
those vertices will
move in a linear fashion
by one Blender unit on the z-axis.
But since the shape key
occurs at the mesh data level,
I can rotate my data container,
my object and trigger the shape key,
and the shape key will behave as expected.
Now, if we have a closer look
to our shape key's information,
we have a minimum range
and a maximum range.
This will allow us to whether clamp
or increase the interpolation range
of the shape key.
If I clomp the maximum value to 0.5,
I won't be able to go further.
If I now allow a maximum value of two,
the vertices of the arrow's head
will move two time further
away in a linear fashion.
If I allow a negative minimum range,
I will be able to extrapolate
the current shape key backward
or negatively, and the vertices
will just move the opposite direction.
You can combine as many
shape keys as you want,
and this is how we generally create
complex facial expression.
I have created a couple
of additional shape keys,
and now I can trigger all the shape keys
at the same time or
combine different values.
The coordinate modification
of each vertices
will be added one on
top of each other based
on the factor of each shape key.
If you need to edit your mesh,
make sure that you have
selected the basis shape key
or you will be editing
the current shape key,
not the basis.
We can use vertex group
to limit the influence of a shape key.
In the vertex group panel,
I will create a new group,
and I will assign at 100%
the tip of the arrow,
and with a value of 50%,
the pace of the arrow.
Now, if I assign this vertex group
to the first shape key
by selecting it in the vertex group slot,
and I now trigger the shape key,
you can see that the tip of the arrow
is moving at its full range,
while the other vertices only move by 50%
of their range.
If I now select one of the vertex
and I exclude it by removing
it from the vertex group,
it will no longer move.
The vertex group value
directly influence the almond
of the shape key motion
that will be applied
to each vertex.
Finally, you can use other
shape keys as a basis.
This way, you can create
complex transformation
by changing the point of reference.
So let's now have a
look on what we could do
with those shape keys onto
our current animation.
I will hide the background
and affixes collection
so that we have a clearer viewport.
And I will directly select
my character object.
But since the character
was linked into this scene,
I can't modify any of the mesh data.
To be able to edit those data,
I need to make the mesh local
and also the object of
the character local.
With both the container
and its data local,
I can now add a new shape key.
Since we will directly be
editing our character model,
I can hide the rig,
and I will scrub through the animation,
and I will try to spot the moment
where the character is moving very fast,
like this hook motion, for example.
I've already created smears using the rig
but now I can add extra
details using shape keys.
Clicking the plus button,
I will add a new shape key.
I will call it Hook01
and I will jump into edit mode,
pressing the Tab key.
To be able to see your
character posed in edit mode,
make sure to enable all the display option
in the armature modifier.
From there, with my shape key selected,
I can start editing my character.
The process is simply to pull some
of the vertices of the character
towards its previous position
as if part of his mesh was dragging
during this quick motion.
I need to disable the x
symmetry while in edit mode,
and now I can pull some
of the vertices back,
and start to create my effect.
The important thing
is that those effects will be seen
from the camera view.
So it's important to make them
work from the camera view.
You can sure edit your mesh
from any point of view you want,
but make sure that it does look good
from your camera point of view
as it is what is going to be rendered.
If you want to create broader shapes
or move multiple vertices at once,
you can enable the editing falloff.
Once you are done with
your first shape key,
you can exit edit mode
and trigger it by changing its value.
As seen in chapter two,
shape keys, as most Blender data,
can be keyed by pressing
i over the keyframe value.
Then I can edit this value whenever I want
over my animation.
This will activate or
deactivate the current shape key
or if you change the value
over multiple frames,
Blender will interpolate
the value of the shape keys.
For example, in the previous frame,
I can add a bit of the shape key
to initiate this transformation
and set it to zero on the previous key.
Once you're happy with your first effect,
you can add more of them.
When working on a shot like that,
this is going to be the final
touch, the final effect.
So I advise you to create
multiple shape keys.
For example, here I want
to add a few details
on the arm too.
I will create a dedicated shape key
instead of adding it on the
same shape key as before.
This way, it's gonna be easier for me
to edit whether the shape key of the arm
or the head delay one
compared to the other
or simply remove it without destroying
what I've done for the head.
Or you will also be able
to show a different version
to your art director, for example.
In my case, I've also
created the shape key
during the kick impact
to try to blend with the previous shape.
This kind of effect, on
top of the smear effect,
will fake motion blur
and will help your audience
to better read your animation.
And as explained in the previous video,
whatever you do to improve the readability
of your animation will
take it to the next level.
(character grunting)
(bag banging)